<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.1d3 20150301//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:ali="http://www.niso.org/schemas/ali/1.0" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v3.0 20080202//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing3.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 3.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, CA USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">4391716</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">25856077</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-14-20592</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Chemosensory Gene Families in Adult Antennae of <italic>Anomala corpulenta</italic> Motschulsky (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Rutelinae)</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Candidate Chemosensory Genes in <italic>Anomala corpulenta</italic></alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Xiao</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author" equal-contrib="yes"><name><surname>Ju</surname><given-names>Qian</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jie</surname><given-names>Wencai</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>Fei</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff002"><sup>2</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Jiang</surname><given-names>Xiaojing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>Jingjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Qu</surname><given-names>Mingjing</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff001"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref rid="cor001" ref-type="corresp">*</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff001"><label>1</label><addr-line>Shandong Peanut Research Institute, Fushan Road 126, Licang District, Qingdao City, Shandong 266100, China</addr-line></aff><aff id="aff002"><label>2</label><addr-line>Ministry of Education, Key Laboratory of Integrated Management of Crop Diseases and Pests, College of Plant Protection, Nanjing Agricultural University, Nanjing 210095, China</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Dickens</surname><given-names>Joseph Clifton</given-names></name><role>Academic Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1"><addr-line>United States Department of Agriculture, Beltsville Agricultural Research Center, UNITED STATES</addr-line></aff><author-notes><fn fn-type="conflict" id="coi001"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="con" id="contrib001"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: XL MJQ. Performed the experiments: QJ. Analyzed the data: WCJ FL XL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: XJJ JJH. Wrote the paper: XL MJQ.</p></fn><corresp id="cor001">* E-mail: <email>13455277580@163.com</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>9</day><month>4</month><year>2015</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2015</year></pub-date><volume>10</volume><issue>4</issue><elocation-id>e0121504</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>8</day><month>5</month><year>2014</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>20</day><month>1</month><year>2015</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-year>2015</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Li et al</copyright-holder><license xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/"><license-p>This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri content-type="pdf" xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="pone.0121504.pdf"/><abstract><sec id="sec001"><title>Background</title><p>The metallic green beetle, <italic>Anomala corpulenta</italic> (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Rutelinae), is a destructive pest in agriculture and horticulture throughout Asia, including China. Olfaction plays a crucial role in the survival and reproduction of A. corpulenta. As a non-model species, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> is poorly understood, and information regarding the molecular mechanisms underlying olfaction in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and other scarab species is scant.</p></sec><sec id="sec002"><title>Methodology/Principle Findings</title><p>We assembled separate antennal transcriptome for male and female <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> using Illumina sequencing technology. The relative abundance of transcripts with gene ontology annotations, including those related to olfaction in males and females was highly similar. Transcripts encoding 15 putative odorant binding proteins, five chemosensory proteins, one sensory neuron membrane protein, 43 odorant receptors, eight gustatory receptors, and five ionotropic receptors were identified. The sequences of all of these chemosensory-related transcripts were confirmed using reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR), and direct DNA sequencing. The expression patterns of 54 putative chemosensory genes were analyzed using quantitative real time RT-PCR (qRT-PCR). Antenna-specific expression was detected for many of these genes, suggesting that they may have important functions in semiochemical detection.</p></sec><sec id="sec003"><title>Conclusions</title><p>The identification of a large number of chemosensory proteins provides a major resource for the study of the molecular mechanism of odorant detection in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and its chemical ecology. The genes identified, especially those that were expressed at high levels in the antennae may represent novel molecular targets for the development of population control strategies based on the manipulation of chemoreception-driven behaviors.</p></sec></abstract><funding-group><funding-statement>This study was supported by awards and grants from the China Agriculture Research System (CARS-14); the Shandong Foundation for Outstanding Young Scientists (BS2010NY022); the Agriculture Science Technology Achievement Transformation Fund (2013GB2C620547); and the Open Fund Project of the Key Laboratory of Crop Comprehensive Management of Biological Disasters, Ministry of Education, Nanjing Agricultural University (IMCDP201304). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group><counts><fig-count count="6"/><table-count count="2"/><page-count count="22"/></counts><custom-meta-group><custom-meta id="data-availability"><meta-name>Data Availability</meta-name><meta-value>All the Illumina sequencing data are available from the SRA database(accession numbers SRR1503480 and SRR1503444)</meta-value></custom-meta></custom-meta-group></article-meta><notes><title>Data Availability</title><p>All the Illumina sequencing data are available from the SRA database(accession numbers SRR1503480 and SRR1503444)</p></notes></front><body><sec sec-type="intro" id="sec004"><title>Introduction</title><p>Chemoreception plays a crucial role in many insect behaviors, such as those related to identifying suitable hosts, mates, predators, and oviposition sites [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref001" ref-type="bibr">1</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref002" ref-type="bibr">2</xref>]. Volatile chemical signals are detected by olfactory sensory neurons (OSNs). OSNs are primarily found on the antennal sensilla of insects and, to a lesser degree, on the maxillary palps [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>]. Proteins that play crucial roles in chemoreception include odorant binding proteins (OBPs), chemosensory proteins (CSPs), sensory neuron membrane proteins (SNMPs), olfactory receptors (ORs), gustatory receptors (GRs), and ionotropic receptors (IRs) [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref004" ref-type="bibr">4</xref>].</p><p>In insects, the first step in the recognition of chemical signals involves OBPs and CSPs, which are abundant in the lymph of antennal sensilla [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref005" ref-type="bibr">5</xref>]. OBPs are small, water-soluble proteins composed of approximately 130 amino acids that typically contain six conserved cysteine residues [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref006" ref-type="bibr">6</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref008" ref-type="bibr">8</xref>]. Minus-C OBPs lack the second and fifth cysteine residues, and plus-C OBPs contain three additional conserved cysteines and one conserved proline [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref009" ref-type="bibr">9</xref>]. It is presumably that OBPs act as molecular carriers of hydrophobic signaling molecules that are taken into the antennae or other sensory organs from the external environment. OBPs transport these molecules through the aqueous space, and deliver them to chemoreceptor proteins located on the membranes of OSNs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref010" ref-type="bibr">10</xref>].</p><p>CSPs belong to a smaller, more conserved protein family that is characterized by four conserved cysteines that form two disulphide bonds [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref011" ref-type="bibr">11</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref012" ref-type="bibr">12</xref>]. Although the molecular functions of CSPs remain poorly understood, it has been suggested that they are involved in semiochemical detection [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref013" ref-type="bibr">13</xref>], and participate in some nonchemosensory functions [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref014" ref-type="bibr">14</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>]. Initially identified in sex-pheromone-specific OSNs of lepidopterans, SNMPs are CD36-like proteins with two transmembrane domains [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>] that are thought to act as cofactors for odorant receptors in pheromone detection [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref017" ref-type="bibr">17</xref>].</p><p>Insect chemoreceptors consist of three major protein families, the ORs, GRs, and IRs, whose activation generates an electrical signal that is transmitted to the brain [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. The ORs are receptor proteins on the dendritic membrane surface of OSNs that are composed of approximately 400 amino acids, and contain seven transmembrane domains that form binding sites for odorant molecules [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref003" ref-type="bibr">3</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref020" ref-type="bibr">20</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>]. Insect olfactory neurons express odorant-specific ORs and a highly conserved coreceptor, known as Orco whose ortholog in <italic>Drosophila</italic> is Or83b. The Orco is required for olfactory functions and the localization of specific ORs, and the Orco and specific OR form a heterodimer that acts as an ion channel [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref022" ref-type="bibr">22</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref023" ref-type="bibr">23</xref>]. Although GRs are members of the same receptor superfamily as ORs, GRs are primarily expressed in gustatory sensory neurons (GSNs) of gustatory organs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. The IRs are members of the iGluR-related olfactory receptor family that was recently identified in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, and are expressed in distinct olfactory neurons that do not express ORs or GRs, suggesting that they function through molecular mechanisms that differ from those of ORs and GRs. Previous studies have shown that IRs are expressed in coeloconic OSNs, and may function in the detection of acids and ammonia [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>].</p><p>Transcriptomes based on next-generation sequencing data have been used to identify chemosensory genes in species for which a complete genomic sequence databases have been unavailable. Compared to conventional homology cloning methods, which are difficult to apply to ORs because of the low levels (20%&#x02013;40%) of sequence identity shared among them, these high throughput transcriptomic approaches are more efficient for large-scale gene discovery, especially with regard to the identification of highly diverse gene families [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref027" ref-type="bibr">27</xref>]. Transcriptomes assembled from high-throughput sequencing data have been used to identify protein families involved in chemoreception in many lepidopterans [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>], whereas such proteins have been identified in only four species of the order Coleoptera [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>].</p><p>The scarab beetle, <italic>Anomala corpulenta</italic> Motschulsky, is a major insect pest in agriculture and horticulture throughout the Asian continent, including China [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref035" ref-type="bibr">35</xref>]. The adults destroy the leaves of a broad range of agriculturally important host plants and the leaves and buds of various trees. The larvae of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> damage the subterranean parts of peanuts, wheat, soybeans, and other crops, causing significant economic losses. Because of their ecological and economic importance, researchers have investigated various approaches to control <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. However, the soil-dwelling habits of the larvae have rendered conventional chemical pesticide treatments ineffective. Chemosensory proteins in insect pests represent potential molecular targets for the development of novel population control strategies that interfere with olfaction [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]. However, relatively little is known regarding the molecular mechanisms underlying odorant detection in coleopterans.</p><p>As no genome sequence information is available for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, we used Illumina sequencing technology to identify olfaction-related genes in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> by assembling antennal transcriptomes of adult males and females. We identified many chemosensory genes expressing in the antennae of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. Our report is the first exhaustive characterization of chemosensory multigene families of a beetle in the superfamily Scarabaeidae.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec005"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec006"><title>Insects</title><p>Live adult <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> were collected in June 2012 from fields at the Experimental Station of the Shandong Peanut Research Institute in Qingdao, China (36.75&#x000b0; N, 120.50&#x000b0; E). The insects were separated into males and females, and were reared on fresh leaves of elm tree, <italic>Ulmus pumila</italic> L. in rotating wire-mesh cages at 26&#x000b1;1&#x000b0;C temperature and 18% to 20% relative humidity in an environmental chamber.</p></sec><sec id="sec007"><title>Complementary DNA (cDNA) library construction and Illumina sequencing</title><p>The antennae were severed at the base of the pedicel using forceps, and transferred immediately to microcentrifuge tubes in liquid nitrogen. The frozen antennae were stored at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C. Total RNA was extracted from about five hundred female or male antennae using the Trizol reagent (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA), according to manufacturer&#x02019;s protocol. The quantity and integrity of the RNA were assessed using an Agilent 2100 Bioanalyzer (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, CA, USA). First-strand cDNA was synthesized from 10 &#x003bc;g of total RNA. The cDNA libraries were constructed using reagents provided in the Illumina sequencing kit, according to the manufacturer&#x02019;s recommendations, and the libraries were sequenced using an Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform at the Chinese National Human Genome Center (Shanghai, China). The <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> male and female antennal Illumina sequence data have been submitted to NCBI (accession numbers SRR1503480 and SRR1503444, respectively).</p></sec><sec id="sec008"><title>Read assembly and sequence annotation</title><p>All sequencing reads were filtered to remove short or low-quality reads and adapter sequences using the TGI Seqclean program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://compbio.dfci.harvard.edu/tgi/software/">http://compbio.dfci.harvard.edu/tgi/software/</ext-link>). We conducted the de novo assembly using the Trinity, release 25.02.2013, program [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref037" ref-type="bibr">37</xref>] using the default parameters, which did not rely on mapping the sequencing reads to a reference genome. The contigs obtained were compared with the NCBI nonredundant protein database (version 31.10.2012) using the BLASTX computational tool with a threshold E-value of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>. Gene Ontology (GO) annotations were assigned using the Blast2GO program [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref038" ref-type="bibr">38</xref>] through a search of the NCBI nonredundant database using the BLASTX algorithm. The E-value cut-off was set at 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>. The transcripts were categorized as cellular component, molecular function, or biological process, allowing for a meta-analyses of the gene populations.</p><p>The ORFs of the annotated olfactory gene families of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> were identified using the Getorf utility in the EMBOSS, version 6.3.1, program (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/cgi-bin/portal.py?#forms::getorf">http://mobyle.pasteur.fr/ cgi-bin/portal.py?#forms::getorf</ext-link>) [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref039" ref-type="bibr">39</xref>], and verified by comparing the predicted sequences to the NCBI nonredundant protein database using the BLASTX computational tool. The cleavage sites for signal peptides were determined using the SignalP, version 4.0, program [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref040" ref-type="bibr">40</xref>]. The transmembrane domains of the candidate ORs, GRs, and IRs were identified using the TMHMM, version 2.0, program [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref041" ref-type="bibr">41</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec009"><title>Phylogenetic analysis</title><p>The phylogenetic trees were constructed using the maximum-likelihood method based on the putative chemosensory protein sequences identified in the transcriptomes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. The OBP data set contained 154 protein sequences, including 49 sequences from <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>], 46 sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>], 13 sequences from <italic>Ips typographus</italic> and 31 from <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The CSP data set contained 38 protein sequences, including 19, 3, 11 sequences from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. Signal peptide sequences were removed from the data set before conducting the analyses because these regions have a high substitution rate. The SNMP data set contained 11 protein sequences, including 2, 2, 3, 3 sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>, respectively [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. The OR data set contained 111 protein sequences from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> that are expressed in the head of the adult [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], 48 sequences from <italic>Megacyllene caryae</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>], 26 sequences from <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and 33 sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic> (&#x0003e;200 aa) [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The final data set contained 259 sequences. The GR data set contained 68 protein sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], 181 sequences from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref047" ref-type="bibr">47</xref>], 3 sequences from <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and 2 sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic> (&#x0003e;200 aa) [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. The IR data set contained 137 protein sequences, including 35 sequences from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, 79 sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>], 3 sequences from <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and 15 sequences from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic> (&#x0003e;190 aa) [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><p>The multiple sequence alignment was performed using the MAFFT program [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref048" ref-type="bibr">48</xref>]. Alignment ambiguities and gap-containing columns were excluded from the phylogenetic analyses. The maximum-likelihood trees were constructed using the Fasttree, version 2.1.7, software [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref049" ref-type="bibr">49</xref>]. The tree images were created using the iTOL web-based program [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref050" ref-type="bibr">50</xref>].</p></sec><sec id="sec010"><title>Reverse transcription and polymerase chain reaction (RT-PCR)</title><p>The sequences of all the identified chemosensory-related transcripts were verified using RT-PCR and direct DNA sequencing. Total RNA was extracted from antennae collected from male and female <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. Primer pairs (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>) were designed according to the Illumina sequencing data using the Primer Premier 5 software (Premier Biosoft, Palo Alto, CA, USA). The PCR was performed using the Titanium Taq DNA polymerase (Clontech, Mountain View, CA, USA) and olfactory-gene-specific primer pairs. Thermal cycling was performed at 94&#x000b0;C 5 min, followed by 30 cycles of 94&#x000b0;C for 50 s, 48&#x000b0;C to 56&#x000b0;C for 1 min, and 72&#x000b0;C for 1 min, with a final extension at 72&#x000b0;C for 10 min. Forty cycles of PCR were used to amplify the OR, GR, and IR sequences because of their relative low levels of abundance. The amplicons were analyzed by electrophoresis on 1.5% agarose gel, and visualized using GelRed staining (Biotium, Hayward, CA, USA). The amplicons were purified using the Qiaquick Gel Extraction Kit (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany), and one amplicon for each gene was sequenced by a commercial service provider (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China).</p></sec><sec id="sec011"><title>Quantitative real time RT-PCR analysis</title><p>The expression of the putative chemosensory genes in different tissues was investigated using quantitative real time RT-PCR (qRT-PCR) experiments. The qRT-PCR was performed on the Bio-RAD CFX connect Real-Time System (Applied Biosystems, USA) using SYBR Green (Invitrogen, USA). Ten micrograms of total RNA sample was used for the synthesis of first-strand cDNA with reverse transcriptase (Takara, Japan) and the cDNA was then used as a template for qRT-PCR. The specific primers for qRT-PCR (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s006" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Table</xref>) were designed using Primer Premier 5. The reaction programs were 1&#x02013;30s at 95&#x000b0;C, 40 cycles of 95&#x000b0;C for 10s and 61&#x000b0;C for 30s. The specificity of the PCR reactions was assessed by measuring a 65&#x02013;95&#x000b0;C melting curve. Expression levels of the genes were calculated relative to the expression of the control gene G3PDH using the 2<sup>-&#x02206;&#x02206;CT</sup> method [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref051" ref-type="bibr">51</xref>]. All reactions were performed in triplicates.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec012"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec013"><title>De novo assembly and gene annotation of chemosensory genes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic></title><p>Solexa sequencing yielded a total of 33,384,121 (99.02%) and 25,729,630 (99.09%) clean reads for the female and male transcriptomes, respectively. The clean reads from the female and male samples were assembled into 145,780 (N50 = 2,265) and 120,190 (N50 = 2,169) contigs larger than 200 bp, respectively. The largest contigs obtained from the female and male data sets were 37,531 and 41,309 bp, respectively. The assembled contigs were compared to the NCBI nonredundant protein database using BLASTX with a cut-off E-value of 1 &#x000d7; 10<sup>&#x02013;5</sup>. In females, the BLASTX searches produced 92,353 hits, which comprised 63.4% of all of the contigs assembled for females. In males, the BLASTX searches produced 83,999 hits, which comprised 69.9% of all of the contigs assembled for males. The highest match percentage (44.4% in female and 44.6% in male) is to <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> sequences (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s007" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Table</xref>). The annotated contigs that shared &#x0003e; 98% amino-acid sequence identity were presumed to represent the same unigene, and only the transcript with the longest ORF was included in the analysis. Based on these criteria, bioinformatics analyses identified a total of 77 unigenes from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> transcriptomes that belonged to gene families putatively involved in insect chemoreception, including 15 OBPs, five CSPs, one SNMP, 43 ORs, eight GRs, and five IRs (Tables <xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="pone.0121504.t002" ref-type="table">2</xref>), none of which have been reported in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> previously. The sequences of all these transcripts assembled were experimentally validated by RT-PCR and Sanger sequencing. The nucleic acid sequences of the cDNAs shared &#x0003e; 99% sequence identity with the corresponding sequences in the respective transcriptomes, indicating that the transcriptome assemblies were accurate. The alignment results showed that all the sequences belonging to the same chemosensory gene family had long overlapping regions without identity, which confirmed that they represented unigenes. The amino acid sequences for all these proteins are provided in <xref rid="pone.0121504.s005" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 File</xref>.</p><table-wrap id="pone.0121504.t001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>BLASTP matches for the putative OBPs, CSPs, and SNMPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0121504.t001g" xlink:href="pone.0121504.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Gene Name</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Acc. number</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>ORF Length(aa)</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Complete ORF</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Signal Peptide</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>C nb</bold><xref rid="t001fn001" ref-type="table-fn">*</xref></th><th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Best Blastp Match</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Name</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Acc. number</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Species</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>E value</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Identity (%)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251641</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">135</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ACX32050.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Holotrichia oblita</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251642</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">odorant binding protein (subfamily minus-C) C04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_975685.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251643</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">142</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADX96030.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Holotrichia oblita</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.00E-59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251644</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">145</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADX96031.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Holotrichia oblita</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">46</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251645</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">149</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGI05179.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251646</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">143</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA12066.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251647</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">140</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAC07271.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Heptophylla picea</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251648</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02960.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251649</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">133</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">odorant binding protein (subfamily minus-C) C04</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_975685.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251650</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to putative odorant-binding protein 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_975684.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251651</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">212</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to odorant-binding protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_972220.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.00E-26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251652</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">214</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OBP21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AGI05159.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251653</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to odorant-binding protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_972220.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251639</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">134</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ASP(precursor)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP_001106744.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Bombyx mori</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.00E-14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOBP15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251640</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">153</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PBP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">BAF79600.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Anomala schonfeldti</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.00E-78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">84</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorCSP1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251633</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">136</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemosensory protein 5 precursor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP_001039287.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.00E-34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">57</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorCSP2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251634</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">108</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemosensory protein 1 precursor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP_001039273.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.00E-42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorCSP3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251635</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">130</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemosensory protein</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AFI45003.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorCSP4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251636</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemosensory protein 6 precursor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP_001039288.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.00E-43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorCSP5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251637</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">126</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1&#x02013;20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">chemosensory protein 7 precursor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">NP_001039289.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.00E-53</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">67</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorSNMP1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251638</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">520</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to sensory neuron membrane protein 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_001816436.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.00E-140</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">48</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="t001fn001"><p>* the number of conserved cysteine residues</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="pone.0121504.t002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>BLASTP matches for the putative ORs, GRs, and IRs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone.0121504.t002g" xlink:href="pone.0121504.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/><col align="left" valign="middle" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Gene Name</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Acc. number</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>ORF Length(aa)</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>Complete ORF</bold></th><th rowspan="2" align="left" colspan="1"><bold>TMD(NO)</bold></th><th colspan="5" align="center" rowspan="1"><bold>Best Blastp Match</bold></th></tr><tr><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Name</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Acc. number</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Species</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>E value</bold></th><th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold>Identity (%)</bold></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOrco</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251654</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">447</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Or83b</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AEG88961.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Holotrichia parallela</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">90</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251655</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">427</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR 167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4E-42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251656</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">436</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM84012.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-94</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251657</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">392</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99229.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4E-43</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251658</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99414.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8E-44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251659</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">403</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA10800.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-62</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251660</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">379</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to odorant receptor 41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_972901.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251661</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">402</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM84012.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251662</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">395</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09299.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR9</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251663</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to odorant receptor 41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_972901.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251664</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">416</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA10800.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5E-79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR11</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251665</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">383</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR110</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09299.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4E-30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">25</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251666</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">441</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM84012.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6E-75</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">38</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251667</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">446</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM84012.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-79</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">39</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251668</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA10800.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251669</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">405</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99227.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6E-52</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251670</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">448</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAM84012.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9E-63</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251671</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">385</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR67</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ97776.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-54</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251672</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">373</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR108</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09139.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR19</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251673</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">376</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99227.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2E-37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251674</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">375</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99416.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7E-57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251675</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR111</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09138.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6E-27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR22</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251676</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">410</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2E-51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251677</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">381</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99416.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251678</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">374</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA10778.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR25</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251679</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251680</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">413</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-45</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR27</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251681</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">372</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5E-38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251682</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">384</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR59</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99171.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9E-51</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR29</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251683</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">386</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99414.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2E-28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251684</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">411</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-46</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251685</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">202</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR84</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA10775.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3e-26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR32</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251686</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">184</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09271.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1e-14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251687</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">261</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to candidate odorant receptor</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_001812261.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2e-28</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR34</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251688</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">346</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR64</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA10800.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4e-42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR35</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251689</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">223</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR108</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09139.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6e-23</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251690</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">191</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR60</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99415.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8e-31</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251691</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">255</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR130</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02882.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2e-13</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">26</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251692</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">256</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR127</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ97733.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2e-14</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251693</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">241</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR116</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA05716.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1e-16</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR40</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251694</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">229</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR112</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA09271.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1e-21</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR41</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251695</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">408</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR167</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA02801.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2e-48</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorOR42</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251696</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">336</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">OR58</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ99414.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5e-36</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">29</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251699</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">442</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to Gustatory and odorant receptor 21a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_973273.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251698</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">437</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GR 155</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA07633.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-44</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">33</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251697</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">328</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">gustatory receptor candidate 24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">CAL23157.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8E-57</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR4</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251700</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">368</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to gustatory receptor candidate 38</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_001814661.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8E-128</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">55</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251701</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">345</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to trehalose receptor 1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_971005.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2E-163</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR6</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251702</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">228</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GR 141</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EEZ97766.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251703</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">103</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">GR 7</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EFA04713.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">41</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorGR8</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251704</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">231</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to Gustatory receptor 28b CG13788-PB</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_968269.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">1E-12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">28</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorIR21a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251705</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">749</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative chemosensory ionotropic glutamate receptor IR21a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADR64678.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">47</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorIR41a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251706</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">594</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">putative chemosensory ionotropic receptor IR41a</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ADR64681.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3E-95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorIR75q</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251708</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">617</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to ionotropic glutamate receptor-invertebrate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_968638.1</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5E-175</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">58</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorIR75x</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251707</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">597</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Y</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to ionotropic glutamate receptor-invertebrate</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_966388.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">2E-102</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">AcorIRx</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">KM251709</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">845</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">N</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PREDICTED: similar to ionotropic glutamate receptor subunit ia</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">XP_974901.2</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec014"><title>Gene ontology annotations</title><p>GO annotation indicated that the analyzed antennal transcriptomes of male and female adults were highly similar with respect to GO terms. In males, 16,702 <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> contigs were assigned to at least one GO term based on BLASTX matches with sequences with previously known function. In females, there were 18,624 such contigs. These contigs were annotated in three main categories: cellular component, biological process and molecular function, and 45 sub-categories. Among the biological process category, cellular and metabolic processes were the two largest groups in both male and female data sets. The molecular function category was mainly comprised of sequences involved in binding and catalytic activities. Under the cellular component category, cell and membrane were the most abundant GO terms (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g001" ref-type="fig">Fig 1</xref>). These GO annotations provide a global gene expression profile for male and female antenna of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, which is basically consistent with previously reported antenna of other Lepidoptera and Coleoptera insects [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref028" ref-type="bibr">28</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref031" ref-type="bibr">31</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>].</p><fig id="pone.0121504.g001" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.g001</object-id><label>Fig 1</label><caption><title>Gene ontology annotations of transcripts isolated from the antennae of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>.</title><p>The X-axis shows that transcripts were assigned to the cellular component, biological process, or molecular function categories and further to 45 subcategories at GO level 2 using the Blast2GO program. The Y-axis shows percentage of transcripts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121504.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec015"><title>Perireceptor olfactory gene families</title><sec id="sec016"><title>OBPs</title><p>We identified a total of 15 different sequences encoding candidate OBPs in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, and numbered them according to the most similar homolog whenever possible (<xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Of these transcripts, full-length ORFs encoding 133 to 223 amino acids were identified in 14 of them, and the remaining candidate, AcorOBP2, corresponded to a partial sequence that encoded 96 amino acids. Other unigene data for these OBPs, including length, signal peptide, closest BLASTP matches, and so on, are listed in <xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>.</p><p>Sequence analysis indicated that each of the 14 candidate OBPs that contained a complete ORF also encoded a signal peptide sequence (<xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). The OBP1 of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> shared 86% amino-acid sequence identity with the OBP1 of <italic>Holotrichia oblita</italic>, and the OBP15 of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> shared 84% amino-acid sequence identity with the PBP2 of <italic>Anomala schonfeldti</italic>, whereas all other candidate OBPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> displayed a low level of sequence similarity with known OBPs of coleopterans. Nine of the candidate sequences represented classic OBPs, each containing the six conserved cysteine residues (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>). AcorOBP14, AcorOBP5, and AcorOBP9 were minus-C OBPs (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s001" ref-type="supplementary-material">S1 Fig</xref>), and AcorOBP11 and AcorOBP13 were plus-C OBPs (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s002" ref-type="supplementary-material">S2 Fig</xref>) [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref043" ref-type="bibr">43</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref052" ref-type="bibr">52</xref>].</p><p>To confirm the annotation and identify potential orthologs, a maximum-likelihood cluster analysis was performed (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g002" ref-type="fig">Fig 2</xref>). The phylogenetic tree had relatively large minus-C OBP and plus-C OBP branches. The OBPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> were distributed over various branches, with all forming small clusters with the OBPs of coleopteran species. Of the 15 putative OBPs, seven clustered with other OBPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, rather than those of other insect species, suggesting that they may be the products of recent gene duplications.</p><fig id="pone.0121504.g002" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.g002</object-id><label>Fig 2</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood phylogenetic tree of the putative OBPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and OBPs from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>.</title><p>The tree was constructed using the FastTree 2.1.7 program. The numbers above the nodes indicate support values. Support values &#x0003c; 0.9 are not shown. The plus-C subfamily is marked in light yellow, and the minus-C subfamily is marked in light green.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121504.g002"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec017"><title>CSPs</title><p>Our bioinformatic analysis identified five unigenes encoding proteins that were 108 to 261 amino acids in length, which is consistent with other insect CSPs (<xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>). Each of the putative CSP unigenes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> had an intact ORF with a signal peptide and four conserved cysteine residues. The maximum-likelihood tree showed that AcorCSP3 clustered confidently with TcasCSP4, DponCSP3 and DponCSP5. AcorCSP4 clustered confidently with TcasCSP6 and ItypCSP4. There were weak values supporting the other three clades: AcorCSP1/DponCSP7, AcorCSP2/TcasCSP1 and AcorCSP5/TcasCSP7/DponCSP4/ItypCSP5 (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g003" ref-type="fig">Fig 3</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121504.g003" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.g003</object-id><label>Fig 3</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood phylogenetic tree of the putative CSPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and CSPs from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>.</title><p>The tree was constructed using the FastTree 2.1.7 program. The numbers above the nodes indicate support values. Support values &#x0003c; 0.9 are not shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121504.g003"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec018"><title>SNMPs</title><p>In general, SNMPs are classified as SNMP1 or SNMP2. Based on the transcriptome data, only one SNMP candidate was identified in the antennae of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. Phylogenetic analysis along with BLASTP search revealed it was classified as SNMP1 (<xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>, <xref rid="pone.0121504.s003" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Fig</xref>). The AcorSNMP1 candidate shared 48% amino-acid sequence identity with an SNMP1 in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> (XP_001816436.1; <xref rid="pone.0121504.t001" ref-type="table">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec id="sec019"><title>Receptor encoding genes families</title><sec id="sec020"><title>ORs</title><p>Forty-three unigenes encoding putative ORs were identified based on the antennal transcriptome data for <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. Transcripts for all the candidate ORs were present in the transcriptomes of both sexes. Among them, 28 contained a full-length ORF that encoded 372 to 448 amino acids. Fifteen partial sequences encoded 184&#x02013;408 amino acids. One OR sequence was found that shared a high level of identity with the conserved Orco proteins of other insect species and named as AcorOrco. The amino-acid sequence of AcorOrco shared 90% identity with Or83b of <italic>Holotrichia parallela</italic> (AEG88961.1) and 81% identity with the Orco of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> (XP_008194693.1). The other ORs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> were highly divergent, and shared low levels of similarity with other insect ORs. Between two and eight transmembrane domains were identified in the ORs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121504.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>), based on comparisons with other insect ORs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref019" ref-type="bibr">19</xref>]. Thirteen (46.4%) of the 28 ORs with complete ORF of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> contained seven transmembrane domains, which is characteristic of the OR protein family. The topology analysis indicated that the N-terminus of 21 of the 28 full-length ORs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> was on the cytoplasmic side of the membrane. This is the typical membrane topology of insect ORs and is inverted relative to vertebrate ORs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref021" ref-type="bibr">21</xref>].</p><p>A maximum-likelihood phylogenetic analysis was performed using a data set containing the sequences of the ORs that were longer than 200 amino acids from <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and other four described coleopteran species [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>] (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g004" ref-type="fig">Fig 4</xref>). The OR sequences were clustered into several subgroups which were numbered from 1 to 7 according to previous studies [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>]. Except for AcorOrco, <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> ORs were only present within previously defined coleopteran OR subgroup1, 2, and 3. The majority of the ORs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> clustered into species-specific expansions within receptor subgroups 2 and 3. As previously reported, receptor subgroups 4, 5, and 6 contained ORs from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, and subgroup 7 contained ORs from <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic> only [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref045" ref-type="bibr">45</xref>], with one exception, ItypOR14, which was clustered within subgroup 5 but showed a weak supporting value. The orthologs to the functionally characterized ORs of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic> were identified in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. McarOR3 and TcasOR65 formed a strong lineage with AcorOR2, AcorOR12, and AcorOR13. AcorOR34 was clustered confidently with DponOR5 and five <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic> olfactory receptors including McarOR5. However, McarOR20 represented no apparent orthologs to any ORs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>.</p><fig id="pone.0121504.g004" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.g004</object-id><label>Fig 4</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood tree of the putative ORs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and ORs of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>.</title><p>The tree was constructed using the FastTree 2.1.7 program. The numbers above the nodes indicate support values. Support values &#x0003c; 0.9 are not shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121504.g004"/></fig></sec><sec id="sec021"><title>GRs</title><p>Bioinformatic analysis identified eight putative GR unigenes. Among them, a complete ORF was identified in AcorGR2, AcorGR3, AcorGR4, and AcorGR5, and the remaining GRs were partial sequences that encoded more than 103 amino acids. Based on the phylogenetic analysis, several potential orthologs for other known insect GRs were identified. AcorGR2 represented an ortholog with TcasGR155. AcorGR5 clustered confidently with ItypGR6. Besides, two <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> GRs clustered within the highly conserved lineage of the DmelGR21a and DmelGR63a. AcorGR3 represented an ortholog to TcasGR1, DponGR1 and DmelGR63a. AcorGR4 was the orthologous receptor of TcasGR3, ItypGR3, DponGR3 and DmelGR63a (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s004" ref-type="supplementary-material">S4 Fig</xref>).</p></sec><sec id="sec022"><title>IRs</title><p>We identified five putative IR unigenes in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, in three of which a complete ORF was identified. Insect IRs typically contain three transmembrane domains [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref026" ref-type="bibr">26</xref>]. We identified three transmembrane domains in four of the IRs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121504.t002" ref-type="table">Table 2</xref>). According to the maximum-likelihood tree of the IRs from <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic> and four coleopterans, we found each member of IR21a, IR41a and IR75q lineage in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). However, we didn&#x02019;t find the ortholog for co-receptor IR8a or IR25a. One <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> IR located at the base of a branch formed by 14 homologs belonging to IR75 group but its exact orthologues were not identified (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>). Thus it was named AcorIR75x. Besides, one <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> IR which clustered with an IR (XP_974901.2) from <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> was named AcorIRx (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g005" ref-type="fig">Fig 5</xref>).</p><fig id="pone.0121504.g005" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.g005</object-id><label>Fig 5</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood tree of the putative IRs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and IRs of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>.</title><p>The tree was constructed using the FastTree 2.1.7 program. The numbers above the nodes indicate support values. Support values &#x0003c; 0.9 are not shown.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121504.g005"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="sec023"><title>Quantitative real time RT-PCR analysis</title><p>We investigated the expression patterns of 54 putative <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> chemosensory genes by performing a qRT-PCR analysis of the RNA extracted from adult male and female antennae, male and female legs as well as non-chemosensory tissues (mixture of male thorax and abdomen which was referred to as body tissues here after) (<xref rid="pone.0121504.g006" ref-type="fig">Fig 6</xref>). Among the 13 tested OBPs, AcorOBP3, AcorOBP4, AcorOBP7, AcorOBP8 and AcorOBP12 displayed antenna-specific expression without sex bias except AcorOBP4, which was expressed at a higher level in male than in female. The remaining OBPs were expressed in the legs and non-chemosensory tissues as well as in the antennae. Of these widely distributed genes, AcorOBP1, AcorOBP6 and AcorOBP15 were expressed at the highest level in male antennae compared with other body parts. The analysis on the expression of all the five <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> CSPs was performed. AcorCSP3 displayed a clear antennae-specific expression with approximately equivalent levels in both sexes. The remaining four CSPs were found to be expressed not only in antennae but also in legs and no-chemosensory tissues. The SNMP1 of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> was expressed only in the antennae with no significant difference observed in the level between males and females.</p><fig id="pone.0121504.g006" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0121504.g006</object-id><label>Fig 6</label><caption><title>Relative expression levels of the putative chemosensory transcripts of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> using qRT-PCR.</title><p>The X-axis shows the different body parts. The Y-axis shows the relative mRNA level. A&#x02640;, female antennae; A&#x02642;, male antennae; L&#x02640;, female legs; L&#x02642;, male, legs; B, body tissues (mixture of male thorax and abdomen).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0121504.g006"/></fig><p>The majority of the tested ORs were clearly antenna-specific. AcorOR10 and AcorOR15 were expressed in legs at lower levels relative to in the antennae. AcorOrco was only expressed in the antennae with no sex bias. Although we didn't find apparent sex-specific genes in these <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> olfactory receptors, AcorOR7, AcorOR9, AcorOR12, AcorOR13, AcorOR15 and AcorOR25 were more highly expressed in male antennae than in female antennae, wheras AcorOR5, AcorOR29 and AcorOR30 were expressed at higher levels in male antennae than in female antennae. All the four tested GRs were not only expressed in the antennae but also in the legs and the body tissues. AcorGR4 and AcorGR6 were more highly expressed in female antennae than in male antenna. Of the four tested IRs, AcorIR21a, AcorIR75q and AcorIR75x displayed an antenna-specific expression, among which AcorIR21a and AcorIR75q were expressed at a higher level in female than in male. AcorIRx was expressed more highly in the legs compared with in the antennae and body tissues.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="conclusions" id="sec024"><title>Discussion</title><p>The molecular basis of chemoreception in coleopterans is relatively poorly understood compared to dipterans and lepidopterans. Major chemosensory gene families have been identified in the red flour beetle, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, and three species of bark beetles [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>&#x02013;<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref034" ref-type="bibr">34</xref>]. We generated antennal transcriptomes of male and female <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> using Illumina next-generation sequencing technology. We identified 77 chemosensory genes encoding members of six protein families, including OBPs, CSPs, SNMPs, ORs, GRs, and IRs. However, transcripts present at low abundance and those that are too divergent to be identified using a BLAST search may be overlooked in transcriptome analysis. Thus, it is unlikely that the identified genes represent the total number of the related chemosensory genes <italic>in A</italic>.<italic>corpulenta</italic>. This is the first comprehensive characterization of olfactory genes in the scarab beetle. Our findings provide insight into the molecular mechanisms of olfaction in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, and identify potential molecular targets for controlling this pest.</p><p>A total of 15 OBPs were identified in the antennal transcriptome of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. This number is equal to that of OBPs previously identified in the antennae of <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic>. By contrast, more OBPs were identified in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> based on a genomic analysis, and more were identified in <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic> based on the transcriptome analysis of various tissues, including the antenna, from different life stages (<xref rid="pone.0121504.s008" ref-type="supplementary-material">S3 Table</xref>). Our analysis of the antennal transcriptome may not have identified OBPs expressed primarily or exclusively in other tissues or life stages, such as in larve. OBPs may share a common ancestor with CSPs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The amino-acid sequence similarity between the OBPs and CSPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and those of other insect species indicates that OBPs are less conserved than the CSPs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. The antennae-specific expression of OBPs has been implicated in pheromone detection, whereas expression of OBPs in other organs has been shown to be related to the other functions apart from chemosensation [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref036" ref-type="bibr">36</xref>]., Some OBPs exhibited antenna-specific pattern of expression, suggesting they may play important roles in detecting odor molecules. Future functional investigation of these genes is warranted to determine their specific roles in chemical communication.</p><p>CSPs constitute another class of small binding proteins. Although most of the genomes of <italic>Drosophila</italic> species contain only four CSP genes, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, which is more closely related to <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, has 20 CSPs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref042" ref-type="bibr">42</xref>]. We identified a modest number of CSPs in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, presumably because the expression of many CSP genes is limited to nonsensory tissues or other developmental stages [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref053" ref-type="bibr">53</xref>]. Among the five predicted CSPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, four were detected in both the antennae and non-chemosensory tissues, which is consistent with the expression patterns of CSPs in other insects [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref054" ref-type="bibr">54</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref055" ref-type="bibr">55</xref>]. Thus, in addition to chemosensation function, CSPs in <italic>A</italic>.<italic>corpulenta</italic> may be involved in other functions such as the regeneration of legs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref015" ref-type="bibr">15</xref>] and female survival and reproduction [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref056" ref-type="bibr">56</xref>]. AcorCSP3 displayed apparent antenna-specific expression suggesting that it may play an important role in semiochemical recognition.</p><p>SNMPs can generally be categorized as SNMP1 or SNMP2, according to sequence similarity and intron locations [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref044" ref-type="bibr">44</xref>]. Although the functions of SNMPs remain largely unclear, SNMPs have been shown to be essential for pheromone responses [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref016" ref-type="bibr">16</xref>]. We identified only one SNMP in the antennal transcriptome of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, which we classified as an SNMP1, and found that it clearly displayed antenna-specific expression in both sexes, suggesting it may be important in chemoreception. The SNMPs are conserved throughout holometabolous insects [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>]. In certain moths, a high level of antenna-specific expression has been observed for SNMP1, whereas SNMP2 is expressed at various levels in a variety of tissues [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref057" ref-type="bibr">57</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref058" ref-type="bibr">58</xref>]. However, studies of SNMPs in coleopterans are scant. We speculate that the tissue specificity of AcorSNMP2 expression may differ from that reported in other coleopterans [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref033" ref-type="bibr">33</xref>]. In addition, an SNMP2 ortholog was not found in an analysis of another scarab chafer, <italic>H</italic>. <italic>parallela</italic> (unpublished). Therefore, we speculate that the level of SNMP2 expression in the antenna of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> may be low, and thus undetectable based on the transcriptome analysis. It is also possible that members of Scarabaeidae may have lost SNMP2 during evolution.</p><p>ORs of coleopterans from the superfamilies Tenebrionoidea, Chrysomeloidea, and Curculionidae have been described, and the findings of our study extend the knowledge base of coleopteran ORs to include the superfamily Scarabaeidae. In insects, ORs have undergone frequent gene duplications and deletion events, representing the &#x0201c;birth-to-death&#x0201d; model of evolution, which has contributed to a high level of diversity in OR genes and variability in gene number between different species. Sixty-three ORs have been identified in <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>], and hundreds of ORs have been identified in ants [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref059" ref-type="bibr">59</xref>]. Relatively few ORs were identified in the antennal transcriptomes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, compared with the number of ORs in the complete genome of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, but comparable to the number of 57 ORs identified in the antennal transcriptome of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic>. Maybe lower expressed ORs were not detected. However, similar to observations in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic>, a species-specific expansion of ORs was observed in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. These species-specific expansions may reflect the different ecological niches of these species. ORs play a key role in odor specification. We may speculate on the possible functions of ORs in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> through those of orthologous ORs in <italic>M</italic>. <italic>caryae</italic>, which was the first beetle in which the function of ORs was characterized. However, the effects of the rapid evolution of OR families might be inconsistent with such speculation. The AcorOR2, AcorOR12, and AcorOR13 clustered into a clade that was a sister group of McarOR3/TcasOR65. McarOR3 binds (<italic>S</italic>)-2-methyl-1-butanol and structurally related chemicals. Whether AcorOR2, AcorOR12, and AcorOR13 have functions that are similar to those of McarOR3 warrants further investigation [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref032" ref-type="bibr">32</xref>]. The expression profiling indicated that <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> ORs were highly restricted in the antennae relative to OBPs and CSPs. We also found several ORs expressed in legs and no-chemosensory tissues, similar to the findings in <italic>Sesamia inferens</italic>[<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref060" ref-type="bibr">60</xref>]. Unlike <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> olfactory co-receptor which was also expressed in legs and other tissues [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>], AcorOrco showed a clear antennae-specific expression pattern.</p><p>A large number of GRs have also been identified in various insect species [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref046" ref-type="bibr">46</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref062" ref-type="bibr">62</xref>]. We identified a small number of GRs in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, which was expected because GRs are primarily expressed in gustatory organs, such as the proboscis, rather than the antennae [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref024" ref-type="bibr">24</xref>]. A previous study showed that GR21a and GR63a of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic> form heterodimers, and are involved in CO<sub>2</sub> detection [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref063" ref-type="bibr">63</xref>]. Both orthologs of these two receptors were found in the antenna transcriptomes of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>, which suggests that <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> might use CO<sub>2</sub> detection as a criterion for host plant selection. In contrast to AcorORs, AcorGRs were widely expressed in different tissues with relatively high leg expression, similar to that reported in <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref061" ref-type="bibr">61</xref>].</p><p>Compared with the ORs and GRs, IRs are more highly conserved in insects, and the number of IRs is generally consistent [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. IRs can be categorized as divergent species-specific IRs and conserved antennal IRs, the latter of which are expressed in the sensory dendrites of antennae [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>,<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref025" ref-type="bibr">25</xref>]. For example, of the 66 IRs identified in drosophilids, 15 were antennal IRs [<xref rid="pone.0121504.ref018" ref-type="bibr">18</xref>]. The orthologs of IR21a, IR41a, and IR75q of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic> were identified in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>. AcorIR21a, AcorIR75q and AcorIR75x displayed antenna-specific expression. Our findings suggest that these IRs may function in olfaction in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic>.</p><p>This study not only described the putative <italic>A</italic>.<italic>corpulenta</italic> chemosensory genes identified from the antennal transcriptome, but also investigated the expression profile of these genes. The genes that are potentially involved in <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> chemical communication may represent novel molecular targets for controlling this beetle by regulating chemoreception.</p></sec><sec sec-type="supplementary-material" id="sec025"><title>Supporting Information</title><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s001"><label>S1 Fig</label><caption><title>Amino-acid sequence alignment of the putative classic OBPs and minus-C OBPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> with OBPs of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic>.</title><p>The alignment was conducted using the ClustalW 2.0 program.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s001.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s002"><label>S2 Fig</label><caption><title>Amino-acid sequence alignment of the putative plus-C OBPs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> with OBPs of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic>.</title><p>The alignment was conducted using the ClustalW 2.0 program.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s002.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s003"><label>S3 Fig</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood tree of the putative SNMP1 of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and SNMPs of <italic>D</italic>. <italic>melanogaster</italic>, <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>.</title><p>The tree was constructed using the FastTree 2.1.7 program. The numbers above the nodes indicate support values. Support values &#x0003c; 0.9 are not shown.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s003.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s004"><label>S4 Fig</label><caption><title>Maximum-likelihood tree of the putative GRs of <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> and GRs of <italic>T</italic>. <italic>castaneum</italic>, <italic>I</italic>. <italic>typographus</italic> and <italic>D</italic>. <italic>ponderosae</italic>.</title><p>The tree was constructed using the FastTree 2.1.7 program. The numbers above the nodes indicate support values. Support values &#x0003c; 0.9 are not shown.</p><p>(TIF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s004.tif"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s005"><label>S1 File</label><caption><title>FASTA format of the amino acid sequences of the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>Corpulenta</italic> chemosensory genes.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s005.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s006"><label>S1 Table</label><caption><title>PCR primers used for RT-PCR and qRT-PCR.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s006.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s007"><label>S2 Table</label><caption><title>Percentage of homologous hits of the <italic>A</italic>. <italic>corpulenta</italic> contigs to other insect species.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s007.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material><supplementary-material content-type="local-data" id="pone.0121504.s008"><label>S3 Table</label><caption><title>Comparison of the number of chemosensory genes identified in different coleopteran species.</title><p>(PDF)</p></caption><media xlink:href="pone.0121504.s008.pdf"><caption><p>Click here for additional data file.</p></caption></media></supplementary-material></sec></body><back><ack><p>We thank Prof. Guirong Wang (Institute of Plant Protection, Chinese Academy of Agricultural Sciences) and Dr. William B. Walker (Swedish University of Agricultural Sciences) for critical reviews.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0121504.ref001"><label>1</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wadhams</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular studies in insect olfaction</article-title>. <source>Insect Mol Biol</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>545</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>551</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11122463?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11122463</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref002"><label>2</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Asahina</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pavlenkovich</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>The survival advantage of olfaction in a competitive environment</article-title>. <source>Curr Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>18</volume>: <fpage>1153</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1155</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cub.2008.06.075">10.1016/j.cub.2008.06.075</ext-link></comment><?supplied-pmid 18674910?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18674910</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref003"><label>3</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clyne</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Freeman</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lessing</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>A novel family of divergent seven-transmembrane proteins: candidate odorant receptors in <italic>drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>22</volume>: <fpage>327</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>338</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10069338?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10069338</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref004"><label>4</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Odorant reception in insects: roles of receptors, binding proteins, and degrading enzymes</article-title>. <source>Annu Rev Entomol</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>58</volume>: <fpage>373</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1146/annurev-ento-120811-153635">10.1146/annurev-ento-120811-153635</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23020622?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23020622</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref005"><label>5</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>S&#x000e1;nchez-Gracia</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular evolution of the major chemosensory gene families in insects</article-title>. <source>Heredity</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>103</volume>: <fpage>208</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>216</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/hdy.2009.55">10.1038/hdy.2009.55</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19436326?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19436326</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref006"><label>6</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Leal</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nikonova</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Peng</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>. <article-title>Disulfide structure of the pheromone binding protein from the silkworm moth, <italic>Bombyx mori</italic></article-title>. <source>FEBS Letters</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>464</volume>: <fpage>85</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>90</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10611489?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10611489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref007"><label>7</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grosse-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Svatos</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>A pheromone-binding protein mediates the bombykol-induced activation of a pheromone receptor in vitro</article-title>. <source>Chem Senses</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>31</volume>: <fpage>547</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>555</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16679489?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16679489</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref008"><label>8</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scaloni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Angeli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pelosi</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Structural analysis and disulfide-bridge pairing of two odorant-binding proteins from <italic>bombyx mori</italic></article-title>. <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>266</volume>: <fpage>386</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>391</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10600513?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10600513</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref009"><label>9</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>YL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fang</surname><given-names>SQ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dong</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YJ</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Large-scale identification of odorant-binding proteins and chemosensory proteins from expressed sequence tags in insects</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>632</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-10-632">10.1186/1471-2164-10-632</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20034407?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20034407</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref010"><label>10</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Olfactory reception in invertebrates</article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>286</volume>: <fpage>720</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>723</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10531050?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10531050</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref011"><label>11</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Smadja</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Genome annotation and comparative analyses of the odorant-binding proteins and chemosensory proteins in the pea aphid <italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Mol Biol</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>19</volume>
<issue>Suppl 2</issue>: <fpage>113</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>122</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2583.2009.00919.x">10.1111/j.1365-2583.2009.00919.x</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20482644?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20482644</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref012"><label>12</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Dani</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michelucci</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Francese</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mastrobuoni</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cappellozza</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>La Marca</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Odorant-binding proteins and chemosensory proteins in pheromone detection and release in the silkmoth <italic>Bombyx mori</italic></article-title>. <source>Chem Senses</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>335</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>344</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/chemse/bjq137">10.1093/chemse/bjq137</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21220518?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21220518</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref013"><label>13</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>SH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>SY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>XY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>JT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Functional characterizations of chemosensory proteins of the Alfalfa plant bug <italic>Adelphocoris lineolatus</italic> indicate their involvement in host recognition</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e42871</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0042871">10.1371/journal.pone.0042871</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22900060?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22900060</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref014"><label>14</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Maleszka</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>For&#x000ea;t</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Saint</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Maleszka</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>. <article-title>RNAi-induced phenotypes suggest a novel role for a chemosensory protein CSP5 in the development of embryonic integument in the honeybee (<italic>Apis mellifera</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Dev Genes Evol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>217</volume>: <fpage>189</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>196</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17216269?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17216269</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref015"><label>15</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nomura</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kawasaki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kubo</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Natori</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>Purification and localization of p10, a novel protein that increases in nymphal regenerating legs of <italic>Periplaneta americana</italic> (American cockroach)</article-title>. <source>Int J Dev Biol</source>. <year>1992</year>;<volume>36</volume>: <fpage>391</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>398</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 1445782?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1445782</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref016"><label>16</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rogers</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antennal SNMPs (sensory neuron membrane proteins) of lepidoptera define a unique family of invertebrate CD36-like proteins</article-title>. <source>J Neurobiol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>49</volume>: <fpage>47</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>61</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11536197?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11536197</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref017"><label>17</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vannice</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>An essential role for a CD36-related receptor in pheromone detection in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>450</volume>: <fpage>289</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>293</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17943085?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17943085</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref018"><label>18</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vannice</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gomez-Diaz</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variant ionotropic glutamate receptors as chemosensory receptors in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>136</volume>: <fpage>149</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>162</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2008.12.001">10.1016/j.cell.2008.12.001</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19135896?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19135896</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref019"><label>19</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Trona</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montagne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Anfora</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ignell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Witzgall</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Putative chemosensory receptors of the codling moth, <italic>Cydia pomonella</italic>, identified by antennal transcriptome analysis</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e31620</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0031620">10.1371/journal.pone.0031620</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22363688?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22363688</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref020"><label>20</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Smart</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kiely</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Beale</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vargas</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carraher</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kralicek</surname><given-names>AV</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title><italic>Drosophila</italic> odorant receptors are novel seven transmembrane domain proteins that can signal independently of heterotrimeric G proteins</article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>770</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>780</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ibmb.2008.05.002">10.1016/j.ibmb.2008.05.002</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18625400?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18625400</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref021"><label>21</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Benton</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sachse</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Michnick</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Atypical membrane topology and heteromeric function of <italic>Drosophila</italic> odorant receptors in vivo</article-title>. <source>PLoS Biol</source>. <year>2006</year>;<volume>4</volume>: <fpage>e20</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 16402857?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16402857</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref022"><label>22</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Domingos</surname><given-names>AI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>WD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Chiappe</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amrein</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vosshall</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Or83b encodes a broadly expressed odorant receptor essential for <italic>Drosophila</italic> olfaction</article-title>. <source>Neuron</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>43</volume>: <fpage>703</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>714</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15339651?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15339651</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref023"><label>23</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pask</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rinker</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zwiebel</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Functional agonism of insect odorant receptor ion channels</article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>8821</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>8825</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1102425108">10.1073/pnas.1102425108</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21555561?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21555561</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref024"><label>24</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Clyne</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Candidate taste receptors in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Science</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>287</volume>: <fpage>1830</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1834</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10710312?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10710312</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref025"><label>25</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Croset</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rytz</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Budd</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brawand</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kaessmann</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Ancient protostome origin of chemosensory ionotropic glutamate receptors and the evolution of insect taste and olfaction</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>6</volume>: <fpage>e1001064</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1001064">10.1371/journal.pgen.1001064</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20808886?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20808886</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref026"><label>26</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Krieger</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gro&#x000df;e-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Mi&#x000df;bach</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Breer</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Variant ionotropic receptors are expressed in olfactory sensory neurons of coeloconic sensilla on the antenna of the desert locust (<italic>Schistocerca gregaria</italic>)</article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Sci</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>10</volume>: <fpage>1</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7150/ijbs.7624">10.7150/ijbs.7624</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 24391446?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24391446</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref027"><label>27</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Allen</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bunger</surname><given-names>PL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garczynski</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Linn</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Sex pheromone receptor specificity in the European corn borer moth, <italic>Ostrinia nubilalis</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e8685</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0008685">10.1371/journal.pone.0008685</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20084285?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20084285</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref028"><label>28</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grosse-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kuebler</surname><given-names>LS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bucks</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogel</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wicher</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hansson</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name>. <article-title>Antennal transcriptome of <italic>Manduca sexta</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>108</volume>: <fpage>7449</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>7454</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1073/pnas.1017963108">10.1073/pnas.1017963108</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21498690?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21498690</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref029"><label>29</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Jacquin-Joly</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legeai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montagn&#x000e9;</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monsempes</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fran&#x000e7;ois</surname><given-names>M-C</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Poulain</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Candidate chemosensory genes in female antennae of the noctuid moth <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic></article-title>. <source>Int J Biol Sci</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>1036</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1050</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.7150/ijbs.4469">10.7150/ijbs.4469</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22904672?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22904672</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref030"><label>30</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Poivet</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gallot</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Montagne</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Glaser</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Legeai</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jacquin-Joly</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>A comparison of the olfactory gene repertoires of adults and larvae in the noctuid moth <italic>Spodoptera littoralis</italic></article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e60263</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0060263">10.1371/journal.pone.0060263</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23565215?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23565215</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref031"><label>31</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gu</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Guo</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Wang</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Candidate olfaction genes identified within the <italic>Helicoverpa armigera</italic> antennal transcriptome</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>7</volume>: <fpage>e48260</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0048260">10.1371/journal.pone.0048260</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23110222?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23110222</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref032"><label>32</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luetje</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Millar</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Soriano-Agaton</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hanks</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Sequencing and characterizing odorant receptors of the cerambycid beetle <italic>Megacyllene caryae</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>42</volume>: <fpage>499</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>505</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.03.007">10.1016/j.ibmb.2012.03.007</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22504490?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22504490</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref033"><label>33</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Andersson</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Grosse-Wilde</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bengtsson</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yuen</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Li</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Antennal transcriptome analysis of the chemosensory gene families in the tree killing bark beetles, <italic>Ips typographus</italic> and <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae: Scolytinae)</article-title>. <source>BMC Genomics</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>14</volume>: <fpage>198</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1186/1471-2164-14-198">10.1186/1471-2164-14-198</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23517120?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23517120</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref034"><label>34</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhu</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yang</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>. <article-title>Global transcriptional analysis of olfactory genes in the head of pine shoot beetle, <italic>Tomicus yunnanensis</italic></article-title>. <source>Comp Funct Genomics</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>2012</volume>: <fpage>491748</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1155/2012/491748">10.1155/2012/491748</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22761546?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22761546</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref035"><label>35</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wei</surname><given-names>XT</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xu</surname><given-names>XD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deloach</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name>. <article-title>Biological control of white grubs (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae) by larvae of <italic>Promachus yesonicus</italic> (Diptera: Asilidae) in China</article-title>. <source>Biol Control</source>. <year>1995</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>290</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>296</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref036"><label>36</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>He</surname><given-names>XL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Insect odorant-binding proteins: Do they offer an alternative pest control strategy?</article-title>
<source>Outlooks on Pest Management</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>31</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>34</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref037"><label>37</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Grabherr</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Yassour</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Levin</surname><given-names>JZ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Amit</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome</article-title>. <source>Nat Biotech</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>29</volume>: <fpage>644</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>652</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nbt.1883">10.1038/nbt.1883</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21572440?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21572440</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref038"><label>38</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Conesa</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>G&#x000f6;tz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Garc&#x000ed;a-G&#x000f3;mez</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Terol</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tal&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robles</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>Blast2GO: a universal tool for annotation, visualization and analysis in functional genomics research</article-title>. <source>Bioinformatics</source>. <year>2005</year>;<volume>21</volume>: <fpage>3674</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>3676</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 16081474?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16081474</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref039"><label>39</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Longden</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bleasby</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>. <article-title>EMBOSS: the European molecular biology open software suite</article-title>. <source>Trends genet</source>. <year>2000</year>;<volume>16</volume>: <fpage>276</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>277</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10827456?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10827456</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref040"><label>40</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Petersen</surname><given-names>TN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brunak</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Nielsen</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>SignalP 4.0: discriminating signal peptides from transmembrane regions</article-title>. <source>Nat Meth</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>785</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>786</lpage>.</mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref041"><label>41</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Krogh</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Larsson</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name>, <name><surname>von Heijne</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sonnhammer</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name>. <article-title>Predicting transmembrane protein topology with a hidden markov model: application to complete genomes</article-title>. <source>J Mol Biol</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>305</volume>: <fpage>567</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>580</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11152613?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11152613</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref042"><label>42</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vieira</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rozas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>. <article-title>Comparative genomics of the odorant-binding and chemosensory protein gene families across the Arthropoda: origin and evolutionary history of the chemosensory system</article-title>. <source>Genome Biol Evol</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>3</volume>: <fpage>476</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>490</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/gbe/evr033">10.1093/gbe/evr033</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21527792?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21527792</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref043"><label>43</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Hekmat-Scafe</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scafe</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name>, <name><surname>McKinney</surname><given-names>AJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Tanouye</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name>. <article-title>Genome-wide analysis of the odorant-binding protein gene family in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Genome Res</source>. <year>2002</year>;<volume>12</volume>: <fpage>1357</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>1369</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 12213773?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12213773</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref044"><label>44</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Nichols</surname><given-names>Z</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>. <article-title>The SNMP/CD36 gene family in Diptera, Hymenoptera and Coleoptera: <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic>, <italic>D</italic>. <italic>pseudoobscura</italic>, <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic>, <italic>Aedes aegypti</italic>, <italic>Apis mellifera</italic>, and <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>398</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>415</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ibmb.2007.11.003">10.1016/j.ibmb.2007.11.003</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18342246?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342246</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref045"><label>45</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Engsontia</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sanderson</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Cobb</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Walden</surname><given-names>KK</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>. <article-title>The red flour beetle's large nose: an expanded odorant receptor gene family in <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>38</volume>: <fpage>387</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>397</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ibmb.2007.10.005">10.1016/j.ibmb.2007.10.005</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18342245?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18342245</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref046"><label>46</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Warr</surname><given-names>CG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Carlson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name>. <article-title>Molecular evolution of the insect chemoreceptor gene superfamily in <italic>Drosophila melanogaster</italic></article-title>. <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>. <year>2003</year>;<volume>100</volume>
<issue>Suppl 2</issue>: <fpage>14537</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>14542</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14608037?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14608037</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref047"><label>47</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><collab>Tribolium Genome Sequencing C</collab>, <name><surname>Richards</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Gibbs</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Weinstock</surname><given-names>GM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Denell</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The genome of the model beetle and pest <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic></article-title>. <source>Nature</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>452</volume>: <fpage>949</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>955</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1038/nature06784">10.1038/nature06784</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18362917?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18362917</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref048"><label>48</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Katoh</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Toh</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name>. <article-title>Recent developments in the MAFFT multiple sequence alignment program</article-title>. <source>Brief Bioinform</source>. <year>2008</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>286</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>298</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/bib/bbn013">10.1093/bib/bbn013</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 18372315?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18372315</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref049"><label>49</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Price</surname><given-names>MN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Dehal</surname><given-names>PS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Arkin</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name>. <article-title>FastTree 2&#x02014;Approximately maximum-likelihood trees for large alignments</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2010</year>;<volume>5</volume>: <fpage>e9490</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0009490">10.1371/journal.pone.0009490</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 20224823?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">20224823</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref050"><label>50</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Letunic</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Bork</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>. <article-title>Interactive Tree Of Life v2: online annotation and display of phylogenetic trees made easy</article-title>. <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>. <year>2011</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>W475</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>W478</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkr201">10.1093/nar/gkr201</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 21470960?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">21470960</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref051"><label>51</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Livak</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Schmittgen</surname><given-names>TD</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis of Relative Gene Expression Data Using Real-Time Quantitative PCR and the 2<sup>&#x02212;&#x00394;&#x00394;CT</sup> Method</article-title>. <source>Methods</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>25</volume>: <fpage>402</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>408</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11846609?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11846609</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref052"><label>52</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Huang</surname><given-names>WS</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Pickett</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Field</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name>. <article-title>"Plus-C" odorant-binding protein genes in two Drosophila species and the malaria mosquito <italic>Anopheles gambiae</italic></article-title>. <source>Gene</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>327</volume>: <fpage>117</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>129</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 14960367?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14960367</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref053"><label>53</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>DP</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhao</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>QY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xiang</surname><given-names>ZH</given-names></name>. <article-title>Identification and expression pattern of the chemosensory protein gene family in the silkworm, <italic>Bombyx mori</italic></article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>37</volume>: <fpage>266</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>277</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 17296501?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17296501</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref054"><label>54</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Angeli</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ceron</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Scaloni</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monti</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Monteforti</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Minnocci</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Purification, structural characterization, cloning and immunocytochemical localization of chemoreception proteins from <italic>Schistocerca gregaria</italic></article-title>. <source>Eur J Biochem</source>. <year>1999</year>;<volume>262</volume>: <fpage>745</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>754</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 10411636?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10411636</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref055"><label>55</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Wanner</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Willis</surname><given-names>LG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Theilmann</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Isman</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Feng</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Plettner</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name>. <article-title>Analysis of the insect OS-D-like gene family</article-title>. <source>J Chem Ecol</source>. <year>2004</year>;<volume>30</volume>: <fpage>889</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>911</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 15274438?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15274438</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref056"><label>56</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Gong</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Luo</surname><given-names>Q</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rizwan-ul-Haq</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Hu</surname><given-names>MY</given-names></name>. <article-title>Cloning and characterization of three chemosensory proteins from <italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic> and effects of gene silencing on female survival and reproduction</article-title>. <source>Bull Entomol Res</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>102</volume>: <fpage>600</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>609</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1017/S0007485312000168">10.1017/S0007485312000168</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22475511?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22475511</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref057"><label>57</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Vogt</surname><given-names>RG</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>NE</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Litvack</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Fandino</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Sparks</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Staples</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>The insect SNMP gene family</article-title>. <source>Insect Biochem Mol Biol</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>39</volume>: <fpage>448</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>456</lpage>. <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.ibmb.2009.03.007">10.1016/j.ibmb.2009.03.007</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19364529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19364529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref058"><label>58</label><mixed-citation publication-type="other">Zhang J, Liu Y, Walker WB, Dong SL, Wang GR. Identification and localization of two sensory neuron membrane proteins from <italic>Spodoptera litura</italic> (Lepidoptera: Noctuidae). Insect Sci. 2014 <comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1111/1744-7917.12131">10.1111/1744-7917.12131</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref059"><label>59</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>XF</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Slone</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rokas</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Berger</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Liebig</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Ray</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Phylogenetic and transcriptomic analysis of chemosensory receptors in a pair of divergent ant species reveals sex-specific signatures of odor coding</article-title>. <source>PLoS Genet</source>. <year>2012</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e1002930</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pgen.1002930">10.1371/journal.pgen.1002930</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 22952454?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">22952454</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref060"><label>60</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Zhang</surname><given-names>YN</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Jin</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Xia</surname><given-names>YH</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zhou</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Deng</surname><given-names>JY</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>Differential Expression Patterns in Chemosensory and Non-Chemosensory Tissues of Putative Chemosensory Genes Identified by Transcriptome Analysis of Insect Pest the Purple Stem Borer <italic>Sesamia inferens</italic> (Walker)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2013</year>;<volume>8</volume>: <fpage>e69715</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0069715">10.1371/journal.pone.0069715</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 23894529?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23894529</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref061"><label>61</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Abdel-latief</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name>. <article-title>A family of chemoreceptors in <italic>Tribolium castaneum</italic> (Tenebrionidae: Coleoptera)</article-title>. <source>PLoS One</source>. <year>2007</year>;<volume>2</volume>: <fpage>e1319</fpage>
<?supplied-pmid 18091992?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18091992</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref062"><label>62</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Brady</surname><given-names>R</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name>., <name><surname>Cravchik</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Morozov</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Rzhetsky</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Zuker</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name>, <etal>et al</etal>
<article-title>A chemosensory gene family encoding candidate gustatory and olfactory receptors in <italic>Drosophila</italic></article-title>. <source>Cell</source>. <year>2001</year>;<volume>104</volume>: <fpage>661</fpage>&#x02013;<lpage>673</lpage>. <?supplied-pmid 11257221?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11257221</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0121504.ref063"><label>63</label><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><name><surname>Robertson</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name>, <name><surname>Kent</surname><given-names>LB</given-names></name>. <article-title>Evolution of the gene lineage encoding the carbon dioxide receptor in insects</article-title>. <source>J Insect Sci</source>. <year>2009</year>;<volume>9</volume>: <fpage>19</fpage>
<comment>doi: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1673/031.009.1901">10.1673/031.009.1901</ext-link></comment>
<?supplied-pmid 19613462?><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19613462</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>