<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Atypon//DTD Atypon Systems Archival NLM DTD Suite v2.2.0 20090301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName atypon-archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName atypon2nlmx.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">J. Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">insc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Insect Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1536-2442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>University of Wisconsin Library</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3281402</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">22236084</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1673/031.011.14701</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Coleopterans Associated with Plants that form Phytotelmata in Subtropical and Temperate Argentina, South America</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>Ra&#x000fa;l E.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr1">
<sup>a*</sup>
</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>Liliana A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1">
<sup>1</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2">
<sup>2</sup>
</xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr2">
<sup>b</sup>
</xref></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label>Instituto, de Limnolog&#x000ed;a &#x0201c;Dr. Ra&#x000fa;l A. Ringuelet,&#x0201d; Universidad Nacional de La Plata - CONICET, CC 712 (1900) La Plata, Buenos Aires, Argentina</aff><aff id="aff2"><label><sup>2</sup></label>Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas y T&#x000e9;cnicas (CONICET)</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1"><label><sup>a*</sup></label><email>rcampos@ilpla.edu.ar</email></corresp><corresp id="corr2"><label><sup>b</sup></label><email>liliafer@museo.fcnym.unlp.edu.ar</email></corresp><corresp id="corr3"><label><sup>*</sup></label>Corresponding author</corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2011</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>7</day><month>11</month><year>2011</year></pub-date><volume>11</volume><elocation-id>147</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>25</day><month>8</month><year>2010</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>15</day><month>12</month><year>2010</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2011</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2011</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>A list of the most common plants that form phytotelmata and their associated coleopterans (aquatic, semi-aquatic and terrestrial) from the northeastern subtropical and temperate area of Argentina, South America with biological and behavioral observations is presented in this study. Species of Poaceae (n = 3), Bromeliaceae (5), Apiaceae (6), Araceae (2), Urticaceae (1), Marantaceae (1), Arecaceae (1), Dipsacaceae (1) and Cyperaceae (1) were identified as phytotelmata. Aquatic species of Scirtidae (2), Dytiscidae (2), and Hydrophilidae (4), semi-aquatic Chelonariidae (2), and terrestrial species of Carabidae (3), Staphylinidae (5), Histeridae (1), Elateridae (1), Cantharidae (1), Cleridae (1), Tenebrionidae (1), Meloidae (1), Anthicidae (1), Chrysomelidae (3), Curculionidae (7) and Apionidae (1) were identified from six species of <italic>Eryngium</italic> L. (Apiales: Apiaceae), two species of <italic>Guadua</italic> Kunth (Poales: Poaceae), <italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic> Lemaire (Poales: Bromeliaceae), and from fallen leaves of <italic>Euterpe edulis</italic> Martius (Arecales: Arecaceae) from the temperate and subtropical area. The highest species richness was recorded in <italic>Eryngium</italic> phytotelmata. Fifteen species of beetles inhabit <italic>Eryngium cabrerae</italic> Pontiroli, 11 in <italic>E. horridum</italic> Malme, 7 in <italic>E. stenophyllum</italic> Urban, 4 in <italic>E.</italic> aff. <italic>serra</italic> Chamisso and Schlechtendal., 3 in <italic>E. elegans</italic> Chamisso and Schlechtendal, 2 in <italic>E. eburneum</italic> Decne and <italic>E. pandanifolium</italic> Chamisso and Schlechtendal. From bamboo, 6 species of coleopterans were collected from <italic>Guadua trinii</italic> (Nees) Nees ex Ruprecht and 4 from <italic>G. chacoensis</italic> (Rojas) Londo&#x000f1;o and Peterson. Three species of aquatic coleopterans were recorded from <italic>A. distichantha</italic> and only one from <italic>E. edulis.</italic>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords
</title><kwd>Aquatic beetle</kwd><kwd><italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic></kwd><kwd>biodiversity</kwd><kwd><italic>Eryngium</italic> species</kwd><kwd><italic>Guadua</italic> species</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="18"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Phytotelmata are pools of water impounded by plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr52">Vargas 1928</xref>). The plants, for the most part, are living but the term phytotelmata also includes pools of water held ephemerally on concave surfaces of fallen leaves (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30">Kitching 1971</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr37">Maguire 1971</xref>). A specific community develops in these micro environments, establishing food chains where not only aquatic species but also terrestrial visiting species are involved (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20">Frank and Lounibos 1983</xref>). The phytotelmata are distributed in all continents except Antarctica, but diversity is greater in the tropics and subtropics. Approximately 1500 plant species where aquatic insects may find habitats suitable for their development (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16">Fish 1983</xref>) are known. Among the most studied phytotelmata, the Bromeliaceae native to the New World, the Heliconiaceae from South and Central America and Indonesia, and the Araceae of cosmopolitan distribution are highlighted. Pitcher plants (Sarraceniaceae and Nepenthaceae) are special phytotelmata due to their insectivorous characteristic. However, some organisms are able to survive in their digestive fluid (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr03">Beaver 1983</xref>). A subset of phytotelmata is the so-called dendrotelmata, cavities in hollow trees and stumps of bamboo (Poaceae), some of which can hold water for a long time.</p><p>The phytotelmata support a large number of species, mainly insects belonging to the order Odonata, Plecoptera, Trichoptera, Hemiptera, Coleoptera and Diptera. The latter are found in all types of phytotelmata, as opposed to other orders (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16">Fish 1983</xref>). Few identified species of beetles have been reported from phytotelmata, of which only members of the families Scirtidae, Dytiscidae, and Hydrophilidae are aquatic (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17">Frank 1983</xref>; Kitching 1983). The other families are mainly terrestrial and at least 20 are known from the Neotropical and Nearctic regions (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">Mestre et al. 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29">Junc&#x000e1; and Da Silva Borges 2002</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">Frank et al. 2004</xref>), although only the species of Staphylinidae were studied (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19">Frank and Barrera 2010</xref>).</p><p>These studies on aquatic beetles of Argentina were mostly taxonomic, but few were carried out on communities. We know of two studies involving communities of aquatic beetles of temperate and subtropical regions. One of them is about the structure and temporal change in the community of coleopterans inhabiting permanent, semi-permanent and temporary puddles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53">Von Ellenrieder and Fern&#x000e1;ndez 2000</xref>). The other is an inventory of species from a National Park in the subtropical region, where new distributions and species from Argentina are reported (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15">Fern&#x000e1;ndez et al. 2008</xref>). A third study, not exclusively on aquatic coleopterans, refers to the community of organisms that live in ephemeral pools, referring to beetles as potential predators of a flood-water mosquito (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr08">Campos et al. 2004</xref>). There are no studies that consider species lists or communities of beetles that live in or are associated with phytotelmata in Argentina, except the study of Montero et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40">2010</xref>) which cites coleopterans to family level, associated with <italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic> Lemaire (Poales: Bromeliaceae).</p><p>During previous studies on mosquitoes that inhabit phytotelmata, associated beetles with each phytotelmata class were collected without performing an exhaustive search. A preliminary report of phytotelmata and their aquatic and amphibious beetles collected from subtropical and temperate Argentina is presented here. This study includes occasional terrestrial beetles that use the same plants as refuge.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2a"><title>Study area</title><p>Field study was conducted from 1994 through 2009 in subtropical and temperate Argentina. The subtropical areas sampled were Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park (25&#x000b0; 39&#x02032; S, 54&#x000b0; 18&#x02032; W) and Chaco National Park (26&#x000b0; 45&#x02032; S and 59&#x000b0; 37&#x02032; W), and the temperate areas were Punta Lara Provincial Park (34&#x000b0; 51&#x02032; S and 57&#x000b0; 52&#x02032; W), and Ernesto Tornquist Provincial Park (38&#x000b0; 10&#x02032; S and 62&#x000b0; 8&#x02032; W) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f01_01">Figure 1</xref>).</p><p>Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park is located north of Misiones Province, separated from neighboring Brazil by the Iguaz&#x000fa; River. This park is part of the Paranense forest ecoregion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12">Dinerstein et al. 1995</xref>) with a topography and drainage pattern dominated by a basaltic plateau that reaches altitudes of 700 m. The annual rainfall varies from 1500 to 2000 mm, the dry season occurs in winter and abundant precipitations are recorded in summer. The mean temperature varies between 16 and 22&#x000b0; C. The dominant vegetation is the subtropical forest (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr01">APN 2009</xref>).</p><p>Chaco National Park is situated in Chaco Province and is part of the humid &#x0201c;Chaco&#x0201d; ecoregion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12">Dinerstein et al. 1995</xref>), a very gentle slope area dominated by depressed environments. It has a warm subtropical climate with summer rainfalls from 750 to 1300 mm. Within the protected area, forest environments, with savannahs, marshes and lagoons are found. The forest consists of trees that are 15 m tall, with the bottom layer covered by bromeliads with strong spines on the edge of their leaves, making the forest area almost impenetrable. Very dense areas of these formations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr01">APN 2009</xref>) are seen on the rivers.</p><p>Punta Lara Provincial Park is situated on the Rio de La Plata, northeast of Buenos Aires Province. The park area corresponds to the austral part of the Paranense forest ecoregion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12">Dinerstein et al. 1995</xref>), which in this area is characterized by a narrow gallery forest on the river. Under natural circumstances, daily floods occur with the tide. On the other side of the gallery forest, there is an open field. Annual rainfall is approximately 850 mm, and the temperature is mild.</p><p>&#x0201c;Ernesto Tornquist&#x0201d; Provincial Park is situated southeast of Buenos Aires Province in the Austral Pampeana ecoregion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12">Dinerstein et al. 1995</xref>). This area is characterized by a plain with extensive pastures from which a mountain range of Paleozoic origin emerges. The mountains measure 170 km long with a maximum height of 1243 MASL and are oriented from northwest to southeast (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26">Harrington 1947</xref>). The climate of the mountain is wet-subwet with scarce or null deficit of water (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr06">Burgos and Vidal 1951</xref>). Annual mean temperature and precipitations are 14&#x000b0; C and 896 mm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr48">SMN 1981</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr49">1986</xref>) with rains falling predominantly in the austral spring-summer period, and occasional snow falling in winter.</p></sec><sec id="sec2b"><title>Sampling</title><p>With the exception of bamboo, all phytotelmata were sampled by extracting the fluid contents with a pipette attached to a lift pump. After the first extraction, the plants were flushed twice with clean tap water, and the aquatic contents were extracted with a pipette after each wash. All insects were killed in the field and preserved in 80% commercial ethyl alcohol.</p><table-wrap id="t01_01" position="float"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><p>Coleopterns inhabiting phytotelmata (except trehole) at subtropical and temperate Argentina.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="t01_01"/></table-wrap><p>Due to the fact that the study was carried out in national parks where it was not possible to cut bamboo, samples were taken by making a hole with a drill in the middle of the internode and extracting the sample with a hose connected to a lift pump. Stump and broken bamboo were sampled again, and internodes were washed twice as with the other phytotelmata. Terrestrial beetles found on plants in the vicinity of phytotelmata were collected manually using entomological forceps.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><p>The identified phytotelmata were: <italic>Guadua trinii</italic> (Nees) Ness ex Ruprecht, <italic>Guadua chacoensis</italic> (Rojas) Londo&#x000f1;o and Peterson, <italic>Merostachys clausseni</italic> Munro (Poaceae), <italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic> Lemaire, <italic>Aechmea recurvata</italic> (Klotzsch), L.B. Smith, <italic>Billbergia nutans</italic> Wendland ex Regel, <italic>Pseudananas sagenarius</italic> (Arruda) Camargo, <italic>Vriesea friburgensis</italic> Mez, (Bromeliaceae), <italic>Eryngium</italic> sp. (Apiaceae), <italic>Alocasia odora</italic> (Lindl.) Hoch, <italic>Philodendron bipinnatifidum</italic> Schott ex Endlicher, (Araceae), <italic>Urera baccifera</italic> (L.) Gaudichaud-Beaupr&#x000e9; ex Weddell, (Urticaceae), <italic>Maranta</italic> sp. (Marantaceae), <italic>Euterpe edulis</italic> Martius, (Arecaceae), <italic>Dipsacus</italic> sp. (Dipsacaceae) at Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park, <italic>Aechmea distichanta</italic> and <italic>Eryngium</italic> sp. at Chaco National Park, <italic>Eryngium horridum</italic> Malme, <italic>Eryngium stenophyllum</italic> Urb., <italic>Eryngium</italic> aff. <italic>serra</italic> Cham. and Schltdl., <italic>Eryngium elegans</italic> Cham. and Schltdl. at Ernesto Tornquist Provincial Park, <italic>Androtrichum giganteum</italic> (Kunth) Pfeiff. (Cyperaceae), <italic>Guadua trinii, Eryngium cabrerae</italic> Pontiroli, <italic>Eryngium eburneum</italic> Decne, <italic>Eryngium pandanifolium</italic> Cham. and Schltdl., and <italic>Dipsacus</italic> sp. at Punta Lara Provincial Park. All except <italic>Alocasia odora</italic> and <italic>Dipsacus</italic> sp. are native phytotelmata.</p><p>From the above 21 classes of phytotelmata sampled, coleopterans were collected from <italic>A. distichantha, E. edulis,</italic> six species of <italic>Eryngium</italic> and two species of <italic>Guadua</italic> (48%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Eryngium</italic> species that are phytotelmata are morphologically similar to bromeliads (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f02_01">Figures 2</xref>, <xref ref-type="fig" rid="f03_01">3</xref>). The imbricate arrangement of their leaves delimits axils, as the peripheral leaves are older than the central ones. The internal axils hold free water and debris, the intermediate a semi-liquid interface composed mainly of debris and slime-fluxes, and the oldest, wet slime and debris. Thus, the real cavity where water is contained for a long time is limited to the axils of internal leaves. Water in external cavities is ephemeral and makes favorable habitats for semi-aquatic or terrestrial macro-invertebrates. Depending on the species, the size of the plants and the water retained by the axils was variable. The mean diameters were: <italic>E. cabrerae</italic> 83 cm (&#x000b1; SD 14.9); <italic>E. horridum</italic> 77 cm (&#x000b1; SD 0.17); <italic>E. stenophyllum</italic> 94 cm (&#x000b1; SD 0.23); <italic>E.</italic> aff. <italic>serra</italic> 46 cm (&#x000b1; SD 0.15); <italic>E. elegans</italic> 40 cm (&#x000b1; SD 0.11). The volumes of impound water were: 69.4 ml (&#x000b1; SD 43.1); 20.6 ml (&#x000b1; SD 14.2); 7.4 ml (&#x000b1; SD 6.6); 19.1 ml (&#x000b1; SD 17.1); 19.1 ml (&#x000b1; SD 17.1); 7.7 ml (&#x000b1; SD 12.3), respectively. No measures of <italic>E. eburneum</italic> were recorded.</p><p><italic>Guadua</italic> bamboos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f04_01">Figure 4</xref>) grow mainly in low places near streams, and can reach up to 12 meters. In the study area we observed two types of bamboo phytotelmata, one in the internodes that have one or more holes in the wall by the penetration of rain water (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f05_01">Figure 5</xref>) and the other in the stumps as a result of cutting bamboo (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f06_01">Figure 6</xref>). The longitude of the internodes, inlet holes and the volume of water retained into the internodes were different in each species of bamboo. <italic>Guadua chacoensis</italic> was the biggest, with a mean longitude, hole diameter and water volume of 23.3 cm (&#x000b1; SD 3.5), 9.1 mm (&#x000b1; SD 4.9) and 366.1 ml (&#x000b1; SD 225), while <italic>G. trinii</italic> was 23.1 cm (&#x000b1; SD 5.5), 6.1 mm (&#x000b1; SD 3.8) and 45.2 ml (&#x000b1; SD 41.1) respectively.</p><p><italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f07_01">Figure 7</xref>) is epiphytic or terricolous and was the dominant bromeliad in Chaco and Iguaz&#x000fa; subtropical parks. The volume of water impounded in its axils, sometimes several liters, was much greater than the volume in the axils of <italic>Eryngium.</italic></p><p>The fallen floral bracts of the palmetto <italic>Euterpe edulis</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f08_01">Figure 8</xref>) were the only type of phytotelmata found in this study in non-living parts of the plant. The bracts, which collect rain water in their inner cavity, are woody and more than one meter in length.</p><p>Sixteen families of coleopterans were recorded, fourteen from <italic>Eryngium</italic>, five from <italic>Guadua</italic>, three from <italic>A. distichantha</italic>, and one from <italic>E. edulis.</italic> Hydrophilidae, Histeridae, Elateridae, Cantharidae, Cleridae, Tenebrionidae, Meloidae, Anthicidae and Chrysomelidae were present exclusively in species of <italic>Eryngium</italic>, while chelonariids were found in <italic>Guadua</italic>, and Apionidae in <italic>A. distichantha.</italic> No exclusive family was found in <italic>E. edulis.</italic> Dytiscids were present in <italic>Eryngium</italic> and <italic>A. distichantha</italic>; scirtids in <italic>Eryngium</italic>, <italic>Guadua</italic> and <italic>A. distichantha</italic>; staphylinids in <italic>Eryngium</italic>, <italic>Guadua</italic> and <italic>E. edulis</italic>, and curculionids in <italic>Eryngium</italic> and <italic>Guadua.</italic> Among aquatic coleopterans, <italic>Enochrus (Hugoscottia)</italic> sp. (Hydrophilidae) and unidentified Scirtidae were collected in the larval stage, while <italic>Copelatus</italic> sp., <italic>Liodessus</italic> sp. (Dytiscidae), <italic>Phaenonotum</italic> sp., <italic>Paracymus</italic> sp., <italic>Tropisternus setiger</italic> (Hydrophilidae) were collected as adults (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>). Semi-aquatic species were represented by Chelonariidae larvae and Curculionidae by <italic>Tyloderma</italic> adults (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>).</p><p>Families of terrestrial beetles were Carabidae, Staphylinidae, Histeridae, Tenebrionidae, Elateridae, Cantharidae, Cleridae, Meloidae, Anthicidae, Chrysomelidae and Curculionidae (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>). The weevil <italic>Heilipodus erythropus</italic> (Klug) (Coleoptera, Curculionidae) was the only species collected in both larval and adult stages from <italic>Eryngium horridum.</italic> Larvae of this weevil were observed drilling the stalk of inflorescence and adults living in axils.</p><p>The greatest diversity of coleopterans (27 species) was found in <italic>Eryngium</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>); the largest percentage of species was collected from <italic>E. cabrerae</italic> (56%), followed by <italic>E. horridum</italic> (41%), <italic>E. stenophyllum</italic> (26%), <italic>E.</italic> aff. <italic>serra</italic> (15%), <italic>E. elegans</italic> (11%), and <italic>E. eburneum</italic> and <italic>E. pandanifolium</italic> (7%). Beetles were poorly represented in <italic>E. edulis</italic>, <italic>A. distichantha</italic> and in both <italic>Guadua</italic> bamboos (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f09_01">Figure 9</xref>). No species inhabiting <italic>Eryngium</italic> were observed in <italic>Guadua</italic> or <italic>E. edulis.</italic> Only <italic>Liodessus</italic> sp. was found both in <italic>Eryngium</italic> and in <italic>A. distichantha</italic> (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>).</p></sec><sec sec-type="discussion" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>Among the 21 classes of phytotelmata reported here, 15 correspond to the subtropical northern area, and nine to the temperate area. Coleopterans were only recorded in <italic>Eryngium</italic>, <italic>Guadua</italic>, <italic>A. distichantha</italic> and <italic>E. edulis.</italic> The species of <italic>Eryngium</italic> are dominant in temperate areas (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr07">Campos 2010</xref>), while the species of <italic>Guadua</italic> are distributed in the subtropical area, extending in the temperate area along a narrow strip of forest on La Plata River. <italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic> and <italic>E. edulis</italic> are subtropical.</p><p>Five families of aquatic coleopterans have been related to phytotelmata in the Neotropical region. A recent review carried out by Frank and Lounibos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">2008</xref>) cites representatives of the families Scirtidae, Dytiscidae and Hydrophilidae inhabiting bromeliads. Other phytotelmata, like bamboo and fallen flower bracts of a palm, also include a few species of the families Elmidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr46">Sanchez and Liria 2009</xref>) and Noteridae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>), respectively. On the other hand, the diversity of terrestrial beetles that visit phytotelmata is higher. A study carried out in southern Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">Mestre et al. 2001</xref>) shows that the bromeliad <italic>Vriesea inflata</italic> (Wawra) Wawra is visited by species of 13 families of terrestrial coleopterans. However, other authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">Gutierrez Ochoa et al. 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23">Greeney 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">Frank et al. 2004</xref>) mentioned other families not cited by Mestre et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">2001</xref>) that use bromeliads and other phytotelmata to hide or find prey, summarizing at least 20 families. In accordance with Frank and Lounibos (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">2008</xref>), representative species of three families of aquatic coleopterans were recorded from phytotelmata of Argentina other than bromeliads. In contrast with the numerous terrestrial coleopterans known, only species of 12 families were recorded, probably due to the lack of an exhaustive search. Several studies show that coleopterans are a taxon of scarce richness and abundance in the communities living in phytotelmata. The exceptions were observed in invertebrate communities of the bromeliads <italic>Vriesea extensa</italic> Sm. (Synon.: <italic>Alcantarea extensa</italic> (Sm.) Grant) and <italic>Vriesea inflata</italic> where a Carabidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29">Junc&#x000e1; and Borges 2002</xref>) and a Scirtidae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">Mestre et al. 2001</xref>), respectively, were dominant although richness was low, contrary to the high species richness (in particular Dytiscidae) observed in fallen floral bracts of a palm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>). In our study, although not quantified, the small number of beetles was highly contrasting with dipterans and other arthropods in all sampled phytotelmata.</p><sec id="sec4a"><title>Aquatic Coleopterans</title><p>Dytiscidae &#x02014; Species of four genera of Dytiscidae have been cited in the literature as inhabitants of phytotelmata (<italic>sensu lato</italic>): <italic>Copelatus</italic> Erichson and <italic>Desmopachria</italic> Babington in bromeliads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23">Greeney 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Frank and Lounibos 2008</xref>) and in fallen flower bracts of the stilt-root palm <italic>Iriartea deltoidea</italic> Ruiz and Pavon (Arecaceae: Iriarteeae), and <italic>Laccophillus</italic> Leach and <italic>Thermonectus</italic> Dejean in this last phytotelmata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>). In our study, adults of unidentified species of the genus <italic>Copelatus</italic> and <italic>Liodessus</italic> Guignot dwelling in the axils of <italic>Eryngium</italic> and <italic>Liodessus</italic> and in the axils of <italic>A. distichantha</italic> were found. As adults were scarce and no immatures were found, it is presumed that these could be opportunistic species, which use water from the axils when the pools dry up.</p><p>Hydrophilidae &#x02014; There are two subfamilies with species that inhabit phytotelmata, Sphaeridiinae and Hydrophilinae. Subfamily Sphaeridiinae is found in a great diversity of habitats, mainly terrestrial, but in some cases some species of this subfamily are secondarily aquatic, while Hydrophilinae are mostly aquatic and are found in most freshwater environments (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr02">Archangelsky 2004</xref>). All the species specialized in living in Bromeliaceae are Sphaeridiinae subfamily and belong to the genera <italic>Coelostoma</italic> Brull&#x000e9;, <italic>Lachnodacnum</italic> Orchymont, <italic>Phaenonotum</italic> Sharp, <italic>Omicrus</italic> Sharp (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Frank and Lounibos 2008</xref>). Other members of this subfamily are <italic>Dactylosternum</italic> Wollaston and <italic>Pelosoma</italic> Mulsant, which were found inhabiting in fallen flower bracts of a palm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>). The genera of Hydrophilinae that were reported from phytotelmata are <italic>Hydrobiomorpha</italic> Blackburn, <italic>Enochrus</italic> Thomson and <italic>Derallus</italic> Sharp, all collected as adults from fallen floral bracts of a palm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>). The only record of a hydrophilid inhabiting treeholes in the Neotropic region was quoted by H. F. Greeney as unpublished data in &#x0201c;The insects of plant-held water: a review and bibliography&#x0201d; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23">Greeney 2001</xref>), and did not mention the genus. During our sampling, we found <italic>Tropisternus setiger</italic> (Germar), <italic>Paracymus</italic> sp. (adults) and <italic>Enochrus</italic> sp. (larva), all Hydrophilinae, and <italic>Phaenonotum</italic> sp. (adults) a Sphaeridiinae, living in the axils of four <italic>Eryngium</italic> phytotelmata. <italic>T. setiger</italic> is a ubiquitous species that lives in ephemeral (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr08">Campos et al. 2004</xref>), temporary, and permanent pools (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr53">Von Ellenrieder and Fern&#x000e1;ndez 2000</xref>) and therefore it cannot be regarded as a specific inhabitant of phytotelmata. Its habit of oviposition on aquatic vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27">Jerez and Moroni 2006</xref>) limits its possibility of developing in the axils of <italic>Eryngium</italic> or other phytotelmata. <italic>Enochrus</italic> is a widely distributed genus living in temporary and permanent environments, whose females lay egg cases that adhere to the underside of the leaves of the floating <italic>Azolla filiculoides</italic> Lamarck (Salviniales: Azollaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14">Fern&#x000e1;ndez 1992</xref>). <italic>Eryngium</italic> phytotelmata are frequently partially submerged in floodwater puddles, where dense vegetation is formed dominated by <italic>A. filiculoides.</italic> When the pond dries up this small plant is retained in the axils (Campos unpublished data), and can contain larvae or egg cases of <italic>Enochrus</italic> between its leaves. This would explain the presence of <italic>Enochrus</italic> larvae in the leaf axils of <italic>E. cabrerae</italic> as was observed in this study.</p><p>Scirtidae &#x02014; Is the most abundant family of coleopterans that inhabit phytotelmata, mainly treeholes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23">Greeney 2001</xref>), bamboo (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35">Louton et al. 1996</xref>), and bromeliads (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43">Ospina-Bautista et al. 2004</xref>). There are five genera known from phytotelmata: <italic>Scirtes</italic> Illiger (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44">Picado 1913</xref>), <italic>Cyphon</italic> Paykull, <italic>Ora</italic> Clark (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">Frank et al 2004</xref>), <italic>Prionocyphon</italic> Redtenbacher (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr54">White 1978</xref>), and <italic>Flavohelodes</italic> Klausnitzer (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr51">Stribling and Young 1990</xref>), whose larval habits are mainly detritivorous converting the leaf litter into fine particles which benefit fine particle feeders co-occurring in the same phytotelmata (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11">Daugherty and Juliano 2003</xref>). Scirtid species from South America are little known, and the only genera cited as phytotelmata inhabitants are <italic>Scirtes</italic>, and <italic>Cyphon</italic> collected from Bromeliaceae in Colombia (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr43">Ospina-Bautista et al. 2004</xref>) and Venezuela (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr34">Liria 2007</xref>), respectively. Other studies carried out in Brazil (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">Mestre et al. 2001</xref>), Per&#x000fa; (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr35">Louton et al. 1996</xref>) and Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr40">Montero et al. 2010</xref>) mentioned Scirtidae living in bromeliads and bamboo without indicating their identity. In this study, larvae of three morpho-species living in <italic>Guadua, A. distichantha</italic> and <italic>Eryngium</italic> phytotelmata in both subtropical and temperate areas were found. However, they could not be identified because they were not reared to the adult stage (and because there are no keys to Argentinian scirtid larvae).</p></sec><sec id="secsec4b"><title>Hydrophilic or semi-aquatic Coleopterans</title><p>Chelonaridae &#x02014; This family is little known and has been found in association with treeholes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50">Spangler 1980</xref>) and bromeliads, apparently feeding on decaying plant matter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10">Costa et al. 1988</xref>). However, there is still controversy over whether or not their larvae are aquatic. Spangler (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr50">1980</xref>), in contrast with others authors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr04">Boving and Craighead 1931</xref>), concludes that these larvae are not aquatic because they do not have real anal gills and attributes their presence in aquatic environments as a consequence of the moss being washed off of their habitat. Only a few larvae are known and little is known of their behavior. More research could reveal unknown species that inhabit phytotelmata that could be adapted to aquatic life. In this study, we reported unidentified Chelonaridae larvae inhabiting bamboo internodes (<italic>Guadua chacoensis</italic> and <italic>G. trinii</italic>). The presence of these larvae in a habitat of vertical and smooth walls, such as bamboo internodes where there is not an interface between water and decaying matter (as in axils of bromeliads and treeholes), would suggest that these species are better adapted to live in an aquatic environment. Because the behavior of Chelonaridae species is unknown, this hypothesis should be tested.</p><p>Curculionidae - Of the 131 species of semi-aquatic weevils (Curculionidae, Erirhinidae and Dryophthoridae) known from Argentina (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42">Morrone and O'Brien 1999</xref>), we collected an unidentified specie of the genus <italic>Tyloderma.</italic> Lanteri et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33">2002</xref>) reports that 12 species of <italic>Tyloderma</italic> in Argentina are associated with aquatic macrophytes. We found abundant individuals of <italic>Tyloderma</italic> living in axils of <italic>E. horridum</italic>, but none was immersed in water.</p></sec><sec id="sec4c"><title>Terrestrial Coleopterans</title><p>This group is composed of beetles that use phytotelmata as refuge or searching for prey, and as already mentioned, is represented by many families. Some species are closely associated with the plant host, while others are occasional. The families that were found during our study are discussed below.</p><p>Carabidae &#x02014; The species which live associated with phytotelmata were only mentioned as inhabitants of Bromeliaceae and belong to <italic>Agra</italic> Fabricius, <italic>Calathus</italic> Bonelli, <italic>Callida</italic> Latreille and Dejean, <italic>Colpodes</italic> MacLeay, <italic>Lebia</italic> Latreille, <italic>Lia</italic> Eschscholtz, <italic>Onypterigia</italic> Dejean, <italic>Phloeoxena</italic> Chaudoir, <italic>Pterostichus</italic> Bonelli, (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32">Laessle 1961</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">Zaragoza 1974</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">Guti&#x000e9;rrez et al. 1993</xref>) and <italic>Platynus</italic> Bonelli (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr41">Montes de Oca et al. 2007</xref>) that were collected in Jamaica and Mexico. Less specialized Carabidae were found occasionally, looking for prey in fallen floral bracts of a palm in Ecuador (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>). During this study, a conspicuous larva of the genus <italic>Pachyteles</italic> Perty, characterized by a widened eighth abdominal segment and sensory bristles that work like a trap when capturing prey, was found in the internodes of <italic>Guadua</italic> bamboo. This eighth modified segment (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="f10_01">Figure 10</xref>) is used to plug the opening of the gallery in which they live (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10">Costa et al. 1988</xref>). Our observations revealed that the larvae of <italic>Pachyteles</italic> sp., reared in bamboo internodes that contained the original sediment and water, dived to the bottom, from which they extracted debris with their mandibles and built a cell compartment on the inner wall of the internodes. It was verified that they are good predators of Isoptera and other small insects because, when feeding, the body bends towards the last abdominal segment and adopts a V form (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10">Costa et al. 1988</xref>). It was also observed that the community of macro-invertebrates living in bamboo internodes is very diverse (unpublished data), and the free water space is occupied by various terrestrial insects, even by termite and ant nests. For this reason, <italic>Pachyteles</italic> larvae could be considered one of the top predators within this community. On the other hand, the unique individual of the unidentified Carabidae collected from <italic>Eryngium cabrerae</italic> is a terrestrial species considered a visitor.</p><p>Staphylinidae &#x02014; This familiy is represented in communities of bromeliads (e. g. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr44">Picado 1913</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr36">L&#x000fc;derwaldt 1915</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">Zaragoza 1974</xref>), fallen floral bracts of a palm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">Greeney 2004</xref>), and from inflorescences of several species of <italic>Heliconia</italic> L. (Zingiberales: Heliconiaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19">Frank and Barrera 2010</xref>). Six species of Staphylinidae were collected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01_01">Table 1</xref>). <italic>Loncovilius</italic> sp., <italic>Pinophilus</italic> sp. and <italic>Stenus</italic> sp. were present exclusively in the axils of the species of <italic>Eryngium. Loncovilius</italic> sp. was most abundant mainly in <italic>Eryngium cabrerae.</italic> An unidentified adult and larva were collected from species of <italic>Guadua</italic> and from fallen floral bracts of <italic>E. edulis</italic>, respectively. All species could be considered as potential top predators from the aquatic communities because they can prey on various species of aquatic larvae as was observed by Greeney (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">2004</xref>) and Frank and Barrera (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19">2010</xref>) during studies carried out in communities inhabiting the fallen floral bracts of a palm, and flower bracts of <italic>Heliconia</italic>, respectively.</p><p>Histeridae - The only species of this family associated with phytotelmata, <italic>Omalodes sobrinus</italic> Erichson, was reported from <italic>Bromelia hemisphaerica</italic> Lamarck 1783 of Mexico, and was listed as a very scarce herbivore (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">Guti&#x000e9;rrez et al. 1993</xref>). We reported an unidentified species associated with <italic>E. cabrerae</italic> in temperate areas, which was also of very low abundance.</p><p>Elateridae - Few studies have been done on Elateridae associated with phytotelmata. Zaragoza (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">1974</xref>) cited Elateridae inhabiting phytotelmata to species level. The species cited were: <italic>Platycrepidius boucardi</italic> (Salle), <italic>Megapenthes cincticollis</italic> Champion, <italic>Ischiodontus anceps</italic> Cand&#x000e8;ze, and <italic>Anchastus seminiger</italic> Champion, inhabiting the bromeliad <italic>Aechmea bracteata</italic> (Swartz) Grisebach in Mexico. Domingues et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13">1989</xref>) reported larvae of unidentified Elateridae inhabiting epiphytic bromeliads in Brazil and Mestre et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">2001</xref>) found unidentified adults of Elateridae in the epiphytic <italic>Vriesea inflata</italic> (Bromeliaceae), but not in terrestrial ones. While Frank et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">2004</xref>) reported <italic>Conoderus amplicollis</italic> (Gyllenhal) inhabiting <italic>Tillandsia recurvata</italic> (Linnaeus) L. in USA. We reported an unidentified species associated with the terrestrial <italic>E. horridum</italic> (Apiaceae).</p><p>Cantharidae - The only record of Cantharidae is <italic>Chauliognathus tripartitus</italic> Chevrolat inhabiting <italic>Vriesea</italic> sp. from Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">Zaragoza 1974</xref>). In our study, we found few larvae of unidentified Cantharidae inhabiting two species of <italic>Eryngium</italic> that could be considered occasional predators that use phytotelmata to hide in or find prey.</p><p>Cleridae and Meloidae &#x02014; This is the first record of representatives of these families of coleopterans associated with phytotelmata. We found adults in <italic>E. horridum</italic>, but unfortunately, their identification was not possible.</p><p>Tenebrionidae - There are few reports of associated Tenebrionidae to phytotelmata, all of them referring to Bromeliaceae. <italic>Goniadera oculata</italic> Champion, <italic>Eurymepoton</italic> sp. and <italic>Eleodes</italic> sp. were cited inhabiting <italic>A.</italic>
<italic>bracteata</italic>, <italic>Tillandsia caputmedusae</italic> Morren, and <italic>Vriesea chiapensis</italic> Matuda, respectively (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">Zaragoza 1974</xref>). <italic>Stibia</italic> sp. was found associated with <italic>Bromelia hemisphaerica</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">Guti&#x000e9;rrez et al. 1993</xref>) and <italic>Glyptotus cribratus</italic> LeConte to <italic>Tillandsia fasciculata</italic> Swartz, the latter in the Nearctic region (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">Frank et al. 2004</xref>).</p><p>Another unidentified tenebrionid was found in terrestrial and epiphytic <italic>Vriesea inflata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr39">Mestre et al. 2001</xref>). The ecological niche of the phytotelmic species is unknown; however, Zaragoza (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">1974</xref>) classified them as detritivorous because they feed on the debris that accumulates in the leaf axils. In the present study, we report <italic>Rhypasma quadricollis</italic> (Fairmaire) associated with <italic>Eryngium cabrerae</italic>, a phytotelmata different from bromeliads.</p><p>Anthicidae - The only species of this family reported from phytotelmata is <italic>Anthicus asphaltinus</italic> Champion, collected in Mexico from <italic>B. hemisphaerica</italic>, which was considered scarcely abundant and its ecological niche unknown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">Guti&#x000e9;rrez et al. 1993</xref>). We collected an identified specimen from <italic>E. stenophyllum.</italic></p><p>Apionidae: The genus <italic>Apion</italic>, classified as Curculionidae and Brentidae by other authors, was reported from <italic>A. bracteata</italic>, <italic>Vriesea chiapensis</italic> (Bromeliaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr55">Zaragoza 1974</xref>), and <italic>T. fasciculata</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">Frank et al. 2004</xref>). We report a species of the same genus inhabiting <italic>A. distichantha</italic>, in the subtropical area.</p><p>Chrysomelidae &#x02014; Although most of the Chrysomelidae are terrestrial, some (Donaciinae, Chrysomelinae and Galerucinae) exhibit some degree of adaptation to aquatic life (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31">Konstantinov 2003</xref>). The few species of Chrysomelidae reported as inhabitants of phytotelmata are of terrestrial habits and feed on the leaves of the host plant (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Frank and Lounibos 2008</xref>). <italic>Acentroptera pulchella</italic> Gu&#x000e9;rin-M&#x000e9;neville (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr38">Mantovani et al. 2005</xref>) of Brazil, <italic>Calliaspis rubra</italic> (Olivier) of Peru (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr05">Burgess et al. 2003</xref>), and <italic>Pachybrachys</italic> sp. of Mexico (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">Gutierrez et al. 1993</xref>) were reported from Bromeliaceae, while some species of <italic>Systena</italic> Chevrolat were found associated with <italic>Eryngium</italic> (Apiaceae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28">Jolivet and Hawkeswood 1995</xref>). No aquatic Chrysomelidae were reported from any phytotelmata. The three species collected during the present study were associated with <italic>Eryngium</italic> spp. One of these was an unidentified cassidine; the others, <italic>Chrysodina cuprescens</italic> Boheman and <italic>Systena</italic> sp., are polyphagous, but only the latter was cited feeding on the leaves of <italic>Eryngium</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28">Jolivet and Hawkeswood 1995</xref>).</p><p>Curculionidae &#x02014; This family is the most extensive of the terrestrial coleopterans associated with phytotelmata, and its species were reported mainly from Bromeliaceae, a major pest of these plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18">Frank 1999</xref>). In their 2002 review, Lanteri et al. reported that <italic>H. erythropus</italic> and <italic>Tonesia argentinica</italic> Hustache were the only curculionid associated with <italic>Eryngium</italic> species in Argentina. We also report, <italic>Napactus dives</italic> Klug associated with <italic>E. horridum</italic>, and <italic>Aramigus tessellates</italic> (Say) associated with <italic>E. horridum</italic>, <italic>E. stenophyllum</italic> and <italic>E. cabrerae.</italic> We also report an unidentified species of Curculionidae from <italic>Guadua</italic> bamboo. <italic>Heilipodus erythropus</italic> is a species extensively distributed in Argentina and neighboring countries (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33">Lanteri et al. 2002</xref>). It was the most abundant in our study and was collected from five species of <italic>Eryngium.</italic> Its larvae drill the inside of the stem of the inflorescence of <italic>Eryngium paniculatum</italic> Cavanilles and Dombey, where they develop their life cycle and later pupate in the root (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr45">R&#x000ed;os de Saluso 1997</xref>). De Saluso mentioned that this weevil was found exclusively on <italic>Eryngium</italic>, but an old report cited this Curculionidae causing damage to Bromeliacaea (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr47">Silva et al. 1968</xref>). Although <italic>H. erythropus</italic> is not cited by Morrone and O'Brien (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr42">1999</xref>) as a semi-aquatic species, it was observed in the field that when the adult is disturbed, it dives into the water where it remains for several minutes until the danger disappears (Campos unpublished data). This behavior was observed several times, even without touching the plant. The mere shadow of our approach made them take refuge in the water. <italic>Tonesia argentinica</italic> was reported inhabiting <italic>E. paniculatum</italic> in subtropical Chaco Province. We found an identified species of this genus associated with <italic>E. cabrerae</italic> in temperate Buenos Aires Province.</p><p>Species of Elateridae, Meloidea, Chrysomelidae, and Curculionidae were observed not only in the axils of <italic>Eryngium</italic> phytotelmata, but also on inflorescence during the hottest hours, taking refuge in the axils in the morning or during drier periods. These species might not be interacting in the aquatic community, except for their input of organic matter as a consequence of their stools.</p><p>The terrestrial beetle community associated with phytotelmata in the subtropical and temperate region of Argentina was richer in species than the aquatic community. Most species of terrestrial beetles found in this study are ubiquitous, being associated with other plants that are not phytotelmata. However, some staphylinids species seem to be exclusive inquilines of <italic>Eryngium</italic>, interacting with the aquatic community as predators. Another specific beetle is the weevil <italic>H. erythropus</italic> whose life cycle takes place in different parts of the plant. Among the aquatic beetles that inhabit <italic>Eryngium</italic>, none of them was specific. All the species found in this study use aquatic environments other than phytotelmata. A possible hypothesis is that the presence of ubiquitous species in phytotelmata could be a strategy of displacement to other aquatic environments, using these plants occasionally and for a short time. Richness of beetles in <italic>Guadua</italic> bamboo was low, however the most common and abundant inhabitant was the carabid <italic>Pachyteles.</italic> For their behavior and their habit of constructing cells within internodes, one could hypothesize that it is a species closely associated with this type of micro-habitat interacting with phytotelmata through the removal of sediment and providing nutrients as a product of excrements. On the other hand, the scarcity of water beetles could be due to the relative smallness of the inlets which, being located in the side wall of the internodes, could not be detected by most ubiquitous species. The only water beetles found in the stumps were scirtids, which are also common inhabitants of treeholes. Their presence could be due to the similarity of bamboo stumps with treeholes.</p><p>The number of coleopterans associated with phytotelmata in Argentina may increase with the exploration of the subtropical forest of the Yungas, located in the northwest. We believe that the same will happen with the diversity of plants that function as phytotelmata. However, the development of comprehensive lists could be limited by the scarce taxonomic knowledge of the Neotropical coleopterans.</p><fig id="f01_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 1. </label><caption><p>Location of sampling sites in Argentina, South America. Subtropical area, INP: Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park (Misiones Province); CNP: Chaco National Park (Chaco Province); Temperate area, PLP: Punta Lara Provincial Park; ETP: &#x0201c;Ernesto Tornquist&#x0201d; Provincial Park (Buenos Aires Province). High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f01_01"/></fig><fig id="f02_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 2. </label><caption><p><italic>Eryngium horridum</italic> Malme (Apiaceae) at the field site in Sierra de la Ventana, Buenos Aires Province. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f02_01"/></fig><fig id="f03_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 3. </label><caption><p><italic>Eryngium</italic> aff. <italic>serra</italic> Cham. and Schltdl. (Apiaceae) at the field site in Sierra de la Ventana, Buenos Aires Province. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f03_01"/></fig><fig id="f04_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 4. </label><caption><p><italic>Guadua chacoensis</italic> (Rojas) Londo&#x000f1;o and Peterson (Poaceae) at the forest site in Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park, Misiones Province. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f04_01"/></fig><fig id="f05_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 5. </label><caption><p>Internodes of <italic>Guadua chacoensis</italic> (Rojas) Londo&#x000f1;o and Peterson (Poaceae) with a hole in the wall. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f05_01"/></fig><fig id="f06_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 6. </label><caption><p>Stumps of <italic>Guadua chacoensis</italic> (Rojas) Londo&#x000f1;o and Peterson (Poaceae). High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f06_01"/></fig><fig id="f07_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 7. </label><caption><p><italic>Aechmea distichantha</italic> Lemaire (Bromeliaceae) at the field site in Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park, Misiones Province. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f07_01"/></fig><fig id="f08_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 8. </label><caption><p>Fallen floral bracts of the palmetto <italic>Euterpe edulis</italic> Martius (Arecaceae) at the field site in Iguaz&#x000fa; National Park, Misiones Province. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f08_01"/></fig><fig id="f09_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 9. </label><caption><p>Number of species of coleopterans by class of phytotelmata from subtropical and temperate Argentina. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f09_01"/></fig><fig id="f10_01" fig-type="figure" position="float"><label>Figure 10. </label><caption><p>Habitus of larva of <italic>Pachyteles</italic> sp. (Carabidae), A: dorsal ; B: lateral. High quality figures are available online.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="f10_01"/></fig></sec></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank the Administraci&#x000f3;n de Parques Nacionales, Delegaci&#x000f3;n Regional Noreste (APN), Centro de Investigaciones Ecol&#x000f3;gicas Subtropicales (CIES), and Administraci&#x000f3;n de Areas Protegidas y Conservaci&#x000f3;n de la Biodiversidad, Ministerio de Asuntos Agrarios de la Provincia de Buenos Aires for logistic help and licence conceded. We also thank Motoyoshi Mogi (Saga University, Japan), Victoria Sy (ILPLA, UNLP-CONICET), and Eduardo Lestani (Universidad Nacional de C&#x000f3;rdoba) for their help in field work, and the following scientists for taxonomic determination of specimens: Susana Mart&#x000ed;nez (<italic>Eryngium</italic> species) (Facultad de Ciencias Exactas y Naturales, Universidad de Buenos Aires), Anal&#x000ed;a Lanteri (Curculionidae), Nora Cabrera (Chrysomelidae) (Facultad de Ciencias Naturales y Museo de La Plata, UNLP), Mariana Chani Posse (Staphylinidae), Gustavo Flores (Tenebrionidae) (Instituto Argentino de Investigaciones en Zonas &#x000c1;ridas, IADIZA - CONICET). Finally, we are grateful to M&#x000f3;nica Caviglia for help with the English translation. This research was supported by Grant 5924, and International Cooperati&#x000f3;n Project D 1369 from Consejo Nacional de Investigaciones Cient&#x000ed;ficas y T&#x000e9;cnicas (CONICET), Argentina. This is a contribution of the Instituto de Limnolog&#x000ed;a Journal Series No 885.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="parsed"><title>References</title><ref id="bibr01"><element-citation publication-type="inbook">
<collab>APN</collab><year>2009</year><article-title>Administraci&#x000f3;n de Parques Nacionales.</article-title><comment>Available online, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.parquesnacionales.gov.ar">http://www.parquesnacionales.gov.ar</ext-link></comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr02"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Archangelsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Higher-level phylogeny of Hydrophylinae (Coleoptera: Hydrophilidae) based on larval, pupal and adult characters.</article-title>
<source><italic>Systematic Entomology</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>188</fpage>
<lpage>214</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr03"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beaver</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year><article-title>The communities living in <italic>Nepenthes</italic> pitcher plants: fauna and food webs.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>
<source><italic>Phytotelmata: terrestrial plants as hosts of aquatic insects communities</italic></source><fpage>29</fpage><lpage>54</lpage><publisher-name>Plexus Inc.</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr04"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boving</surname><given-names>AG</given-names></name><name><surname>Craighead</surname><given-names>FC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1931</year>
<article-title>Illustrated synopsis of the principal larval forms of the order Coleoptera.</article-title>
<source><italic>Entomologica Americana</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>352</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr05"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowman</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Observations of a beetle herbivore on a bromeliad in Peru.</article-title>
<source>Journal of the Bromeliad Society</source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>221</fpage>
<lpage>224</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr06"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Vidal</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1951</year>
<article-title>Los climas de la rep&#x000fa;blica Argentina seg&#x000fa;n la nueva clasificaci&#x000f3;n de Thornthwaite.</article-title>
<source><italic>Meteoros</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>32</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr07"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>
<italic>Eryngium</italic> (Apiaceae) phytotelmata and their macro-invertebrates communities, including a review and bibliography.</article-title>
<source><italic>Hydrobiologia</italic></source>
<volume>652</volume>
<fpage>311</fpage>
<lpage>328</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr08"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sy</surname><given-names>VE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Study of insects associated with the floodwater mosquito <italic>Ochlerotatus albifasciatus</italic> (Diptera: Culicidae) and their posible predators in Buenos Aires Province, Argentina.</article-title>
<source><italic>Hydrobiologia</italic></source>
<volume>524</volume>
<fpage>91</fpage>
<lpage>102</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr09"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cave</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>
<italic>Trigonopeltastes delta</italic> (Coleoptera: Scarabaeidae: Cetoniinae) larva developing in a bromeliad terrarium.</article-title>
<source><italic>Coleopterist Bulletin</italic></source>
<volume>59</volume>
<fpage>527</fpage>
<lpage>528</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Costa</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Vanin</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Casari</surname><given-names>Chen SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1988</year><source><italic>Larvas de Coleoptera do Brasil.</italic></source><publisher-name>Museum de Zoolog&#x000ed;a, Universidade de S&#x000e3;o Paulo</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Brazil</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Daugherty</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Juliano</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Leaf scraping beetle feces are a food resource for tree hole mosquito larvae.</article-title>
<source><italic>The American Midland Naturalist</italic></source>
<volume>150</volume>
<fpage>181</fpage>
<lpage>184</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Dinerstein</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name><name><surname>Graham</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Primm</surname><given-names>SA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bookbinder</surname><given-names>MP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ledec</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year><source><italic>Una evaluaci&#x000f3;n del estado de conservaci&#x000f3;n de las ecoregiones terrestres de Am&#x000e9;rica Latina y el Caribe.</italic></source><publisher-name>WWF and World Bank</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Washington D.C.</publisher-loc>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Domingues</surname><given-names>RAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Pugialli</surname><given-names>HRL</given-names></name><name><surname>Dietz</surname><given-names>JM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Densidade e diversidade de fauna fitotelmata em brom&#x000e9;lias de quatro tipos de florestas degradadas.</article-title>
<source><italic>Revista Brasileira de Biologia</italic></source>
<volume>49</volume>
<fpage>125</fpage>
<lpage>129</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Descripci&#x000f3;n de la ooteca y estadios larvales de <italic>Enochrus (Hugoscottia) scutellaris</italic> (Bruch) y <italic>Enochrus (Methydrus) vulgaris</italic> (Steinheil) (Coleoptera, Hydrophilidae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Revista de la Sociedad Entomol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</italic></source>
<volume>50</volume>
<fpage>343</fpage>
<lpage>349</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Archangelsky</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Manzo</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Cole&#x000f3;pteros acu&#x000e1;ticos del Parque Provincial Salto Encantado y valle del Cu&#x000f1;a Pir&#x000fa; (Misiones, Argentina).</article-title>
<source><italic>Revista de la Sociedad Entomol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</italic></source>
<volume>67</volume>
<fpage>87</fpage>
<lpage>98</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Fish</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year><article-title>Phytotelmata: flora and fauna.</article-title><article-title>Phytotelmata: terrestrial plants as hosts of aquatic insects communities.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>
<source><italic>Phytotelmata: terrestrial plants as hosts of aquatic insects communities</italic></source><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>27</lpage><publisher-name>Plexus Inc.</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year><article-title>Bromeliad phytotelmata and their biota, especially mosquitoes.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>
<source><italic>Phytotelmata: terrestrial plants as hosts of aquatic insects communities</italic></source><fpage>101</fpage><lpage>128</lpage><publisher-name>Plexus Inc.</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Bromeliad-eating weevils.</article-title>
<source><italic>Selbyana</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>40</fpage>
<lpage>48</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Barrera</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Natural history of <italic>Belonuchus</italic> Normann spp. and allies (Coleoptera: Staphylinidae) in <italic>Heliconia</italic> L. (Zingiberales: Heliconiaceae) flower bracts.</article-title>
<source><italic>Insecta Mundi</italic></source>
<volume>110</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>11</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1983</year><source><italic>Phytotelmata: terrestrial plants as hosts of aquatic insects communities.</italic></source><publisher-name>Plexus Inc.</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lounibos</surname><given-names>LP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Insects and allies associated with bromeliads: a review.</article-title>
<source><italic>Terrestrial Arthropod Rewiews</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>125</fpage>
<lpage>153</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Frank</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Sreenivasan</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Benshoff</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Deyrup</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>GB</given-names></name><name><surname>Halbert</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamon</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Lowman</surname><given-names>MD</given-names></name><name><surname>Mockford</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Scheffran</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Steck</surname><given-names>GJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Thomas</surname><given-names>MC</given-names></name><name><surname>Walker</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Welbourn</surname><given-names>WC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Invertebrate animals extracted from native <italic>Tillandsia</italic> (Bromeliales: Bromeliaceae) in Sarasota County, Florida.</article-title>
<source><italic>Florida Entomologist</italic></source>
<volume>87</volume>
<fpage>176</fpage>
<lpage>185</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greeney</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>The insects of plant-held waters: a review and bibliography.</article-title>
<source><italic>Journal of Tropical Ecology</italic></source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>241</fpage>
<lpage>260</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Greeney</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Fallen flower bracts of the stilt-root palm <italic>Iriartea deltoidea</italic> (Palmae: Iriarteeae) as phytotelmata habitats in a lowland Ecuadorian rainforest.</article-title>
<source><italic>Milwaukee Public Museum Contributions in Biology and Geology</italic></source>
<volume>101</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>20</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Guti&#x000e9;rrez Ochoa</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Camino Lavin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Castrejon Ayala</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Jim&#x000e9;nez P&#x000e9;rez</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1993</year>
<article-title>Arthropods associated with <italic>Bromelia hemisphaerica</italic> (Bromeliales: Bromeliaceae) in Morelos, Mexico.</article-title>
<source><italic>Florida Entomologist</italic></source>
<volume>76</volume>
<fpage>616</fpage>
<lpage>621</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harrington</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1947</year>
<article-title>Explicaci&#x000f3;n de las hojas 33m y 34m: Sierra de Curamalal y Ventana, Provincia de Buenos Aires.</article-title>
<source><italic>Direcci&#x000f3;n de Minas y Geolog&#x000ed;a Buenos Aires Bolet&#x000ed;n</italic></source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>33</fpage>
<lpage>34</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jerez</surname><given-names>V</given-names></name><name><surname>Moroni</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Diversity of freshwater beetle of Chile.</article-title>
<source><italic>Gayana</italic></source>
<volume>70</volume>
<fpage>72</fpage>
<lpage>81</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jolivet</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Hawkeswood</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1995</year><source><italic>Host-plants of Chrysomelidae of the world.</italic></source><publisher-name>Backhuys Publishers</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Junc&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>FA</given-names></name><name><surname>Da Silva Borges</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Fauna associada a brom&#x000e9;lias terr&#x000ed;colas da Serra da Jib&#x000f3;ia, Bahia.</article-title>
<source><italic>Sitientibus s&#x000e9;rie Ci&#x000ea;ncias Biol&#x000f3;gicas</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>
<lpage>81</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitching</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>An ecological study of water-filled tree-holes and their position in the woodland ecosystem.</article-title>
<source><italic>Journal of Animal Ecology</italic></source>
<volume>40</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>
<lpage>302</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konstantinov</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year><article-title>Chrysomelidae: aquatic leaf beetles of China (Coleoptera).</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>J&#x000e4;ch</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ji</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<source><italic>Water beetles of China</italic></source><volume>3</volume><fpage>563</fpage><lpage>572</lpage><publisher-name>Zoologisch-Botanische Gesellschaft in &#x000d6;sterreich and Wiener Coleopterologenverein Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Laessle</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1961</year>
<article-title>A micro-limnological study of Jamaican bromeliads.</article-title>
<source><italic>Ecology</italic></source>
<volume>42</volume>
<fpage>499</fpage>
<lpage>517</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lanteri</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marvaldi</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Su&#x000e1;rez</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Gorgojos de la Argentina y sus plantas hu&#x000e9;spedes. Tomo I: Apionidae y Curculionidae.</article-title>
<source><italic>Publicaci&#x000f3;n Especial de la Sociedad Entomol&#x000f3;gica Argentina</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>98</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr34"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Liria</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Fitotelmata fauna on the bromeleans <italic>Aechmea fendleri</italic> Andr&#x000e9; y <italic>Hohenbergia strellata</italic> Schult of the San Esteban Nacional Park, Venezuela.</article-title>
<source><italic>Revista Peruana de Biolog&#x000ed;a</italic></source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>33</fpage>
<lpage>38</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr35"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Louton</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Gelhaus</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bouchard</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>The aquatic macrofauna of water-filled bamboo (Poaceae: Bambusoideae: <italic>Guadua</italic>) internodes in a Peruvian lowland tropical forest.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biotropica</italic></source>
<volume>28</volume>
<fpage>228</fpage>
<lpage>242</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr36"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;derwaldt</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1915</year>
<article-title>Insekten und sinstiges Tierleben an brasilianischen Bromeliaceen. Zeitshrift f&#x000fc;r wissenschaftliche.</article-title>
<source><italic>Insektenbiologie</italic></source>
<volume>11</volume>
<fpage>78</fpage>
<lpage>84</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr37"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Maguire</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>Phytotelmata: Biota and community structure determination in plant-held waters.</article-title>
<source><italic>Annual Review of Ecology and Systematics</italic></source>
<volume>2</volume>
<fpage>439</fpage>
<lpage>464</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr38"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mantovani</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Magalh&#x000e3;es</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Teixeira</surname><given-names>ML</given-names></name><name><surname>Leit&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Staines</surname><given-names>CL</given-names></name><name><surname>Resende</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2005</year><article-title>First report on host plants and feeding habits of the leaf beetle <italic>Acentroptera pulchella</italic> Gu&#x000e9;rin-M&#x000e9;neville (Chrysomelidae, Hispinae).</article-title><source><italic>Contributions to systematics and biology of beetles.</italic></source><publisher-name>Papers celebrating the 80th birthday of Igor Konstantinovich Lopatin. Pensoft Series Faunistica No. 43</publisher-name><fpage>153</fpage><lpage>157</lpage><publisher-loc>Pensoft</publisher-loc></element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr39"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Mestre</surname><given-names>LAM</given-names></name><name><surname>Aranha</surname><given-names>JMR</given-names></name><name><surname>Esper</surname><given-names>MdeLP</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Macroinvertebrate fauna associated to the bromeliad <italic>Vriesea inflata</italic> of the Atlantic forest (Paran&#x000e1; State, Southern Brazil).</article-title>
<source><italic>Brazilian Archives of Biology and Technology</italic></source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>89</fpage>
<lpage>94</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr40"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montero</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Feruglio</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Barberis</surname><given-names>IM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The phytotelmata and foliage macrofauna assemblages of a bromeliad species in different habitats and seasons.</article-title>
<source><italic>Insect Conservation and Diversity</italic></source>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>92</fpage>
<lpage>102</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr41"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Montes de Oca</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Ball</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name><name><surname>Spence</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Diversity of Carabidae (Insecta, Coleoptera) in epiphytic Bromeliaceae in central Veracruz, Mexico.</article-title>
<source><italic>Environmental Entomology</italic></source>
<volume>36</volume>
<fpage>560</fpage>
<lpage>568</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540065</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr42"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morrone</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>CW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>The aquatic and semiaquatic weevils (Coleoptera: Curculionoidea: Curculionidae, Dryopthoridae and Erirhinidae) of Argentina, with indication of their host plants.</article-title>
<source><italic>Physis</italic></source>
<volume>57</volume>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr43"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ospina-Bautista</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Est&#x000e9;vez-Var&#x000f3;n</surname><given-names>JV</given-names></name><name><surname>Betencur</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Realpe-Rebolledo</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Estructura y composici&#x000f3;n de la comunidad de macro invertebrados acu&#x000e1;ticos asociados a <italic>Tillandsia turneri</italic> Baker (Bromeliaceae) en un bosque alto andino Colombiano.</article-title>
<source><italic>Acta Zool&#x000f3;gica Mexicana (Nueva Serie)</italic></source>
<volume>20</volume>
<fpage>153</fpage>
<lpage>166</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr44"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Picado</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1913</year>
<article-title>Les brom&#x000e9;liacees &#x000e9;phiphytes consid&#x000e9;r&#x000e9;es come milieu biologique.</article-title>
<source><italic>Bulletin Scientifique de la France et de la Belgique</italic></source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage>
<lpage>360</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr45"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R&#x000ed;os de Saluso</surname><given-names>MLA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1997</year>
<article-title>Artr&#x000f3;podos asociados al &#x0201c;Caraguat&#x000e1;,&#x0201d; <italic>Eryngium paniculatum</italic> (Apiaceae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Revista Cient&#x000ed;fica Agropecuaria</italic></source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>35</fpage>
<lpage>37</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr46"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sanchez</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Liria</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2009</year>
<article-title>Relative abundance and temporal variation of macroinvertebrates in a Venezuelan could forest habitat.</article-title>
<source><italic>International Journal of Tropical Insect Science</italic></source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>3</fpage>
<lpage>10</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr47"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>AGDA</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>CR</given-names></name><name><surname>Monteiro Galv&#x000e3;o</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gon&#x000e7;alves</surname><given-names>AJL</given-names></name><name><surname>Gomes</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Do Nacimento Silva</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>De Simoni</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1968</year>
<source><italic>Quarto cat&#x000e1;logo dos insectos que vivem nas plantas do Brasil, seus parasitos e predatores.</italic> Ministerio da Agricultura, Departamento de Defensa a Inspec&#x000e3;o Agropecuaria, Servi&#x000e7;o de Defensa Sanitaria Vegetal, Laboratorio Central de Patolog&#x000ed;a Vegetal.</source>
<publisher-name>R&#x000ed;o de Janeiro</publisher-name>
<publisher-loc>GB, Brazil</publisher-loc>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr48"><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>SMN</collab>
<year>1981</year>
<article-title>Estad&#x000ed;sticas climatol&#x000f3;gicas. 1961&#x02013;1970.</article-title><source>Servicio Meteorol&#x000f3;gico Nacional, Fuerza A&#x000e9;rea Argentina.</source><comment>Available online, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.smn.gov.ar">www.smn.gov.ar</ext-link></comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr49"><element-citation publication-type="other">
<collab>SMN</collab>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Estad&#x000ed;sticas climatol&#x000f3;gicas. 1971&#x02013;1980 Servicio Meteorol&#x000f3;gico Nacional, Fuerza A&#x000e9;rea Argentina.</article-title><comment>Available online, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.smn.gov.ar">www.smn.gov.ar</ext-link></comment>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr50"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spangler</surname><given-names>PJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1980</year>
<article-title>Chelonariid larvae, aquatic or not? (Coleoptera: Chelonariidae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Coleopterists Bulletin</italic></source>
<volume>34</volume>
<fpage>105</fpage>
<lpage>114</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr51"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stribling</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name><name><surname>Young</surname><given-names>DK</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1990</year>
<article-title>Descriptions of the larva and pupa of <italic>Flavohelodes thoracica</italic> (Gu&#x000e9;rin-M&#x000e9;neville) with notes on a phytotelma association (Coleoptera: Scirtidae).</article-title>
<source><italic>Proceedings of Entomological Society of Washington</italic></source>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>765</fpage>
<lpage>770</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr52"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>Vargas</collab><collab>L</collab></person-group>
<year>1928</year>
<article-title>Ein interessanter biotope der biocon&#x000f6;se von wasser Organismen.</article-title>
<source><italic>Biologisches Zentralblatt</italic></source>
<volume>48</volume>
<fpage>143</fpage>
<lpage>162</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr53"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Von Ellenrieder</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Fern&#x000e1;ndez</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Aquatic coleoptera in the Subtropical-Pampasic ecotone (Argentina, Buenos Aires): species composition and temporal changes.</article-title>
<source><italic>Coleopterists Bulletin</italic></source>
<volume>54</volume>
<fpage>23</fpage>
<lpage>35</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr54"><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1978</year><article-title>Aquatic Coleoptera.</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Merritt</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cummins</surname><given-names>KW</given-names></name></person-group>
<source><italic>An introduction to the aquatic insects of North America</italic></source><volume>20</volume><fpage>399</fpage><lpage>473</lpage><publisher-name>Kendall and Hunt Press</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="bibr55"><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zaragoza</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1974</year>
<article-title>Cole&#x000f3;pteros de algunas bromelias ep&#x000ed;fitas y doce nuevos registros de especies para la fauna Mexicana.</article-title>
<source><italic>Anales del Instituto de Biolog&#x000ed;a, Universidad Nacional Aut&#x000f3;noma de M&#x000e9;xico (Serie Zoolog&#x000ed;a)</italic></source>
<volume>45</volume>
<fpage>111</fpage>
<lpage>118</lpage>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>