<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//Atypon//DTD Atypon Systems Archival NLM DTD Suite v2.2.0 20090301//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName atypon-archivearticle.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.2?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName atypon2nlmx.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Insect Sci</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">insc</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>Journal of Insect Science</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1536-2442</issn><publisher><publisher-name>University of Wisconsin Library</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">2999421</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1673/031.007.3001</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Article</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Trophic Interactions Between Two Herbivorous Insects, <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> and <italic>Myzus lythri</italic>, Feeding on Purple Loosestrife, <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>, and Two Insect Predators, <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> and <italic>Chrysoperla carnea</italic></article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>Bethzayda</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff2"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Obrycki</surname><given-names>John J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"><sup>1</sup></xref><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="corr1"/></contrib><aff id="aff1"><label><sup>1</sup></label>Department of Entomology, University of Kentucky, Lexington KY 40546</aff><aff id="aff2">Department of Entomology, Iowa State University, Ames IA 50011</aff></contrib-group><author-notes><corresp id="corr1">Correspondence: <email>bmatos@iastate.edu</email>, <email>John.Obrycki@uky.edu</email></corresp></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2007</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>10</day><month>5</month><year>2007</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><elocation-id>30</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2006</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>26</day><month>10</month><year>2006</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2007</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2007</copyright-year><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.5/"><license-p>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited.</license-p></license></permissions><abstract><p>The effects of two herbivorous insects, <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> Duftschmid and <italic>Myzus lythri</italic> L. (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae), feeding on purple loosestrife, <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> L. (Myrtiflorae: Lythraceae), were measured in the presence of two insect predators, <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> Pallas (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae) and <italic>Chrysoperla carnea</italic> (Stephens) (Neuroptera: Chrysopidae). A greenhouse cage experiment examined the direct effects of these predators on these herbivores, and indirect effects of predation on aboveground biomass, defoliation, number of leaves, and internode length. Eight treatment combinations with <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic>, <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> and <italic>C. carnea</italic> were applied to caged <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria.</italic> The experiment ended when <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> adults were observed, 11 to 13 days after release of first instar <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis. G. calmariensis</italic> larvae alone removed significant amounts of leaf tissue and reduced the number of <italic>L. salicaria</italic> leaves. Predators did not reduce levels of defoliation by <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis. C. carnea</italic> had no effect on <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> survival, but <italic>H. axyridis</italic> reduced <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> survival in the presence of <italic>M. lythri.</italic> Both predators reduced the survival of <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri.</italic> This short duration greenhouse study did not demonstrate that predator-prey interactions altered herbivore effects on <italic>L. salicaria.</italic>
</p></abstract><kwd-group><title>Keywords
</title><kwd>trophic cascade</kwd><kwd>biological control of weeds</kwd><kwd>predator-prey interactions</kwd></kwd-group><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec sec-type="" id="sec1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Purple loostrife, <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> L. (Myrtiflorae: Lythraceae) is an invasive weed with high fecundity that displaces native vegetation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr30">Thompson et al. 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr02">Balough and Bookhout 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr04">Blossey et al. 2001</xref>). In the early 1990s, two species of herbivorous insects, <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> L. and <italic>Galerucella pusilla</italic> Duftschmid (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae), were introduced in North America to reduce <italic>L. salicaria</italic> density (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr14">Hight et al. 1995</xref>). Since 1994, more than 1.4 million individual <italic>Galerucella</italic> spp. have been released in Iowa wetlands (J.J. Obrycki, unpublished data). In a field cage study, Cortilet (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr05">1998</xref>) demonstrated that the percentage defoliation and terminal bud damage of <italic>L. salicaria</italic> increased with increasing <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> larval density. After 47 days, 50 <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> larvae caused 25% defoliation and more than 20 terminal buds per stem were damaged (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr05">Cortilet 1998</xref>). In a second cage study, ten <italic>L. salicaria</italic> plants were enclosed with 45 <italic>G</italic>. <italic>pusilla</italic> eggs in individual cages for 35 days resulting in 14% defoliation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32">Wiebe 2001</xref>). Additionally, Katovich et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18">1999</xref>) released 50 <italic>Galerucella</italic> spp. adults and larvae on caged <italic>L. salicaria</italic> plants for two months, resulting in an average of 86% defoliation.</p><p><italic>Myzus lythri</italic> (Schrank) (Homoptera: Aphididae), first recorded in the U.S. in the 1930s (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr09">Gillette and Palmer 1934</xref>), was observed feeding on <italic>L. salicaria</italic> in Indiana in 1992 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31">Voegtlin 1995</xref>). In a greenhouse study, significantly lower dry weight of roots and shoots were observed for plants infested with <italic>M. lythri</italic>, compared to plants without aphids (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31">Voegtlin 1995</xref>).</p><p>Previous studies have shown negative effects on <italic>L. salicaria</italic> when either <italic>M. lythri</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31">Voegtlin 1995</xref>) or <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> were the only herbivorous species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr05">Cortilet 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32">Wiebe 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr18">Katovich et al. 1999</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr19">Landis et al. 2003</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr07">Denoth and Myers 2005</xref>). However, to our knowledge no studies have examined interactions of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> on <italic>L. salicaria.</italic> A previous discussion of the potential for biological control of <italic>L. salicaria</italic> predicted that combinations of insect herbivores would have a greater negative effect on <italic>L. salicaria</italic> than single herbivorous species (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr20">Malecki et al. 1993</xref>). Interspecific interactions of these herbivores on <italic>L. salicaria</italic> allow one to test whether an additive effect reduces <italic>L. salicaria</italic> biomass, or if interspecific competition between the herbivores inhibits reduction of <italic>L. salicaria.</italic> In biological control, interactions are considered when multiple natural enemy species are introduced into a new habitat. Multiple agents are believed to increase cumulative stress on weeds (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23">Myers 1985</xref>). Competing insects, located in the same areas of the plant, increase destruction of the plant, thus reducing plant growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr13">Harris 1981</xref>).</p><p><italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> larvae and <italic>M. lythri</italic> adults and nymphs are suitable prey for preimaginal development of the predatory insects, <italic>Chrysoperla carnea</italic> (Stephens) (Neuroptera: Chrysopidae), and <italic>Harmonia axyridis</italic> Pallas (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Matos and Obrycki 2006</xref>). <italic>M. lythri</italic> was highly suitable prey for <italic>H. axyridis</italic> and <italic>C. carnea</italic> (survival of 80% and 61%, respectively), whereas <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> was highly suitable prey for <italic>C. carnea</italic> (survival of 76%), but less suitable for <italic>H. axyridis</italic> (survival of 27%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Matos and Obrycki 2006</xref>).</p><p>Predator-prey interactions have the potential to be detrimental to suppression of <italic>L. salicaria</italic> through trophic cascades. A trophic cascade occurs when top predators have an indirect influence on the abundance of plant species via their effect on the number of herbivores present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr27">Schmitz et al. 2000</xref>). A field study in Sweden, demonstrated that defoliation of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> by <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> is higher when fewer insect predators are present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11">Hamback et al. 2000</xref>). These results indicated that <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> abundance is affected by predation by lady beetles (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr11">Hamback et al. 2000</xref>). In North American wetlands infested with <italic>L. salicaria,</italic> predation has been reported on <italic>Galerucella</italic> spp. eggs and larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29">Sebolt and Landis 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33">Wiebe and Obrycki 2004</xref>).</p><p>The objectives of this study were twofold; to determine if two herbivorous species (<italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic>) have an additive negative effect on selected plant measurements, and, second, whether the presence of insect predators that consume the herbivores reduce the effects of herbivory on <italic>L. salicaria,</italic> causing an indirect effect on the plant.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="sec2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="sec2a"><title>Insect cultures</title><p><italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> adults and <italic>M. lythri</italic> adults and nymphs were reared on <italic>L. salicaria</italic> plants; pea aphids, <italic>Acyrthosiphon pisum</italic> (Harris) (Hemiptera: Aphididae) were reared on fava beans, <italic>Vicia faba</italic> L<italic>.</italic> (Fabaceae). All rearing was done on plants enclosed in cages in the Iowa State University Department of Entomology greenhouse and growth chambers at 25 &#x000b1; 5&#x000b0;C 16:8 h (L:D). Voucher specimens of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, <italic>M. lythri</italic>, <italic>C. carnea</italic>, <italic>C. maculata</italic>, and <italic>H. axyridis</italic> were deposited in the Iowa State University Insect Collection, Department of Entomology, Ames, IA.</p><table-wrap id="t01" position="float"><label>Table 1. </label><caption><p>Eight predator-prey combination treatments.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="t01_01"/></table-wrap><p><italic>C. carnea</italic> were purchased from Rincon-Vitova Inc. (Fillmore, CA) as first instars and were fed on a mixture of <italic>Ephestia kuehniella</italic> Zeller (Lepidoptera: Pyralidae) eggs and <italic>A. pisum. H. axyridis</italic> adults were collected from Story County, Iowa. <italic>H. axyridis</italic> adults were maintained in 0.24-liter paper cages (Neptune Paper Products, Jersey City, NJ) in growth chambers (Model No. 1&#x02013;30 BLL, Percival, <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.percival-scientific.com">www.percival-scientific.com</ext-link>) at 24 &#x000b1; 1&#x000b0;C with a photoperiod of 16:8 (L:D). Adults were fed pea aphids, <italic>A. pisum</italic>, until females laid eggs, which were collected daily.</p></sec><sec id="sec2b"><title>Experimental design</title><p>In early June 2004, <italic>L. salicaria</italic> seeds were planted in SunGro Sunshine LC1 Mix&#x000ae; and maintained in a greenhouse at 25 &#x000b1; 5&#x000b0;C 16:8 h (L:D). When <italic>L. salicaria</italic> plants reached a height of 60 &#x000b1; 3 cm, each of 42 seedlings were transplanted into single 19-L pots and enclosed in mesh sleeves (120 cm tall &#x000d7; 70 cm wide) (No-See-Um netting, Balsom Hercules Group, Providence, RI) supported by tomato cages.</p><p>The experimental design was an incomplete block design with eight treatments and five replicates (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). The marsh habitat of purple loosestrife was simulated using potted plants in each of 10 wading pools (100 cm diameter, 30 cm height, containing 10 cm of water). Seven of the eight treatments were randomly selected and assigned to an individual potted plant in a wading pool, each of which served as a replication. The remaining treatments, which was the eighth pot (totaling five potted plants from the five blocks), were placed in a sixth pool, thereby creating an incomplete block. In the sixth pool, two additional potted plants were placed to create a pool environment similar to the other five pools with seven potted plants.</p><p>These treatments were selected because in a previous laboratory study, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> were found to be suitable prey for the development and survival of <italic>H. axyridis</italic> and <italic>C</italic>. <italic>carnea</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Matos and Obrycki 2006</xref>). In addition, due to logistical accommodation of the experimental units, we selected eight treatments out of all possible combinations. This selection was based on two preliminary studies and several prior experimental studies (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr31">Voegtlin 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr05">Cortilet 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr32">Wiebe 2001</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr08">Finke and Denno 2004</xref>). One plant in each block was randomly assigned to one of eight treatments (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t01">Table 1</xref>). Predator and herbivore densities were similar to densities observed in the field (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr22">Matos and Obrycki 2007</xref> in press). The experiment concluded when <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> adults eclosed, because plant measurements were taken in response to <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> larval feeding.</p></sec><sec id="sec2c"><title>Parameters measured</title><p>The number of herbivores and predators in each cage were counted at the end of the experiment. <italic>M. lythri</italic> infested plants for 25 days, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> infested plants for 11&#x02013;13 days, and predators were caged on plants for 9&#x02013;11 days. <italic>Myzus lythri</italic> were released on the plants 14&#x02013;16 days before predators were released and <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> first instars were released 2 days before the predators were released.</p><p>Five measurements of <italic>L. salicaria</italic> were taken: number of leaves, above ground biomass, internode length, leaf tissue removed, and total leaf area. Above ground dry biomass was determined by harvesting all live aboveground vegetation, which was dried in an oven for 7 days at 55&#x000b0;C and then weighed. Skeletonizing of the leaves occurs as a result of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> larvae feeding. Total leaf area and percentage defoliation (leaf tissue removed) were measured at the end of the experiment using Adobe Photoshop&#x000ae; (version 7.0). Multiple leaves were scanned into a digital format using Hewlett Packard Scanjet 4600 series digital flatbed scanners<sup>&#x000ae;</sup> (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="www.hp.com">www.hp.com</ext-link>) with HP Photo Imaging Gallery Software (1996&#x02013;2002) (version 1.1, images scanned at 600 dpi). This technique is similar to O'Neal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr24">2002</xref>) who determined that a flatbed scanner is an accurate and precise tool for leaf area measurement. Two copies of the original images were made. To estimate leaf tissue removal, the area removed from a leaf in the copied image was filled with black pixels. The area was measured using the histogram option (selected from the Image menu in Adobe Photoshop<sup>&#x000ae;</sup>).</p><table-wrap id="t02" position="float"><label>Table 2. </label><caption><p>Effects of herbivore-predator treatments on on <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>(mean &#x000b1; SE) in a greenhouse study.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="t02_01"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec2d"><title>Data analysis</title><p>The herbivore-plant and predator-prey effects on number of leaves, internode lengths, leaf area measured, leaf tissue removal, and aboveground dry biomass of <italic>L. salicaria</italic> were analyzed independently with mixed-model analyses of variance in which a block (replication) was modeled as a random source of variation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">SAS 2003</xref>). Subsequently, the following contrasts were used to examine the effects of herbivory (control vs. <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, control vs. <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic>), interaction of herbivores (control vs. <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> + <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> vs. <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> + <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, and <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> vs. <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> + <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>), predation on herbivores (<italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> vs. <italic>C. carnea</italic> + <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, <italic>M. lythri</italic> vs. <italic>H</italic>. <italic>axyridis</italic> + <italic>M. lythri</italic>, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> + <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> vs. <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> + <italic>M. lythri</italic> + predator), and predator effect on plant (control vs. herbivores + predator). To determine effects on herbivore survival, means separation was done using LSD statistic test (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr25">SAS 2003</xref>). Results were considered significant at P &#x0003c; 0.05.</p><table-wrap id="t03" position="float"><label>Tables 3. </label><caption><p>Probability values for single degree-of-freedom linear contrasts of plant parameters.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="t03_01"/></table-wrap></sec></sec><sec sec-type="" id="sec3"><title>Results</title><sec id="sec3a"><title>Herbivore - plant interactions</title><p>The greatest leaf tissue removal occurred in the <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> alone treatment (927.4 &#x000b1; 305.3 cm<sup>2</sup>; mean &#x000b1; SE) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t02">Table 2</xref>). <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> removed a significantly larger amount of leaf tissue when compared to the control (P &#x0003c;0.0001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). Over 50% defoliation was measured in <italic>L. salicaria</italic> plants with <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> only. <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> also significantly reduced the number of leaves compared to the control treatments (P &#x0003c; 0.0001; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). <italic>M. lythri</italic> alone did not significantly affect internode length (P = 0.27; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). Plants infested with <italic>M. lythri</italic> had more leaves at the end of the experiment compared to the <italic>M. lythri</italic> + <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> treatment (P = 0.0014; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="t04" position="float"><label>Table 4. </label><caption><p>Percentage survival (&#x000b1; SE) of <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> and mean survival (&#x000b1; SE) of <italic>Myzus lythri</italic> alone and in the presence of an individual predator.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="t04_01"/></table-wrap></sec><sec id="sec3b"><title>Interactions of two herbivore species</title><p>Over 29% of <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> and a mean of 93.9 <italic>M. lythri</italic> per 12 leaves survived in the <italic>M. lythri </italic>plus <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 4</xref>). Total numbers of <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M. lythri</italic> surviving were similar to treatments in which each individual herbivore was alone. The results indicated that neither herbivore species influenced the survival of the other.</p></sec><sec id="sec3c"><title>Herbivore - predator interactions</title><p>The herbivores plus predator treatments reduced leaf area compared to the control (P = 0.02; <xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>). The presence of <italic>C. carnea</italic> did not influence the number of leaves on plants exposed to <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> (P = 0.05). The presence of predators affected survival of herbivores but had no effect on plant measurements. Over 20% of <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> survived in the <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> plus <italic>C. carnea</italic> treatment (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 4</xref>), which is similar to the <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> alone treatment. When both herbivores were in the same cage with <italic>C. carnea</italic>, <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> survival was unaffected (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 4</xref>). <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> survival in the <italic>M. lythri</italic> with both <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> and <italic>H. axyridis</italic> treatment was significantly less (12.4%) than in the <italic>M. lythri </italic>plus <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> treatment (29.6%) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t04">Table 4</xref>). The lowest survival of <italic>M. lythri</italic> (2.2 per 12 leaves per plant) was observed in the <italic>M. lythri</italic> plus both <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> and <italic>H. axyridis</italic> treatment.</p></sec><sec id="sec3d"><title>Plant-predator interactions</title><p>At least one of the three predators released in each cage survived, indicating that predation occurred within the cages. At the end of the experiment, the predators were either in their pupal stage or last instar. The presence of predators did not affect any plant measurement (<xref ref-type="table" rid="t03">Table 3</xref>).</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="" id="sec4"><title>Discussion</title><p>These findings have several implications for the understanding of multitrophic interactions associated with <italic>L. salicaria</italic>. First, the two herbivores (<italic>G. calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M. lythri</italic>) did not have an additive negative effect on <italic>L. salicaria</italic>. Second, two predatory species (<italic>C. carnea</italic> and <italic>H. axyridis</italic>) decreased <italic>M. lythri</italic> survival, and <italic>H. axyridis</italic> reduced <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> survival when <italic>M. lythri</italic> was present. Finally, predator presence did not indirectly benefit the plant, based upon the parameters measured.</p><p>Several studies have attempted to determine if multiple species of herbivores increase the success of weed biological control projects (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr06">Denoth et al. 2002</xref>). In the biological control program for the control of the invasive weed species, <italic>Lantana camara</italic> L., temporally separated natural enemies including (<italic>Teleonemia scrupulosa</italic> Stal (Hemiptera: Tingidae) during summer months and three species of Lepidoptera during winter months, contributed to the suppression of <italic>L. camara</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr01">Andres and Goeden, 1971</xref>). In some cases multiple herbivore species do not increase levels of biological control (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr23">Myers 1985</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16">Hunt-Joshi and Blossey 2005a</xref>). In a 4-year field cage study, there was no increase in damage to <italic>L. salicaria</italic> when two spatially separated herbivores, <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> and a root feeding weevil, <italic>Hylobius transversovittatus</italic> Goeze (Coleoptera: Curculionidae), were present (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15">Hunt-Joshi and Blossey 2004</xref>). By itself, <italic>G. calmariensis</italic> reduced <italic>L. salicaria</italic> height, reproductive ability, and aboveground biomass whereas <italic>H.</italic>  <italic>transversovittatus</italic> increased mortality of actively growing stems and thinned <italic>L. salicaria</italic> stands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15">Hunt-Joshi and Blossey 2004</xref>). However, in combined herbivore treatments, no increased suppression of <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> was observed (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr15">Hunt-Joshi and Blossey 2004</xref>). In our study, an additive effect due to the herbivores <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M. lythri</italic> on <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> was not observed because <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> alone did not reduce any of the plant characteristics assessed.</p><p>In the absence of predators, survival of one herbivore was not affected by the presence of the other herbivorous species. Previous studies examined coexistence of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> and <italic>G</italic>. <italic>pusilla</italic> on <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr03">Blossey 1995</xref>) and interactions of the spatially separated root-feeding weevil, <italic>H. transversovittatus</italic>, and the herbivore, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> on <italic>L. salicaria</italic> plants (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16">Hunt-Joshi and Blossey 2005a</xref>). Although <italic>G</italic>. <italic>pusilla</italic> and <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> adults aggregate at the same sites and use the same host plant, these herbivorous species have similar competitive abilities and coexist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr03">Blossey 1995</xref>). Root herbivory by <italic>H. transversovittatus</italic> did not affect <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>; in contrast, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> herbivory negatively affected the survival of larvae of the root weevil <italic>H. transversovittatus</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr16">Hunt-Joshi and Blossey 2005a</xref>).</p><p>Although specialist predators and parasites are eliminated in the quarantine process before release (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr12">Harley and Forno 1992</xref>), naturally occurring generalist enemies in the release habitats have the potential to reduce establishment and success of the introduced herbivores (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr10">Goeden and Louda 1976</xref>). In our study species of generalist predators were chosen that occur in <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic>-infested wetlands (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29">Sebolt and Landis 2004</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr33">Wiebe and Obrycki 2004</xref>). The results showed that survival of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> in the treatment cages was not reduced by the presence of predators, except when <italic>H. axyridis</italic> and <italic>M. lythri</italic> were present. Previously, we showed that <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> was suitable for preimaginal development and survival of <italic>C. carnea</italic> and <italic>H. axyridis</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Matos and Obrycki 2006</xref>). However, in the present study, <italic>C. carnea</italic> did not reduce <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> numbers compared to when <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> was alone. Neonate <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> feed within <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> shoot tips presumably avoiding predation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28">Sebolt and Landis 2002</xref>). In the presence of the predator <italic>Coleomegilla maculata</italic> (De Geer) (Coleoptera: Coccinellidae), <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> neonate survival was higher in <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> shoot tips (70%) than those neonates exposed on <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> leaves (7.1%) (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr28">Sebolt and Landis 2002</xref>). A shift in behavior of herbivores or predators may alter the occurrence of a trophic cascade (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr26">Schmitz et al. 1997</xref>).</p><p>The suitability of prey for <italic>H. axyridis</italic> was higher for <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> compared to <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr21">Matos and Obrycki 2006</xref>). In the current study, it seems likely that <italic>M. lythri</italic> supplemented the low nutritional quality of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> for <italic>H. axyridis</italic> development and survival. Similarly to <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic>, <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> is found on leaves and stems and this may have created an opportunity for <italic>H. axyridis</italic> to attack <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis.</italic> Sebolt and Landis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr29">2004</xref>) showed that the attack rates of <italic>H. axyridis</italic> on <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> first to third instars ranged from 60 to 100%. Our study showed higher <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> mortality when <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> was present and preyed upon by <italic>H. axyridis</italic> compared to the mortality when <italic>H. axyridis</italic> was absent. Because we did not include a treatment with only <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> plus <italic>H. axyridis</italic>, this treatment design did not determine whether the presence of <italic>M. lythri</italic> influenced predation of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis.</italic></p><p><italic>M. lythri</italic> survival was significantly reduced in the presence of the predators. <italic>M. lythri</italic> did not reduce internode length; however, internode length was shorter in the <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> plus <italic>H. axyridis</italic> treatment than in the <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> alone treatment. Possibly <italic>M</italic>. <italic>lythri</italic> altered its behavior in the presence of <italic>H. axyridis</italic> and this behavior resulted in <italic>M. lythri</italic> moving to more protected sites where its feeding was detrimental to internode length.</p><p><italic>C</italic>. <italic>carnea</italic> and <italic>H. axyridis</italic> did not indirectly benefit the growth of <italic>L. salicaria.</italic> Although <italic>H. axyridis</italic> caused <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> and <italic>M. lythri</italic> mortality and <italic>C. carnea</italic> caused <italic>M. lythri</italic> mortality, herbivory was not significantly reduced in this greenhouse cage study. During a 4-year field study, an opportunistic predator <italic>Plagiognathus politis</italic> (Hemiptera: Miridae) consumed large numbers of <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> eggs and young larvae (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17">Hunt-Joshi et al. 2005b</xref>). However, after the second and third season, <italic>G</italic>. <italic>calmariensis</italic> populations increased to levels that caused significant defoliation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17">Hunt-Joshi et al. 2005b</xref>). Hunt-Joshi et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="bibr17">2005b</xref>) suggested that a more controlled experiment where predators and herbivore population levels were manipulated could result in a strong trophic cascade effect. Our study was a controlled short-term greenhouse experiment where herbivore and predator levels were manipulated, but no indirect positive effect of the two species of generalist predators on <italic>L</italic>. <italic>salicaria</italic> was found.</p></sec></body><back><ack><title>Acknowledgements</title><p>We thank Dr. Mark Gleason's (Iowa State University) laboratory group and Dr. Matt O'Neal, Department of Entomology, Iowa State University for providing valuable criticism. We thank Jeffrey Bradshaw, Department of Entomology at Iowa State University for technical assistance in scanning, using, and analyzing leaf data using computer software. Brenda and Amanda Knapp, Cristy Matos, and Kevin Day helped with rearing of insects. Dr. Philip Dixon (Iowa State University) from the Department of Statistics provided statistical advice. BM was supported by George Washington Carver Doctoral fellowship from the Graduate College at Iowa State University.</p></ack><ref-list content-type="parsed"><title>References</title><ref id="bibr01"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Andres</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Goeden</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name></person-group><year>1971</year><article-title>The biological control of weeds by introduced natural enemies</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Huffaker</surname><given-names>C. B</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Biological Control</italic></source><fpage>143</fpage><lpage>162</lpage><publisher-name>Plenum Press</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr02"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Balough</surname><given-names>GR</given-names></name><name><surname>Bookhout</surname><given-names>TA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1989</year><article-title>Purple loosestrife (<italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>) in Ohio's Lake Erie Marshes.</article-title><source><italic>Ohio Journal of Science</italic></source><volume>89</volume><fpage>62</fpage><lpage>64</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr03"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>A comparison of various approaches for evaluating potential biological control agents using insects on <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>.</article-title><source><italic>Biological Control</italic></source><volume>5</volume><fpage>113</fpage><lpage>122</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr04"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Skinner</surname><given-names>LC</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><article-title>Impact and management of purple loosestrife (<italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>) in North America.</article-title><source><italic>Biodiversity and Conservation</italic></source><volume>10</volume><fpage>1787</fpage><lpage>1807</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr05"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cortilet</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1998</year><source><italic>Evaluation of natural enemies released for the biological control of purple loosestrife in Iowa</italic>. M. S. Thesis.</source><publisher-name>Iowa State University</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Ames</publisher-loc><fpage>85</fpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr06"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denoth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Frid</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Multiple agents in biological control: improving the odds?.</article-title><source><italic>Biological Control</italic></source><volume>24</volume><fpage>20</fpage><lpage>30</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr07"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Denoth</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005</year><article-title>Variable success of biological control of <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> in British Columbia.</article-title><source><italic>Biological Control</italic></source><volume>32</volume><fpage>269</fpage><lpage>279</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr08"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Finke</surname><given-names>DL</given-names></name><name><surname>Denno</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Predator diversity dampens trophic cascades.</article-title><source><italic>Nature</italic></source><volume>429</volume><fpage>407</fpage><lpage>410</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15164061</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr09"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gillette</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Palmer</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><year>1934</year><article-title>The Aphididae of Colorado, Part III.</article-title><source><italic>Annals of the Entomological Society of America</italic></source><volume>27</volume><fpage>133</fpage><lpage>255</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr10"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Goeden</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Louda</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1976</year><article-title>Biotic interference with insects imported for weed control.</article-title><source><italic>Annual Review of Entomology</italic></source><volume>21</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>342</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr11"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hamback</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Agren</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ericson</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Associational resistance: insect damage to purple loosestrife reduced in thickets of sweet gale.</article-title><source><italic>Ecology</italic></source><volume>81</volume><fpage>1784</fpage><lpage>1794</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr12"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harley</surname><given-names>KLS</given-names></name><name><surname>Forno</surname><given-names>IW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1992</year><source><italic>Biological control of weeds: a handbook for practitioners and students</italic>.</source><publisher-name>CSIRO Division of Entomology</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Australia. Inkata Press</publisher-loc></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr13"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Harris</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><year>1981</year><article-title>Stress in biological control of weeds</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Papavizas</surname><given-names>G. C</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Biological Control in Crop Production</italic></source><fpage>333</fpage><fpage>340</fpage><publisher-loc>Allanheld</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Osmun and Co</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr14"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hight</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Laihng</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>DeClerck-Floate</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Establishment of insect biological control agents from Europe against <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> in North America.</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Entomology</italic></source><volume>24</volume><fpage>967</fpage><lpage>977</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr15"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt-Joshi</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Root and leaf herbivory on <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>: implications for plant performance and communities.</article-title><source><italic>Ecological Applications</italic></source><volume>14</volume><fpage>1574</fpage><lpage>1589</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr16"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt-Joshi</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005a</year><article-title>Interactions of root and leaf herbivores on purple loosestrife (<italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>).</article-title><source><italic>Oecologia</italic></source><volume>142</volume><fpage>554</fpage><lpage>563</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15619100</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr17"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt-Joshi</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Root</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><year>2005b</year><article-title>Disruption of weed biological control by an opportunistic mirid predator.</article-title><source><italic>Ecological Application</italic>s</source><volume>15</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>870</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr18"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Katovich</surname><given-names>EJS</given-names></name><name><surname>Becker</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Ragsdale</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><year>1999</year><article-title>Effect of Galerucella spp. on survival of purple loosestrife (<italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>) roots and crowns.</article-title><source><italic>Weed Science</italic></source><volume>47</volume><fpage>360</fpage><lpage>365</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr19"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Sebolt</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Haas</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Klepinger</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><year>2003</year><article-title>Establishment and impact of <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> L. (Coleoptera : Chrysomelidae) on <italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic> L. and associated plant communities in Michigan.</article-title><source><italic>Biological Control</italic></source><volume>28</volume><fpage>78</fpage><lpage>91</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr20"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malecki</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Blossey</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Hight</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Kok</surname><given-names>LT</given-names></name><name><surname>Coulson</surname><given-names>JR</given-names></name></person-group><year>1993</year><article-title>Biological control of purple loosestrife.</article-title><source><italic>BioScience</italic></source><volume>43</volume><fpage>680</fpage><lpage>686</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr21"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Obrycki</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2006</year><article-title>Prey suitability of Galerucella calmariensis L. (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) and Myzus lythri (Schrank) (Homoptera: Aphididae) for development of three predatory species.</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Entomology</italic></source><volume>35</volume><fpage>345</fpage><lpage>350</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr22"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Matos</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Obrycki</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2007</year><article-title>Evaluations of mortality of <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> L. (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) preimaginal life stages and pupal survival at two wetlands in Iowa.</article-title><source><italic>Journal of the Kansas Entomological Society</italic></source><volume>80</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>26</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr23"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Myers</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><year>1985</year><article-title>How many insect species are necessary for biocontrol of weeds?</article-title><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Delfosse</surname><given-names>E. S</given-names></name></person-group><source><italic>Proceedings of the 6<sup>th</sup> International Symposium on the Biological Control of Weeds</italic></source><fpage>77</fpage><lpage>82</lpage><publisher-loc>Agriculture Canada</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Canadian Government Printing Office</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr24"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>O'Neal</surname><given-names>ME</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Isaacs</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>An inexpensive, accurate method for measuring leaf area and defoliation through digital Image analysis.</article-title><source><italic>Journal of Economic Entomology</italic></source><volume>95</volume><fpage>1190</fpage><lpage>1194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12539831</pub-id></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr25"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><collab>SAS Institute.</collab></person-group><year>2003</year><source><italic>SAS for Windows</italic>, version 9.1.</source><publisher-name>SAS Institute</publisher-name></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr26"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckerman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>O'Brien</surname><given-names>KM</given-names></name></person-group><year>1997</year><article-title>Behaviorally mediated trophic cascades: effects of predation risk on food web interactions.</article-title><source><italic>Ecology</italic></source><volume>78</volume><fpage>1388</fpage><lpage>1399</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr27"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Hamback</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Beckerman</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2000</year><article-title>Trophic cascades in terrestrial systems: a review of the effects of carnivore removals on plants.</article-title><source><italic>American Naturalist</italic></source><volume>155</volume><fpage>141</fpage><lpage>153</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr28"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sebolt</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2002</year><article-title>Neonate <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) behavior on purple loosestrife (<italic>Lythrum salicaria</italic>) contributes to reduced predation.</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Entomology</italic></source><volume>31</volume><fpage>880</fpage><lpage>886</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr29"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sebolt</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Landis</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Arthropod predators of <italic>Galerucella calmariensis</italic> L. (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae): an assessment of biotic interference.</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Entomology</italic></source><volume>33</volume><fpage>356</fpage><lpage>361</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr30"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>DQ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stuckey</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thompson</surname><given-names>EB</given-names></name></person-group><year>1987</year><source><italic>Spread, impact, and control of purple loosestrife (Lythrum salicaria) in North America wetlands</italic></source><fpage>55</fpage><publisher-name>U. S Fish and Wildlife Service</publisher-name><publisher-loc>Jamestown, ND</publisher-loc><comment>Northern Prairies Wildlife Research Center. Retrieved 8 October 2002. From: <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.npwrc.usgs.gov/resource/1999/loosstrf/loosstrf.htm">http://www.npwrc.usgs.gov/resource/1999/loosstrf/loosstrf.htm</ext-link></comment></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr31"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Voegtlin</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>1995</year><article-title>Potential Impact of <italic>Myzus lythri</italic> (Homoptera: Aphididae) to Influence growth and development of Lythrum salicaria (Myrtiflorae: Lythraceae).</article-title><source><italic>Environmental Entomology</italic></source><volume>24</volume><fpage>724</fpage><lpage>729</lpage></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr32"><mixed-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name></person-group><year>2001</year><source><italic>Trophic interactions influencing the biological control of purple loosestrife (Lythrum salicaria)</italic>. 111 pp. M. S. Thesis</source><publisher-loc>Iowa State University, Ames</publisher-loc></mixed-citation></ref><ref id="bibr33"><mixed-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wiebe</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Obrycki</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name></person-group><year>2004</year><article-title>Quantitative assessment of predation of eggs and larvae of <italic>Galerucella pusilla</italic> in Iowa.</article-title><source><italic>Biological Control</italic></source><volume>31</volume><fpage>16</fpage><lpage>28</lpage></mixed-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>