<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v3.0 20080202//EN" "archivearticle3.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD Journal Publishing DTD v2.0 20040830//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName journalpublishing.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 2.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PLoS One</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PLoS ONE</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">plos</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">plosone</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PLoS ONE</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">1932-6203</issn><publisher><publisher-name>Public Library of Science</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3353970</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">PONE-D-12-07377</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036862</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Research Article</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Agriculture</subject><subj-group><subject>Agricultural Biotechnology</subject><subj-group><subject>Genetically Modified Organisms</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Crops</subject><subj-group><subject>Crop Management</subject></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Pest Control</subject><subj-group><subject>Integrated Control</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="Discipline-v2"><subject>Biology</subject><subj-group><subject>Microbiology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasitology</subject><subj-group><subject>Parasite Groups</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group><subj-group><subject>Zoology</subject><subj-group><subject>Animal Physiology</subject><subject>Entomology</subject></subj-group></subj-group></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Characterization of Digestive Enzymes of Bruchid Parasitoids&#x02013;Initial Steps for Environmental Risk Assessment of Genetically Modified Legumes</article-title><alt-title alt-title-type="running-head">Digestive Enzymes of Bruchid Parasitoids</alt-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez-Alfageme</surname><given-names>Fernando</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/><xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1"><sup>&#x0002a;</sup></xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;thi</surname><given-names>Christoph</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Romeis</surname><given-names>J&#x000f6;rg</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="aff1"><addr-line>Agroscope Reckenholz-T&#x000e4;nikon Research Station ART, Zurich, Switzerland</addr-line></aff><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Palli</surname><given-names>Subba Reddy</given-names></name><role>Editor</role><xref ref-type="aff" rid="edit1"/></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="edit1">U. Kentucky, United States of America</aff><author-notes><corresp id="cor1">&#x0002a; E-mail: <email>fernando.alvarez@art.admin.ch</email></corresp><fn fn-type="con"><p>Conceived and designed the experiments: FAA CL JR. Performed the experiments: FAA CL. Analyzed the data: FAA. Wrote the paper: FAA CL JR.</p></fn></author-notes><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2012</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="epub"><day>16</day><month>5</month><year>2012</year></pub-date><volume>7</volume><issue>5</issue><elocation-id>e36862</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received"><day>13</day><month>3</month><year>2012</year></date><date date-type="accepted"><day>14</day><month>4</month><year>2012</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000c1;lvarez-Alfageme et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2012</copyright-year></permissions><abstract><p>Genetically modified (GM) legumes expressing the &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor 1 (&#x003b1;AI-1) from <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L. or cysteine protease inhibitors are resistant to several bruchid pests (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae). In addition, the combination of plant resistance factors together with hymenopteran parasitoids can substantially increase the bruchid control provided by the resistance alone. If the strategy of combining a bruchid-resistant GM legume and biological control is to be effective, the insecticidal trait must not adversely affect bruchid antagonists. The environmental risk assessment of such GM legumes includes the characterization of the targeted enzymes in the beneficial species and the assessment of the <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility to the resistance factor. The digestive physiology of bruchid parasitoids remain relatively unknown, and their susceptibility to &#x003b1;AI-1 has never been investigated. We have detected &#x003b1;-amylase and serine protease activities in all five bruchid parasitoid species tested. Thus, the deployment of GM legumes expressing cysteine protease inhibitors to control bruchids should be compatible with the use of parasitoids. <italic>In vitro</italic> inhibition studies showed that sensitivity of &#x003b1;-amylase activity to &#x003b1;AI-1 in the parasitoids was comparable to that in the target species. Direct feeding assays revealed that harmful effects of &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitors on bruchid parasitoids cannot be discounted and need further evaluation.</p></abstract><counts><page-count count="8"/></counts></article-meta></front><body><sec id="s1"><title>Introduction</title><p>Grain legumes, also known as pulses or food legumes, are mainly cultivated in developing countries, where they are essential for nutrition. Pulses represent a source of income and livestock feed and meet the requirements of small-scale, low-income farmers in developing countries <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Popelka1">[1]</xref>. Grain legumes are commonly stored over extended periods to ensure supplies of household food and seed for sowing <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Nukenine1">[2]</xref>. Several coleopteran and lepidopteran pests are responsible for extensive losses to stored grain legumes because these pests develop and reproduce rapidly, completing multiple generations in the storage. In addition, insect pests increase the temperature and humidity of the stored pulses, which increases grain respiration and thereby reduces grain quantity and quality <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Odogola1">[3]</xref>. The average grain-weight loss for pulses due to insect pests is 20&#x00025; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Philips1">[4]</xref>, although it can be up to 100&#x00025; and is generally much higher than the loss caused by rodents, microorganisms, and other pests <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Nukenine1">[2]</xref>. Larvae of several <italic>Acanthoscelides</italic>, <italic>Zabrotes</italic>, and <italic>Callosobruchus</italic> spp. (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae) are among the most important insect pests of pulses worldwide.</p><p>Many insects, especially those like bruchids that feed on starchy seeds, depend on &#x003b1;-amylases for survival <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Franco1">[5]</xref>. Because these enzymes are active in the digestive tract and play a key role in carbohydrate metabolism, they are ideal targets for seed-based pest management approaches. Genetically modified (GM) legumes (i.e., cowpeas, peas, chickpeas, and azuki beans) expressing the &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor 1 (&#x003b1;AI-1) from the common bean, <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> L., are resistant to several bruchid species under laboratory <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Schroeder1">[6]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Solleti1">[9]</xref> and field conditions <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Morton1">[10]</xref>. The deployment of GM legumes expressing other types of digestive enzyme inhibitors to control bruchids, such as plant protease inhibitors, has also been suggested <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Koiwa1">[11]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Amirhusin2">[13]</xref>. Robust, reproducible, and efficient transformation procedures are available for many legumes species <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Popelka1">[1]</xref>. In addition, the combination of plant resistance factors together with biological control agents, especially hymenopteran parasitoids, can substantially increase the bruchid control provided by host-plant resistance alone <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Schmale1">[14]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Velten1">[16]</xref>. If the strategy of combining a bruchid-resistant GM legume and biological control is to be effective and sustainable, the insecticidal trait expressed by the resistant crop must not adversely affect bruchid antagonists. A conceptual model describing how GM legume seeds expressing &#x003b1;AI-1 could harm the biological control service provided by parasitoids of bruchids has been developed by L&#x000fc;thi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Lthi1">[17]</xref>. The model consists of five sequential steps and could be applied for protease inhibitor-expressing plants as well. In the first two steps, the model (i) characterizes the targeted digestive enzymes in the beneficial species and (ii) assesses the <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility to the plant resistance factor. The information required to satisfy these two steps of the model are not available for bruchid parasitoids. In the case of bruchid parasitoids, the physiological and biochemical aspects of their nutrition remain relatively unknown, and their susceptibility to &#x003b1;AI-1 has never been investigated.</p><p>In this study, we have characterized the &#x003b1;-amylase and protease activities in extracts of larvae and adult females of five common hymenopteran exoparasitoids of last instar larvae or pupae of bruchid pests. We then conducted <italic>in vitro</italic> experiments to assess the susceptibility of the exoparasitoid &#x003b1;-amylases to &#x003b1;AI-1 from <italic>P. vulgaris</italic>; for comparison, these biochemical assays also included extracts of three bruchid species. Finally, we used direct feeding assays to evaluate the effects of a commercial wheat &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor and a serine protease inhibitor on females of two parasitoid species.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec id="s2a"><title>Insects</title><sec id="s2a1"><title>Bruchids</title><p>The following bruchids were obtained from C. Adler (Julius K&#x000fc;hn-Institut, Germany) and were maintained for several years on chickpea (<italic>Cicer arietinum</italic> L.) seeds (Kabuli type) at 24&#x000b1;2&#x000b0;C, 60&#x000b1;5&#x00025; r.h., and complete darkness: <italic>Acanthoscelides obtectus</italic> (Say), <italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic> (L.), and <italic>Callosobruchus maculatus</italic> (F.) (Coleoptera: Chrysomelidae).</p></sec><sec id="s2a2"><title>Parasitoids</title><p>Seeds infested with bruchids and parasitoids were sent to us by several investigators. <italic>Heterospilus prosopidis</italic> Viereck (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) parasitizing <italic>C. chinensis</italic> reared on Azuki bean [<italic>Vigna angularis</italic> (Willd.)] seeds were provided by M. Shimada (University of Tokyo, Japan). <italic>Anisopteromalus calandrae</italic> (Howard) (Hymenotpera: Pteromalidae) and <italic>Lariophagus distinguendus</italic> (F&#x000f6;rst.) (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) reared on wheat (<italic>Triticum aestivum</italic> L.) seeds infested with <italic>Sitophilus granarius</italic> (L.) (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) were obtained from J. Steidle (Hohenheim University, Germany). <italic>Dinarmus basalis</italic> (Rond.) (Hymenoptera: Pteromalidae) and <italic>Eupelmus vuilleti</italic> (Crw.) (Hymenoptera: Eupelmidae) on cowpea [Vigna unguiculata (L.) Walp.] seeds infested with <italic>C. maculatus</italic> were provided by J.P. Monge (Tours University, France). Upon arrival, seeds were kept in a climate chamber at 24&#x000b1;2&#x000b0;C, 60&#x000b1;5&#x00025; r.h., and complete darkness. Emerging adults were then transferred to plastic containers (10.5 cm diameter, 15 cm high) containing last-instar larvae and/or pupae of <italic>C. chinensis</italic> in chickpea seeds and were reared in the laboratory for at least two generations before the start of the experiments.</p><p>Females of all species but <italic>H. prosopodis</italic> are synovigenic, i.e., they are born with immature eggs and must feed on their host to sustain egg production.</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2b"><title>Characterization of Digestive Enzymes in Parasitoids and Bruchids and <italic>in vitro</italic> Inhibitory Activity of Purified <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> &#x003b1;AI-1</title><sec id="s2b1"><title>Preparation of insect extracts</title><p>Fourth-instar larvae of all bruchid species and third-instar larvae and 1-week-old females of all parasitoid species from the rearing colonies were used for the <italic>in vitro</italic> characterization of digestive enzymes. Insects were homogenized in ice-cold 0.15 M NaCl (100 insects ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>). The homogenates were centrifuged at 10,000 <italic>g</italic> for 5 min, and the supernatants were pooled and stored frozen at &#x02212;20&#x000b0;C to obtain soluble protein extracts for determination of enzymatic activity. Total protein content was determined according to the method of Bradford <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Bradford1">[18]</xref> using bovine serum albumin (BSA) as the standard.</p></sec><sec id="s2b2"><title>Characterization of &#x003b1;-amylase activity</title><p>A series of overlapping buffers was used to generate a pH range from 3 to 11. Reaction buffers were: 0.1 M citrate (pH 3&#x02013;6), 0.1 M phosphate (pH 6&#x02013;7), 0.1 M Tris-HCl (pH 7&#x02013;9), and 0.1 M glycine-NaOH (pH 9&#x02013;11). All buffers contained 0.15 M NaCl and 5 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>. Assays were performed using a modified version of the Bernfeld assay <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Bernfeld1">[19]</xref>. The standard assay volume was 100 &#x000b5;l, which contained 5 &#x000b5;g of insect protein extract and potato starch as substrate added to a final concentration of 0.5&#x00025; (w/v). After the samples had been incubated at 30&#x000b0;C for 45 min, the reaction was stopped by the addition of 100 &#x000b5;l of dinitrosalicylic acid (DNSA) reagent, followed by boiling for 5 min in a thermoblock (1102, SKS Bio-medical Instruments Ltd., Luton, England). Then, 1 ml of distilled water was added to the solution, which was mixed and left at room temperature for 15 min. Finally, the absorbance was read at 540 nm in a spectrophotometer, and &#x003b1;-amylase activity was expressed as mg of maltose liberated min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mg protein<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>. A standard curve with maltose was constructed to calculate &#x003b1;-amylase activity.</p><p>The &#x003b1;-amylase activity of each bruchid and parasitoid extract was further characterized at its optimum pH in the presence of the specific inhibitors acarbose and wheat &#x003b1;-AI. Both inhibitors were incubated with the extracts at room temperature for 15 min before the substrate was added. The inhibitors were added in 10 &#x000b5;l of distilled water to a final concentration of 0.001&#x00025; (w/v).</p></sec><sec id="s2b3"><title>In vitro inhibitory activity of purified P. vulgaris &#x003b1;AI-1</title><p>The susceptibility of extracts of bruchid larvae and of parasitoid larvae and females to purified &#x003b1;AI-1 was determined by <italic>in vitro</italic> assay. &#x003b1;AI-1 purified from the seeds of <italic>P. vulgaris</italic> as described by Marshall and Lauda <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Marshall1">[20]</xref> was provided by T.J.V. Higgins (CSIRO, Australia). Previous studies have indicated that the two <italic>Callosobruchus</italic> species used in the current investigation are highly susceptible to &#x003b1;AI-1 <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ishimoto2">[21]</xref> whereas the &#x003b1;-amylase activity of <italic>A. obtectus</italic> is not <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ishimoto3">[22]</xref>. The &#x003b1;-amylase activity in the extract of each parasitoid and bruchid species was assayed at its optimum pH as described above. &#x003b1;AI-1 at concentrations ranging from 0 to 1 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> was preincubated with the insect extracts for 15 min at room temperature before the substrate was added. Results were expressed as the percentage of &#x003b1;-amylase activity relative to that in the absence of the inhibitor.</p></sec><sec id="s2b4"><title>Characterization of general proteolytic activity</title><p>For determination of general proteolytic activity in the bruchid <italic>C. chinensis</italic> and in the parasitoids <italic>H. prosopidis</italic>, <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>, and <italic>A. calandrae</italic>, a series of overlapping buffers (see section 2.2.2) was used to generate a pH range from 3 to 11. The standard assay volume was 100 &#x000b5;l, which contained 10 &#x000b5;g of insect protein extract and sulfanilamide-azocasein as substrate added to a final concentration of 0.5&#x00025; (w/v). Samples were subsequently incubated overnight at 30&#x000b0;C. The reaction was stopped by the addition of 50 &#x000b5;l of ice-cold 10&#x00025; TCA. Samples were then centrifuged at 10,000 <italic>g</italic> for 5 min, and 120 &#x000b5;l of the supernatant was added to 18 &#x000b5;l of 5 M NaOH. Finally, absorbance was measured at 450 nm using a SpectrafluorPlus plate reader (Tecan, M&#x000e4;nnedorf, Switzerland), and general proteolytic activity was expressed as Abs<sub>450</sub> min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mg protein<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>.</p><p>The proteolytic activity of the <italic>C. chinensis</italic> extract and of each parasitoid extract was further characterized at its optimum pH in the presence of the following class-specific protease inhibitors: the serine protease inhibitors SKTI (soybean Kunitz trypsin inhibitor) and PMSF (phenylmethylsulphonyl fluoride), the cysteine protease inhibitors E-64 (L-<italic>trans-</italic>epoxysuccinyl-leucylamido-(4-guanidino)-butane) and IAA (iodoacetamide), the aspartic protease inhibitor pepstatin-A, and the metalloprotease inhibitor EDTA (ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid); final assay concentrations were 1 mM, 10 &#x000b5;M, 10 &#x000b5;M, 1 mM, 10 &#x000b5;M, and 10 mM, respectively. Protease inhibitors were incubated at room temperature for 15 min before the substrate was added. All compounds were added in 10 &#x000b5;l of 0.15 M NaCl, except PMSF and pepstatin-A, which were added in 10 &#x000b5;l of DMSO (dimethyl sulfoxide). The doses tested were selected according to the concentrations recommended by Beynon and Salvesen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Beynon1">[23]</xref>.</p><p>All enzymatic assays were carried out in triplicate, and appropriate blanks were used to account for spontaneous breakdown of substrates. Chemicals were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s2c"><title>Effect of Wheat &#x003b1;-AI and SKTI on Female Parasitoid Survival</title><p>Bioassays were conducted to test the effect of the commercial inhibitors wheat &#x003b1;-AI and SKTI on the survival of females of the parasitoids <italic>A. calandrae</italic> and <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>. &#x003b1;-Amylase and serine protease inhibitors are known to have detrimental effects on pests of stored products. The two parasitoid species were selected because they are synovigenic and belong to different hymenopteran families. Females of <italic>A. calandrae</italic> and <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> from the rearing colonies were collected after emergence (&#x0003c;24 h), individually kept in plastic boxes (2&#x000d7;2&#x000d7;1.5 cm), and provided with two 0.5-&#x000b5;l droplets of a 2 M sucrose solution containing different concentrations of either wheat &#x003b1;-AI or SKTI (0, 0.1, and 1&#x00025;, w/v). In the bioassay with wheat &#x003b1;-AI, potato starch (20 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was added to the sucrose solution to stimulate &#x003b1;-amylase, whereas in the bioassay with SKTI, BSA (20 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was added to stimulate protease activity. Thirty females were tested per treatment. The food solutions were changed three times per week and were never completely consumed during this time period. Survival of the females was recorded daily. Bioassays were conducted in a climate chamber at 25&#x000b1;2&#x000b0;C, 70&#x000b1;5&#x00025; RH, and 16:8 h L:D. Previous assays had shown that both parasitoids ingest the sucrose solution containing either of the two inhibitors (unpublished observations).</p></sec><sec id="s2d"><title>Data Analysis</title><p>The survival response of female parasitoids to wheat &#x003b1;-AI or SKTI was analyzed using the Kaplan-Meier procedure and Logrank test. The &#x003b1;-level was set at 5&#x00025;. Statistical analyses were conducted with the software package Statistica (Version 9, StatSoft Inc., Tulsa, OK, USA).</p></sec></sec><sec id="s3"><title>Results</title><sec id="s3a"><title>Characterization of &#x003b1;-amylase Activity</title><p>We analyzed the optimum pH, the specific activity, and the effect of two specific &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitors on the hydrolysis of potato starch to characterize &#x003b1;-amylase activity in several bruchid and hymenopteran parasitoids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036862-t001">Table 1</xref>). &#x003b1;-Amylase activity was detected over a broad range of pH in both bruchids and parasitoids. In general, &#x003b1;-amylase activity was much higher in bruchids than in the parasitic wasps, and in females than in larvae of parasitoids. Hydrolysis of potato starch was greatest at pH 5.5 in all bruchid larvae and at pH 5 to 7 in parasitoid larvae and females. Hydrolysis of potato starch was greatly inhibited by acarbose and wheat &#x003b1;AI in extracts from all insects.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0036862-t001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036862.t001</object-id><label>Table 1</label><caption><title>&#x003b1;-Amylase activity (mg of maltose liberated min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mg<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> protein) and inhibition of potato starch hydrolysis by the specific inhibitors acarbose and wheat &#x003b1;AI in extracts of bruchids and hymenopteran parasitoids.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0036862-t001-1" xlink:href="pone.0036862.t001"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Source of extract</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">&#x003b1;-Amylase activity</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Inhibition (&#x00025;)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt103">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt101">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Optimum pH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific activity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt102">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Acarbose (10<sup>&#x02212;3&#x00025;</sup>)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Wheat &#x003b1;AI (10<sup>&#x02212;3&#x00025;</sup>)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chrysomelidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. obtectus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.68&#x000b1;0.010</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.9&#x000b1;0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.9&#x000b1;1.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. chinensis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#x000b1;0.023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">98.0&#x000b1;1.09</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">51.2&#x000b1; 3.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. maculatus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.5</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.51&#x000b1;0.032</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.2&#x000b1;0.33</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">91.4&#x000b1;0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braconidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>H. prosopidis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#x000b1;0.006</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">35.0&#x000b1;1.77</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">71.7&#x000b1;0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.14&#x000b1;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">97.9&#x000b1;0.17</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.8&#x000b1;1.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eupelmidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. vuilleti</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.17&#x000b1;0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">77.8&#x000b1;0.26</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">73.0&#x000b1;1.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.25&#x000b1;0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">95.6&#x000b1;0.61</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.4&#x000b1;4.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pteromalidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. calandrae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000b1;0.000</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">99.2&#x000b1;0.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.1&#x000b1;1.96</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.81&#x000b1;0.023</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2&#x000b1;0.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">87.4&#x000b1;2.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>D. basalis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.21&#x000b1;0.001</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">60.4&#x000b1;3.37</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">63.7&#x000b1;4.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.38&#x000b1;0.017</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">94.4&#x000b1;0.30</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">49.6&#x000b1;1.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>L. distinguendus</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x000b1;0.003</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">96.2&#x000b1;0.80</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">82.2&#x000b1;0.00</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.84&#x000b1;0.032</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">61.6&#x000b1;1.91</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.9&#x000b1;4.57</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt101"><label>a</label><p>L &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; larvae; F &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; females.</p></fn><fn id="nt102"><label>b</label><p>Values are means &#x000b1; SE of triplicate measurements for a unique pool of extracts.</p></fn><fn id="nt103"><label>c</label><p>The percentage of inhibition was calculated as [1-(activity with an inhibitor/activity in control) &#x000d7;100]. Inhibition was measured at the optimum pH.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3b"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> Inhibitory Activity of Purified <italic>Phaseolus Vulgaris</italic> &#x003b1;AI-1</title><p><italic>In vitro</italic> inhibition studies were conducted to assess the susceptibility of bruchids and parasitoids to purified &#x003b1;AI-1. &#x003b1;-Amylase activity in extracts from all parasitoid larvae and females was reduced by the inhibitor (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g001">Fig. 1B&#x02013;F</xref>). Except for <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g001">Fig. 1C</xref>), inhibition was greater in females than in larvae of parasitoids. &#x003b1;-Amylase inhibition caused by &#x003b1;AI-1 in the susceptible bruchid species <italic>C. chinensis</italic> and <italic>C. maculatus</italic> was similar to that in the hymenopteran parasitoids (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>). As expected, the &#x003b1;-amylase activity of <italic>A. obtectus</italic> was not inhibited by &#x003b1;AI-1 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g001">Fig. 1A</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0036862-g001" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036862.g001</object-id><label>Figure 1</label><caption><title><italic>In vitro</italic> activity of &#x003b1;AI-1 from <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>.</title><p>Inhibitory activity of &#x003b1;AI-1 against &#x003b1;-amylase activity in extracts of (A) three bruchids (<italic>Acanthoscelides obtectus</italic>, <italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic>, and <italic>Callosobruchus maculatus</italic>) and in extracts of larvae and adult females of the hymenopteran parasitoids (B) <italic>Heterospilus prosopidis</italic>, (C) <italic>Eupelmus vuilleti</italic>, (D) <italic>Anisopteromalus calandrae</italic>, (E) <italic>Dinarmus basalis</italic>, and (F) <italic>Lariophagus distinguendus</italic>. Relative activity was calculated as [(activity with &#x003b1;AI-1/activity without &#x003b1;AI-1)&#x000d7;100]. Bars represent means &#x000b1; SE of three measurements from a unique pool of extracts.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0036862.g001"/></fig></sec><sec id="s3c"><title>Characterization of General Proteolytic Activity</title><p>We characterized proteolytic activity in protein extracts of the bruchid <italic>C. chinensis</italic> and the parasitoids <italic>H. prosopidis</italic>, <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>, and <italic>A. calandrae</italic>. Hydrolysis of the general substrate azocasein occurred over a broad range of pH in all species, although the profile differed for <italic>C. chinensis</italic> vs. the three parasitoids (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036862-t002">Table 2</xref>). While azocasein was hydrolyzed mainly at acidic pH values by the bruchid, and bruchid proteolytic activity was highest at pH 5.0, proteolysis in parasitoid larvae and females was highest at alkaline pH values. Proteolytic activities were further characterized with specific diagnostic protease inhibitors (<xref ref-type="table" rid="pone-0036862-t002">Table 2</xref>). Proteolytic activity of <italic>C. chinensis</italic> was inhibited by the cysteine-like protease inhibitors E-64 and IAA, and by the aspartic protease inhibitor pepstatin-A. In contrast, general proteolysis was inhibited by the serine proteases inhibitors SKTI and PMSF in larvae of the parasitoids <italic>H. prosopidis</italic> and <italic>A. calandrae,</italic> and only by SKTI in <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> larvae. Hydrolysis of azocasein was reduced by SKTI and the metalloproteases inhibitor EDTA in females of <italic>A. calandrae</italic> and <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>. Together, these results indicate that the proteolytic mechanisms differ for the bruchid <italic>C. chinensis</italic> and the three parasitoids: whereas <italic>C. chinensis</italic> relies on cysteine and aspartic proteases, parasitoid larvae rely on serine proteases, and parasitoid females rely on serine proteases and metalloproteases.</p><table-wrap id="pone-0036862-t002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036862.t002</object-id><label>Table 2</label><caption><title>Proteolytic activity (as indicated by Abs<sub>450</sub> min<sup>&#x02212;1</sup> mg protein<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) and inhibition of azocasein hydrolysis by specific protease inhibitors in extracts of <italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic> and three parasitoid species.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic id="pone-0036862-t002-2" xlink:href="pone.0036862.t002"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col align="left" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/><col align="center" span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><td colspan="3" align="left" rowspan="1">Source of extract</td><td colspan="2" align="left" rowspan="1">Proteolytic activity</td><td colspan="6" align="left" rowspan="1">Inhibition (&#x00025;)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt106">c</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Family</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Species</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Stage<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt104">a</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Optimum pH</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Specific activity<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="nt105">b</xref></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">PMSF (10 mM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">SKTI (10 &#x000b5;M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">E-64 (10 &#x000b5;M)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">IAA (1 mM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">EDTA (10 mM)</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pepstatin-A (10 &#x000b5;M)</td></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chrysomelidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>C. chinensis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">22.2&#x000b1;0.12</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">68.2&#x000b1;1.03</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">52.6&#x000b1;0.39</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">34.9&#x000b1;2.56</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Braconidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>H. prosopidis</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">216.4&#x000b1;17.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">24.4&#x000b1;4.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4&#x000b1;2.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.1&#x000b1;0.55</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">nd</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Eupelmidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>E. vuilleti</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">196.7&#x000b1;1.15</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">83.1&#x000b1;1.20</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.0&#x000b1;1.56</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">78.6&#x000b1;0.89</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">40.6&#x000b1;3.95</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pteromalidae</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>A. calandrae</italic></td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">L</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">9.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">147.2&#x000b1;9.88</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">36.3&#x000b1;4.18</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">75.4&#x000b1;2.78</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">F</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.0</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">144.2&#x000b1;4.10</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">69.3&#x000b1;1.24</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">86.5&#x000b1;0.98</td><td align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">ni</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="nt104"><label>a</label><p>L &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; larvae; F &#x0200a;=&#x0200a; females.</p></fn><fn id="nt105"><label>b</label><p>Values are means &#x000b1; SE of triplicate measurements for a unique pool of extracts.</p></fn><fn id="nt106"><label>c</label><p>The percentage of inhibition was calculated as [1-(activity with an inhibitor/activity in control) &#x000d7;100]. Inhibition was measured at the optimum pH.</p></fn><fn id="nt107"><label/><p>Protease inhibitors abbreviations: PMSF (phenylmethylsulphonyl fluoride), SKTI (soybean Kunitz trypsin inhibitor), E-64 (L-<italic>trans-</italic>epoxysuccinyl-leucylamido-(4-guanidino)-butane), IAA (iodoacetamide), EDTA (ethylenediaminetetraacetic acid).</p></fn><fn id="nt108"><label/><p>&#x0201c;ni&#x0201d;: inhibition &#x0003c;10&#x00025;.</p></fn><fn id="nt109"><label/><p>&#x0201c;nd&#x0201d;: not determine.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec id="s3d"><title>Effect of Two Digestive Inhibitors, Wheat &#x003b1;AI and SKTI, on Female Parasitoid Survival</title><p>The effect of wheat &#x003b1;-AI and the serine protease inhibitor SKTI on the survival of <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> and <italic>A. calandrae</italic> females was investigated <italic>in vivo</italic>. For <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>, female longevity in the control treatments was 51.0&#x000b1;2.64 days (mean &#x000b1; SE) in the wheat &#x003b1;-AI assay and 31.9&#x000b1;1.67 days in the SKTI assay. For <italic>A. calandrae</italic>, female longevity in the control treatments was 75.8&#x000b1;2.32 days in the wheat &#x003b1;-AI assay and 66.2&#x000b1;3.65 days in the SKTI assay. The survival of <italic>E. vuillleti</italic> and <italic>A. calandrae</italic> fed with 1&#x00025; wheat &#x003b1;-AI was significantly lower than in the control (<italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.007 and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.035, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g002">Fig. 2A, 2C</xref>). SKTI significantly decreased the survival of <italic>A. calandrae</italic> at 0.1&#x00025; and 1&#x00025; concentration (<italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.001 and <italic>P</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;0.044, respectively) (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g002">Fig. 2D</xref>) whereas no effect was observed in <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> females (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="pone-0036862-g002">Fig. 2B</xref>).</p><fig id="pone-0036862-g002" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pone.0036862.g002</object-id><label>Figure 2</label><caption><title>Effect of wheat &#x003b1;AI and SKTI on bruchid parasitoids.</title><p>Survival of females of the parasitoids <italic>Eupelmus vuilleti</italic> (2A, 2B) and (2C, 2D) <italic>Anisopteromalus calandrae</italic> fed with a 2 M sucrose solution containing different amounts of either wheat &#x003b1;AI or the serine protease inhibitor SKTI. (<italic>N</italic>&#x0200a;=&#x0200a;28&#x02212;30). Potato starch or BSA (20 &#x000b5;g ml<sup>&#x02212;1</sup>) was added to the sucrose solution to stimulate &#x003b1;-amylase and protease activity, respectively. An asterisk indicates that survival was significantly lower with wheat &#x003b1;AI or SKTI than with the control (Logrank test, <italic>P</italic>&#x0003c;0.05).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="pone.0036862.g002"/></fig></sec></sec><sec id="s4"><title>Discussion</title><sec id="s4a"><title>Characterization of &#x003b1;-amylase Activity</title><p>&#x003b1;-Amylase activity has been mainly studied in lepidopteran and coleopteran (including bruchids) storage pests. Only a few studies have characterized the &#x003b1;-amylase activity in insect predators <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ferreira1">[24]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Oliveira1">[27]</xref> and parasitoids <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Kluh1">[28]</xref>, and to our knowledge &#x003b1;-amylase activity has never been characterized in any parasitoid of bruchids. In our study, significant &#x003b1;-amylase activity was measured in extracts of all parasitoid species tested. Hydrolysis of potato starch was highest at pH 5&#x02013;6 for larval extracts and at pH 6&#x02013;7 for female extracts. Similar pH values for optimal &#x003b1;-amylase activity were recorded by Kluh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Kluh1">[28]</xref> for three hymenopteran species that included adults of the ichneumonid <italic>Venturia canescens</italic> Grav., which is an endoparasitoid of lepidopteran larvae. As previously reported by Podoler and Applebaum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Podoler1">[29]</xref>, Campos et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Campos1">[30]</xref>, and Franco et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Franco2">[31]</xref>, &#x003b1;-amylase activity in the bruchid larvae in the current study was optimal under acidic conditions. &#x003b1;-Amylase activity in parasitoid extracts was usually greater in females than in larvae. This difference might be due to the ability of female parasitoids to feed on carbohydrate-rich sources, like floral and extra-floral nectar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Jervis1">[32]</xref>. Except for extracts from <italic>A. calandrae</italic> and <italic>L. distinguendus</italic> females, &#x003b1;-amylase activity was lower in parasitic wasp extracts than in bruchid larval extracts. This is not surprising because bruchid larvae exclusively feed on starchy legume seeds and therefore rely mainly on &#x003b1;-amylases for food digestion.</p></sec><sec id="s4b"><title><italic>In vitro</italic> Inhibitory Activity of Purified <italic>Phaseolus Vulgaris</italic> &#x003b1;AI-1</title><p>In our study, the &#x003b1;-amylase activity of all hymenopteran parasitoids was reduced when exposed to purified &#x003b1;AI-1. With the exception of <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>, <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibition was higher in females than in larvae. For comparison, larval extracts of the bruchids <italic>A. obtectus</italic>, <italic>C. chinensis</italic>, and <italic>C. maculatus</italic> were also exposed to purified &#x003b1;AI-1. The &#x003b1;-amylase activity of <italic>C. chinensis</italic> and <italic>C. maculatus</italic> larvae was reduced by &#x003b1;AI-1, and the reduction was greater for <italic>C. maculatus</italic>. This is in agreement with previous reports that neither species was able to grow on seeds of the common bean <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ishii1">[33]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Janzen1">[34]</xref>. In contrast, the &#x003b1;-amylase activity in larval extracts of <italic>A. obtectus</italic> was insensitive to &#x003b1;AI-1. The reasons for which <italic>A. obtectus</italic> can survive on common beans remain unknown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ishimoto4">[35]</xref>. Our <italic>in vitro</italic> results with larvae of the three bruchid species are in agreement with those published by Ishimoto and Kitamura <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ishimoto2">[21]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Ishimoto3">[22]</xref>. Our results also revealed that the inhibition of &#x003b1;-amylase activity by &#x003b1;AI-1 in the parasitoids was similar to that in their bruchid hosts.</p><p>The inhibitor &#x003b1;AI-1 has been shown to have a broad spectrum of <italic>in vitro</italic> activity against arthropods. Kluh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Kluh1">[28]</xref> screened the <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibitory activity of purified &#x003b1;AI-1 against &#x003b1;-amylases from 30 arthropod species representing nine orders. The &#x003b1;-amylases from coleopteran, dipteran, and hymenopteran species, including that from the parasitoid <italic>V. canescens</italic>, were susceptible to the inhibitor. Together with our results, it appears that coleopteran and hymenopteran species are highly sensitive to &#x003b1;AI-1 in general. In contrast, &#x003b1;-amylase activities of lepidopteran larvae as well as of those species belonging to Blattodea, Psocoptera, Orthoptera, Hemiptera, and Acari were not inhibited by &#x003b1;AI-1 at concentrations up to 1 &#x000b5;M <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Kluh1">[28]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4c"><title>Characterization of General Proteolytic Activity</title><p>We partially characterized the proteolytic enzymes in larval and female extracts of the parasitic wasps <italic>H. prosopidis</italic>, <italic>E. vuilleti</italic>, and <italic>A. calandrae</italic>, and in larval extracts of the bruchid <italic>C. chinensis</italic>. General proteolytic activity in the parasitic wasps was highest under alkaline conditions and higher in larvae than in females. This might be due to different nutritional requirements of females vs. larvae: while females consume the small amounts of haemolymph that exude from punctures in the host cuticle <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Jervis2">[36]</xref>, the larvae consume most of their host. The ability of extracts to hydrolyze the general substrate azocasein, the optimal pH for hydrolysis, and the sensitivity to a range of protease inhibitors demonstrated that larvae predominantly rely on serine proteases for protein digestion while <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> and <italic>A. calandrae</italic> females contain both serine proteases and metalloproteases. Because females are host-feeders, they feed from the same resource as the larvae. Such serine-protease based digestive metabolism has been previously reported from other hymenopteran species, including ants <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Whitworth1">[37]</xref>, bees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Moritz1">[38]</xref>, bumblebees <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Malone1">[39]</xref>, and parasitic wasps. Trypsin- and chymotrypsin-like activities were detected in larvae of the ectoparasitoid <italic>Eulophus pennicornis</italic> (Nees) (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae) <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Down1">[40]</xref>. Similarly, the predominant proteases detected in larvae of the ectoparasitoid <italic>Habrobracon hebetor</italic> Say (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) and in larvae and adults of the aphid parasitoids <italic>Aphelinus abdominalis</italic> Dalman (Hymenoptera: Aphelinidae) and <italic>Aphidius ervi</italic> Haliday (Hymenoptera: Braconidae) belonged to the serine protease class <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Baker1">[41]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Azzouz2">[43]</xref>. In contrast to parasitic wasps, maximal hydrolysis of azocaseine in larval extracts of the bruchid <italic>C. chinensis</italic> occurred at acidic pH. Indeed, the proteolytic enzymes detected differed between <italic>C. chinensis</italic> larvae and their hymenopteran parasitoids in that both cysteine and aspartic proteases were detected in <italic>C. chinensis</italic> larvae but not in the parasitoids. Our results agree with those of similar studies conducted with several bruchid species, including <italic>C. chinensis</italic><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Kitch1">[44]</xref>&#x02013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Melo1">[47]</xref>.</p></sec><sec id="s4d"><title>Effect of Digestive Inhibitors (Wheat &#x003b1;AI and SKTI) on Female Parasitoid Survival</title><p>The two parasitoids tested in our study differed in susceptibility to digestive enzyme inhibitors. The survival of the <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> females was reduced by wheat &#x003b1;AI, while the survival of <italic>A. calandrae</italic> was reduced by wheat &#x003b1;AI and the serine protease inhibitor SKTI. Although serine protease activity in extracts of <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> was inhibited <italic>in vitro</italic> by SKTI, no effect was observed when the protease inhibitor was administered <italic>in vivo</italic>. This could be explained by the ability of some natural enemies to adapt their digestive metabolism to the presence of plant antidigestive proteins <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-lvarezAlfageme1">[48]</xref>.</p><p>The negative effects of the test compounds on both parasitoids are unlikely to be biologically relevant because females that fed on &#x003b1;AI and SKTI survived much longer than required for oviposition. Survival of susceptible females that consumed &#x003b1;AI and SKTI was not affected until after day 50, but in previous studies, female <italic>A. calandrae</italic> and <italic>E. vuilleti</italic> kept on seeds infested with bruchid larvae, and thus able to oviposit, lived for only 10 and 13 days, respectively <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Schmale1">[14]</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Giron1">[49]</xref>. Only a few studies have assessed the <italic>in vivo</italic> effects of serine protease inhibitors on hymenopteran parasitoids, and the impact of digestive enzyme inhibitors on bruchid parasitoids has never been previously evaluated. Negative, host-mediated effects of the cowpea trypsin inhibitor (CpTI) and the soybean Bowman-Birk inhibitor (SbBBI) on adult <italic>E. pennicornis</italic> and <italic>A. abdominalis</italic> were reported by Bell et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Bell1">[50]</xref> and Azzouz et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Azzouz1">[42]</xref>, respectively. When those parasitoid species were directly fed with sugar solutions containing the protease inhibitor, however, no detrimental effects were observed, suggesting that the negative effects were due to reduced host quality (because the hosts are known to be susceptible to the test compound) rather than to a direct effect of the inhibitor.</p></sec><sec id="s4e"><title>Conclusions</title><p>This is the first study to characterize the &#x003b1;-amylase and proteolytic enzymes in parasitoids of bruchids and to assess the <italic>in vitro</italic> susceptibility of the parasitoids to &#x003b1;AI-1. The results of our study also provide information required by the model of L&#x000fc;thi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="pone.0036862-Lthi1">[17]</xref>, which assesses the potential effects of GM legumes on non-target species.</p><p>The results of this study indicate that serine proteases are the main digestive enzymes in all the parasitoids of bruchids that were tested, whereas cysteine proteases are the main digestive enzymes in bruchid larvae. It follows that the use of GM legumes expressing cysteine protease inhibitors to control bruchids should be compatible with the control provided by hymenopteran parasitoids. We have also detected significant levels of &#x003b1;-amylase activity in larval and female extracts of several hymenopteran parasitoid species used for bruchid control. Subsequent <italic>in vitro</italic> inhibition studies showed that sensitivity of &#x003b1;-amylase activity to &#x003b1;AI-1 in the bruchid antagonists was comparable to that in the target species, suggesting that parasitoids might be negatively affected by &#x003b1;AI-1-expressing legumes if they consume this inhibitor when feeding on their hosts. Direct feeding assays performed in our study under worst-case exposure conditions revealed that harmful effects of &#x003b1;AI on bruchid parasitoids cannot be discounted. Future bioassays should therefore be conducted under more realistic exposure conditions to evaluate the compatibility of &#x003b1;AI-1-expressing GM legumes with biological control agents for bruchid management.</p></sec></sec></body><back><ack><p>We are grateful to T.J.V. Higgins for providing purified &#x003b1;AI-1 and to F. Ortego for helpful comments on earlier drafts of the manuscript.</p></ack><fn-group><fn fn-type="conflict"><p><bold>Competing Interests: </bold>The authors have declared that no competing interests exist.</p></fn><fn fn-type="financial-disclosure"><p><bold>Funding: </bold>This study was partly funded by the National Center of Competence in Research (NCCR) Plant Survival, a research program of the Swiss National Science Foundation. No additional external funding received for this study. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</p></fn></fn-group><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="pone.0036862-Popelka1"><label>1</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Popelka</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Terryn</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Higgins</surname><given-names>TJV</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Gene technology for grain legumes: Can it contribute to the food challenge in developing countries?</article-title>
<source>Plant Sci</source>
<volume>167</volume>
<fpage>195</fpage>
<lpage>206</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Nukenine1"><label>2</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Nukenine</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Stored product protection in Africa: Past, present and future.</article-title>
<source>Julius-K&#x000fc;hn-Archiv</source>
<volume>425</volume>
<fpage>26</fpage>
<lpage>41</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Odogola1"><label>3</label><element-citation publication-type="book">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Odogola</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1994</year>
<article-title>Postharvest management and storage of food legumes.</article-title>
<publisher-name>Technical Systems for Agriculture. AGROTEC UNDP/OPS, Harare, Zimbabwe</publisher-name>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Philips1"><label>4</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Philips</surname><given-names>TW</given-names></name><name><surname>Throne</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>Biorational approaches to managing stored-product insects.</article-title>
<source>Ann Rev Entomol</source>
<volume>55</volume>
<fpage>375</fpage>
<lpage>397</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">19737083</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Franco1"><label>5</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigden</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Grossi-de-S&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>MF</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Plant &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitors and their interaction with insect &#x003b1;-amylases. Structure, function and potential for crop protection.</article-title>
<source>Eur J Biochem</source>
<volume>269</volume>
<fpage>397</fpage>
<lpage>412</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11856298</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Schroeder1"><label>6</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Gollasch</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tabe</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Craig</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1995</year>
<article-title>Bean &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor confers resistance to the pea weevil (<italic>Bruchus pisorum</italic>) in transgenic peas (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>107</volume>
<fpage>1233</fpage>
<lpage>1239</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228429</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Ishimoto1"><label>7</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Sato</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Bruchid resistance of transgenic azuki bean expressing seed &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor of common bean.</article-title>
<source>Entomol Exp Appl</source>
<volume>79</volume>
<fpage>309</fpage>
<lpage>315</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Sarmah1"><label>8</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sarmah</surname><given-names>BK</given-names></name><name><surname>Moore</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Tate</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Molvig</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Transgenic chickpea seeds expressing high levels of a bean &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor.</article-title>
<source>Mol Breeding</source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>73</fpage>
<lpage>82</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Solleti1"><label>9</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Solleti</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Bakshi</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Purkayasthan</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Panda</surname><given-names>SK</given-names></name><name><surname>Sahoo</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Transgenic cowpea (<italic>Vigna unguiculata</italic>) seeds expressing a bean &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor 1 confer resistance to storage pests, bruchid beetles.</article-title>
<source>Plant Cell Rep</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>1841</fpage>
<lpage>1850</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18784925</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Morton1"><label>10</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morton</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Schroeder</surname><given-names>HE</given-names></name><name><surname>Bateman</surname><given-names>KS</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Armstrong</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Bean alpha amylase inhibitor 1 in transgenic peas (<italic>Pisum sativum</italic>) provides complete protection from pea weevil (<italic>Bruchus pisorum</italic>) under field conditions.</article-title>
<source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>3820</fpage>
<lpage>3825</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10759552</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Koiwa1"><label>11</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Koiwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Zhu-Salzman</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Subramanian</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Phage display selection can differentiate insecticidal activity of soybean cystatins.</article-title>
<source>Plant J</source>
<volume>14</volume>
<fpage>371</fpage>
<lpage>379</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9628031</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Amirhusin1"><label>12</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amirhusin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Koiwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bressan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Soyacystatin N inhibits proteolysis of wheat &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor and potentiates toxicity against cowpea weevil.</article-title>
<source>J Econ Entomol</source>
<volume>97</volume>
<fpage>2095</fpage>
<lpage>2100</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15666770</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Amirhusin2"><label>13</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Amirhusin</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Shade</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Koiwa</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Hasegawa</surname><given-names>PM</given-names></name><name><surname>Bressan</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Protease inhibitors from several classes work synergistically against <italic>Callosobruchus maculatus</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J Insect Physiol</source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>734</fpage>
<lpage>740</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17482206</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Schmale1"><label>14</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmale</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2001</year>
<article-title>Control potential of three hymenopteran parasitoid species against the bean weevil in stored beans: the effect of adult parasitoid nutrition on longevity and progeny production.</article-title>
<source>Biol Control</source>
<volume>21</volume>
<fpage>134</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Schmale2"><label>15</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Schmale</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>W&#x000e4;ckers</surname><given-names>FL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Combining parasitoids and plant resistance for the control of the bruchid <italic>Acanthoscelides obtectus</italic> in stored beans.</article-title>
<source>J Stored Prod Res</source>
<volume>39</volume>
<fpage>401</fpage>
<lpage>411</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Velten1"><label>16</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Velten</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Rott</surname><given-names>AS</given-names></name><name><surname>Conde Petit</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Cardona</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Dorn</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2008</year>
<article-title>Improved bruchid management through favorable host plant traits and natural enemies.</article-title>
<source>Biol Control</source>
<volume>47</volume>
<fpage>133</fpage>
<lpage>140</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Lthi1"><label>17</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>L&#x000fc;thi</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez-Alfageme</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Romeis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2010</year>
<article-title>The potential of transgenic legumes in integrated bruchid management: assessing the impact on bruchid parasitoids.</article-title>
<source>Julius-K&#x000fc;hn-Archiv</source>
<volume>425</volume>
<fpage>977</fpage>
<lpage>982</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Bradford1"><label>18</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bradford</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>A rapid and sensitive method for the quantitation of microgram quantities of protein utilizing the principle of protein-dye binding.</article-title>
<source>Anal Biochem</source>
<volume>72</volume>
<fpage>248</fpage>
<lpage>254</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">942051</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Bernfeld1"><label>19</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bernfeld</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1955</year>
<article-title>Amylases, &#x003b1; and &#x003b2;.</article-title>
<source>Methods Enzymol</source>
<volume>1</volume>
<fpage>149</fpage>
<lpage>158</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Marshall1"><label>20</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>JJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Lauda</surname><given-names>CM</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1975</year>
<article-title>Purification and properties of phaseolamin, an inhibitor of &#x003b1;-amylase, from kidney bean, <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>250</volume>
<fpage>8030</fpage>
<lpage>8037</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">240849</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Ishimoto2"><label>21</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Growth inhibitory effects of &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor from the kidney bean, <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic> (L) on 3 species of bruchids (Coleoptera, Bruchidae).</article-title>
<source>Appl Entomol Zool</source>
<volume>24</volume>
<fpage>281</fpage>
<lpage>286</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Ishimoto3"><label>22</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitamura</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1992</year>
<article-title>Tolerance to the seed &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor by the two insect pests of the common bean, <italic>Zabrotes subfasciatus</italic> and <italic>Acanthoscelides obtectus</italic> (Coleoptera, Bruchidae).</article-title>
<source>Appl Entomol Zool</source>
<volume>27</volume>
<fpage>243</fpage>
<lpage>251</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Beynon1"><label>23</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Beynon</surname><given-names>RJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Salvesen</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Proteolytic enzymes: a practical approach.</article-title>
<source>In: Beynon RJ, Bond JS (Eds.) IRL Press at Oxford Inoversoty Press, Oxford,</source>
<volume>241&#x02013;249</volume>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Ferreira1"><label>24</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ferreira</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Terra</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Spatial organization of digestion, secretory mechanisms and digestive enzyme properties in <italic>Pheropsophus aequinoctialis</italic> (Coleoptera, Carabidae).</article-title>
<source>Insect Biochem</source>
<volume>19</volume>
<fpage>383</fpage>
<lpage>391</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Zeng1"><label>25</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zeng</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Demonstration of amylase from the zoophytophagous anthocorid <italic>Orius insidiosus</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Arch Insect Biochem</source>
<volume>44</volume>
<fpage>136</fpage>
<lpage>139</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Boyd1"><label>26</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boyd</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Cohen</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Alverson</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2002</year>
<article-title>Digestive enzymes and stylet morphology of <italic>Deraeocoris nebulosis</italic> (Hemiptera: Miridae), a predacious plant bug.</article-title>
<source>Ann Entomol Soc Am</source>
<volume>95</volume>
<fpage>395</fpage>
<lpage>401</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Oliveira1"><label>27</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Oliveira</surname><given-names>MG</given-names></name><name><surname>Guedes</surname><given-names>RN</given-names></name><name><surname>Soares</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2006</year>
<article-title>Morphology and preliminary enzyme characterization of the salivary glands from the predatory bug <italic>Podisus nigrispinus</italic> (Heteroptera: Pentatomidae).</article-title>
<source>Bull Entomol Res</source>
<volume>96</volume>
<fpage>251</fpage>
<lpage>258</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16768813</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Kluh1"><label>28</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kluh</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Horn</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>H&#x000fd;blov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Hubert</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Dole&#x0010d;kov&#x000e1;-Mare&#x00161;ov&#x000e1;</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Inhibitory specificity and insecticidal selectivity of &#x003b1;-amylase inhibitor from <italic>Phaseolus vulgaris</italic>.</article-title>
<source>Phytochemistry</source>
<volume>66</volume>
<fpage>31</fpage>
<lpage>39</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15649508</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Podoler1"><label>29</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Podoler</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Applebau</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1971</year>
<article-title>Alpha-amylase of beetle <italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic> &#x02013; Properties.</article-title>
<source>Biochem J</source>
<volume>121</volume>
<fpage>321</fpage>
<lpage>325</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5000646</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Campos1"><label>30</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Campos</surname><given-names>FAP</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Ary</surname><given-names>MB</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1989</year>
<article-title>Resolution and partial characterization of proteinases and alpha-amylases from midguts of larvae of the bruchid beetle <italic>Callosobruchus maculatus</italic> (F.).</article-title>
<source>Comp Biochem Phys B</source>
<volume>92</volume>
<fpage>51</fpage>
<lpage>57</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Franco2"><label>31</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mendes</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name><name><surname>Paes</surname><given-names>NS</given-names></name><name><surname>Yokoyama</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Characterization of two <italic>Acanthoscelides obtectus</italic> &#x003b1;-amylases and their inactivation by wheat inhibitors.</article-title>
<source>J Agr Food Chem</source>
<volume>53</volume>
<fpage>1585</fpage>
<lpage>1590</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15740044</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Jervis1"><label>32</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jervis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>NAC</given-names></name><name><surname>Heimpel</surname><given-names>GE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Parasitoid adult feeding behaviour and biocontrol &#x02013; a review.</article-title>
<source>Biocontrol News and Information</source>
<volume>17</volume>
<fpage>1N</fpage>
<lpage>22N</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Ishii1"><label>33</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishii</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1952</year>
<article-title>Studies on host preference of the cowpea weevil (<italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source>Bull Natl Inst Agr Sci Ser</source>
<volume>C1</volume>
<fpage>185</fpage>
<lpage>256</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Janzen1"><label>34</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Janzen</surname><given-names>DH</given-names></name><name><surname>Juster</surname><given-names>HB</given-names></name><name><surname>Liener</surname><given-names>IE</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1976</year>
<article-title>Insecticidal action of the phytohemagglutinin in black beans on a bruchid beetle.</article-title>
<source>Science</source>
<volume>192</volume>
<fpage>795</fpage>
<lpage>796</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1265481</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Ishimoto4"><label>35</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Chrispeels</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Protective mechanism of the Mexican bean weevil against high levels of alpha-amylase inhibitor in the common bean.</article-title>
<source>Plant Physiol</source>
<volume>111</volume>
<fpage>393</fpage>
<lpage>401</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8787024</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Jervis2"><label>36</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Jervis</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>NAC</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Host-feeding strategies in hymenopteran parasitoids.</article-title>
<source>Biol Rev</source>
<volume>61</volume>
<fpage>395</fpage>
<lpage>434</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Whitworth1"><label>37</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitworth</surname><given-names>ST</given-names></name><name><surname>Blum</surname><given-names>MS</given-names></name><name><surname>Travis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1998</year>
<article-title>Proteolytic enzymes from larvae of the fire ant, <italic>Solenopsis invicta</italic>: Isolation and characterization of four serine endopeptidases.</article-title>
<source>J Biol Chem</source>
<volume>273</volume>
<fpage>14430</fpage>
<lpage>14434</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9603955</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Moritz1"><label>38</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moritz</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Crailsheim</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1987</year>
<article-title>Physiology of protein digestion in the midgut of the honeybee (<italic>Apis mellifera</italic> L.).</article-title>
<source>J Insect Physiol</source>
<volume>33</volume>
<fpage>923</fpage>
<lpage>931</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Malone1"><label>39</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Malone</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Burgess</surname><given-names>EPJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Stefanovic</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatehouse</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Effects of four protease inhibitors on the survival of worker bumblebees, <italic>Bombus terrestris</italic> L. Apidologie</article-title>
<volume>31</volume>
<fpage>25</fpage>
<lpage>38</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Down1"><label>40</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Down</surname><given-names>RE</given-names></name><name><surname>Ford</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Mosson</surname><given-names>HJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fitches</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatehouse</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1999</year>
<article-title>Protease activity in the larval stage of the parasitoid wasp, <italic>Eulophus pennicornis</italic> (Nees) (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae); effects of protease inhibitors.</article-title>
<source>Parasitology</source>
<volume>119</volume>
<fpage>157</fpage>
<lpage>166</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10466123</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Baker1"><label>41</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Baker</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Fabrick</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2000</year>
<article-title>Host hemolymph proteins and protein digestion in larval <italic>Habrobracon hebetor</italic> (Hymenoptera: Braconidae).</article-title>
<source>Insect Biochem Molec</source>
<volume>30</volume>
<fpage>937</fpage>
<lpage>946</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Azzouz1"><label>42</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azzouz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Campan</surname><given-names>EDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherqui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Saguez</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Couty</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Potential effects of plant protease inhibitors, oryzacystatin I and soybean Bowman-Birk inhibitor, on the aphid parasitoid <italic>Aphidius ervi</italic> Haliday (Hymenoptera, Braconidae).</article-title>
<source>J Insect Physiol</source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>941</fpage>
<lpage>951</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15936030</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Azzouz2"><label>43</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Azzouz</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Cherqui</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Campan</surname><given-names>EDM</given-names></name><name><surname>Rahbe</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Duport</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2005</year>
<article-title>Effects of plant protease inhibitors, oryzacystatin I and soybean Bowman-Birk inhibitor, on the aphid <italic>Macrosiphum euphorbiae</italic> (Homoptera, Aphididae) and its parasitoid <italic>Aphelinus abdominalis</italic> (Hymenoptera, Aphelinidae).</article-title>
<source>J Insect Physiol</source>
<volume>51</volume>
<fpage>75</fpage>
<lpage>86</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15686649</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Kitch1"><label>44</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kitch</surname><given-names>LW</given-names></name><name><surname>Murdock</surname><given-names>LL</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1986</year>
<article-title>Partial characterization of a major gut thiol proteinase from larvae of <italic>Callosobruchus maculatus</italic> F. Arch Insect Biochem</article-title>
<volume>3</volume>
<fpage>561</fpage>
<lpage>575</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Silva1"><label>45</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Silva</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name><name><surname>Xavier-Filho</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>1991</year>
<article-title>Comparison between the levels of aspartic and cysteine proteinases of the larval midguts of <italic>Callosobruchus maculatus</italic> (F) and <italic>Zabrotes subfasciatus</italic> (Boh) (Coleoptera, Bruchidae).</article-title>
<source>Comp Biochem Physiol B</source>
<volume>99</volume>
<fpage>529</fpage>
<lpage>533</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Kuroda1"><label>46</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kuroda</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Ishimoto</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Suzuki</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Kondo</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Abe</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>1996</year>
<article-title>Oryzacystatins exhibit growth-inhibitory and lethal effects on different species of bean insect pests, <italic>Callosobruchus chinensis</italic> (Coleoptera) and <italic>Riptortus clavatus</italic> (Hemiptera).</article-title>
<source>Biosci Biotech Biochem</source>
<volume>60</volume>
<fpage>209</fpage>
<lpage>212</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Melo1"><label>47</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Melo</surname><given-names>FR</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>MO</given-names></name><name><surname>Franco</surname><given-names>OL</given-names></name><name><surname>Rigden</surname><given-names>DJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Mello</surname><given-names>LV</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2003</year>
<article-title>Use of phage display to select novel cystatins specific for <italic>Acanthoscelides obtectus</italic> cysteine proteinases.</article-title>
<source>BBA-Proteins Proteom</source>
<volume>1651</volume>
<fpage>146</fpage>
<lpage>152</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-lvarezAlfageme1"><label>48</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>&#x000c1;lvarez-Alfageme</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name><name><surname>Martinez</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pascual-Ruiz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Castanera</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Diaz</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><etal/></person-group>
<year>2007</year>
<article-title>Effects of potato plants expressing a barley cystatin on the predatory bug <italic>Podisus maculiventris</italic> via herbivorous prey feeding on the plant.</article-title>
<source>Transgenic Res</source>
<volume>16</volume>
<fpage>1</fpage>
<lpage>13</lpage>
<pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17072562</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Giron1"><label>49</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Giron</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Pincebourde</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Casas</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Lifetime gains of host-feeding in a synovigenic parasitic wasp.</article-title>
<source>Physiol Entomol</source>
<volume>29</volume>
<fpage>436</fpage>
<lpage>442</lpage>
</element-citation></ref><ref id="pone.0036862-Bell1"><label>50</label><element-citation publication-type="journal">
<person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bell</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Kirkbride-Smith</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Marris</surname><given-names>GC</given-names></name><name><surname>Edwards</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Gatehouse</surname><given-names>AMR</given-names></name></person-group>
<year>2004</year>
<article-title>Oral toxicity and impact on fecundity of three insecticidal proteins on the gregarious ectoparasitoid <italic>Eulophus pennicornis</italic> (Hymenoptera: Eulophidae).</article-title>
<source>Agr Forest Entomol</source>
<volume>6</volume>
<fpage>215</fpage>
<lpage>222</lpage>
</element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>