<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v1.0 20120330//EN" "JATS-archivearticle1.dtd"> 
<article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article"><?properties open_access?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierValue -//NLM//DTD JATS (Z39.96) Journal Publishing DTD v1.0 20120330//EN?><?DTDIdentifier.IdentifierType public?><?SourceDTD.DTDName JATS-journalpublishing1.dtd?><?SourceDTD.Version 1.0?><?ConverterInfo.XSLTName jp2nlmx2.xsl?><?ConverterInfo.Version 2?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="pmc">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">PeerJ</journal-id><journal-title-group><journal-title>PeerJ</journal-title></journal-title-group><issn pub-type="epub">2167-8359</issn><publisher><publisher-name>PeerJ Inc.</publisher-name><publisher-loc>San Francisco, USA</publisher-loc></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmcid">3932820</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">240</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Ecology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Entomology</subject></subj-group><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Plant Science</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>Comparison of lodgepole and jack pine resin chemistry: implications for range expansion by the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)</article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib id="author-1" contrib-type="author" corresp="yes"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>Erin L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref><email>eclark1@unbc.ca</email></contrib><contrib id="author-2" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Pitt</surname><given-names>Caitlin</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-3" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>Allan L.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-2">2</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-4" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>B. Staffan</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><contrib id="author-5" contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>Dezene P.W.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="aff-1">1</xref></contrib><aff id="aff-1"><label>1</label><institution>Ecosystem Science and Management Program, University of Northern British Columbia</institution>, <addr-line>Prince George</addr-line>, <addr-line>British Columbia</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff><aff id="aff-2"><label>2</label><institution>Department of Forest &#x00026; Conservation Sciences, University of British Columbia</institution>, <addr-line>Vancouver</addr-line>, <addr-line>British Columbia</addr-line>, <country>Canada</country></aff></contrib-group><contrib-group><contrib id="editor-1" contrib-type="editor"><name><surname>Higley</surname><given-names>Leon</given-names></name></contrib></contrib-group><pub-date pub-type="epub" date-type="pub" iso-8601-date="2014-02-11"><day>11</day><month>2</month><year iso-8601-date="2014">2014</year></pub-date><pub-date pub-type="collection"><year>2014</year></pub-date><volume>2</volume><elocation-id>e240</elocation-id><history><date date-type="received" iso-8601-date="2013-10-09"><day>9</day><month>10</month><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year></date><date date-type="accepted" iso-8601-date="2013-12-17"><day>17</day><month>12</month><year iso-8601-date="2013">2013</year></date></history><permissions><copyright-statement>&#x000a9; 2014 Clark et al.</copyright-statement><copyright-year>2014</copyright-year><copyright-holder>Clark et al.</copyright-holder><license license-type="open-access" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/"><license-p> This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/">Creative Commons Attribution License</ext-link>, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited.</license-p></license></permissions><self-uri xlink:href="https://peerj.com/articles/240"/><abstract><p>The mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic>, is a significant pest of lodgepole pine in British Columbia (BC), where it has recently reached an unprecedented outbreak level. Although it is native to western North America, the beetle can now be viewed as a native invasive because for the first time in recorded history it has begun to reproduce in native jack pine stands within the North American boreal forest. The ability of jack pine trees to defend themselves against mass attack and their suitability for brood success will play a major role in the success of this insect in a putatively new geographic range and host. Lodgepole and jack pine were sampled along a transect extending from the beetle&#x02019;s historic range (central BC) to the newly invaded area east of the Rocky Mountains in north-central Alberta (AB) in Canada for constitutive phloem resin terpene levels. In addition, two populations of lodgepole pine (BC) and one population of jack pine (AB) were sampled for levels of induced phloem terpenes. Phloem resin terpenes were identified and quantified using gas chromatography. Significant differences were found in constitutive levels of terpenes between the two species of pine. Constitutive <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene levels &#x02013; a precursor in the biosynthesis of components of the aggregation and antiaggregation pheromones of mountain pine beetle &#x02013; were significantly higher in jack pine. However, lower constitutive levels of compounds known to be toxic to bark beetles, e.g., 3-carene, in jack pine suggests that this species could be poorly defended. Differences in wounding-induced responses for phloem accumulation of five major terpenes were found between the two populations of lodgepole pine and between lodgepole and jack pine. The mountain pine beetle will face a different constitutive and induced phloem resin terpene environment when locating and colonizing jack pine in its new geographic range, and this may play a significant role in the ability of the insect to persist in this new host.</p></abstract><kwd-group kwd-group-type="author"><kwd>Secondary metabolites</kwd><kwd>Terpenes</kwd><kwd>Coleoptera</kwd><kwd>Curculionidae</kwd><kwd>Scolytinae</kwd><kwd>Plant defense</kwd><kwd>Bark beetles</kwd></kwd-group><funding-group><funding-statement>Funding for this research was generously provided by the Natural Resources Canada Mountain Pine Beetle Initiative research grant (8.45), the Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada, the Canada Research Chairs Program, the Canada Foundation for Innovation, and the British Columbia Knowledge Development Fund. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding-statement></funding-group></article-meta></front><body><sec><title>Introduction</title><p>The primary host of the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> Hopkins (Coleoptera: Curculionidae) in its native range in western Canada is lodgepole pine (<italic>Pinus contorta</italic> Dougl. var. <italic>latifolia</italic> Engelm.), but the insect is also capable of utilizing other species of pine, including jack pine (<italic>P. banksiana</italic> Lamb.) (<xref rid="ref-16" ref-type="bibr">Furniss &#x00026; Schenk, 1969</xref>; <xref rid="ref-50" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik &#x00026; Linton, 1982</xref>; <xref rid="ref-5" ref-type="bibr">Cerezke, 1995</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2011</xref>; <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Lodgepole pine is found throughout northwestern North America, but occurs primarily in British Columbia (BC) and north-central Alberta, Canada. The northeastern portion of the range of lodgepole pine is contiguous with jack pine in Alberta. Jack pine extends east across Canada and into the northeastern United States (<xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Little, 1971</xref>). Where the two species&#x02019; ranges overlap, they form a hybrid zone (<xref rid="ref-33" ref-type="bibr">Moss, 1949</xref>), which in recent years has been successfully invaded by the mountain pine beetle (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Langor, Rice &#x00026; Williams, 2007</xref>). More recently, beetles have been found successfully reproducing in pure jack pine stands (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Historically, mountain pine beetle populations have been most common west of the Rocky Mountains (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik &#x00026; Carroll, 2006</xref>). Non-forested prairies, the high elevations of the mountains, and cold winters at higher latitudes have contributed to confining it to that distribution. Its recent invasion of the pine forests east of the Rocky Mountains in north-central Alberta (<xref rid="ref-23" ref-type="bibr">Langor, Rice &#x00026; Williams, 2007</xref>; <xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) has raised concerns that it may have the capacity to spread eastward through Canada&#x02019;s extensive jack pine forest (<xref rid="ref-27" ref-type="bibr">Logan &#x00026; Powell, 2001</xref>; <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2010</xref>).</p><p>Invasion of a novel habitat by either a native or an alien herbivore may require that animal to exploit new host-plant populations or species. Release from competition and/or predation associated with the herbivore&#x02019;s native habitat are other factors that may contribute to the success of an invasive species (<xref rid="ref-21" ref-type="bibr">Keane &#x00026; Crawley, 2002</xref>). Encountering plants that are not able to defend themselves against specific forms of herbivory often enables an invading species to do well in a new environment. For instance, the emerald ash borer, <italic>Agrilus planipennis</italic> Fairmaire (Coleoptera: Buprestidae), an insect native to Asia where it is not considered a major pest, is very destructive to several species of ash (<italic>Fraxinus</italic> spp.) in North America (<xref rid="ref-19" ref-type="bibr">Haack <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2002</xref>; <xref rid="ref-34" ref-type="bibr">Poland &#x00026; McCullough, 2006</xref>). Asian ash species are more resistant to the emerald ash borer (<xref rid="ref-46" ref-type="bibr">Rebek, Herms &#x00026; Smitley, 2008</xref>), possibly due to significant differences in constitutive phloem chemistry, including compounds that are toxic or deterrent to other herbivores (<xref rid="ref-14" ref-type="bibr">Eyles <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2007</xref>).</p><p>In a similar fashion, mountain pine beetle invading previously unoccupied range may encounter hosts not adapted to defending against them, i.e., they enter relatively &#x02018;defense-free space&#x02019; (<xref rid="ref-18" ref-type="bibr">Ghandi &#x00026; Herms, 2010</xref>). <xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Cudmore <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2010)</xref> found that the productivity of beetles was higher in tree populations putatively na&#x000ef;ve to mountain pine beetle outbreaks, but did not investigate potential mechanisms for this phenomenon. In northern Alberta, recent evidence for successful reproduction in jack pine (<xref rid="ref-12" ref-type="bibr">Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2011</xref>) suggests the mountain pine beetle may be successful in these novel hosts, but the fitness and resultant dynamics of beetle populations in this new environment is presently unknown. Factors such as climate, the abundance and distribution of susceptible and suitable host trees, and overall stand structure may play key roles in determining the ultimate outcome of the spread into the jack pine forests. Since the susceptibility and suitability of a potential host tree to the mountain pine beetle is primarily a function of its chemistry (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik &#x00026; Carroll, 2006</xref>) variation in tree chemistry in novel habitats will play a key role in determining the insect&#x02019;s success.</p><p>Among the major defenses used by conifers against attacking organisms are their resin terpenes. Terpenes can serve as attractants or repellants for bark beetles (<xref rid="ref-17" ref-type="bibr">Gershenzon &#x00026; Croteau, 1991</xref>; <xref rid="ref-36" ref-type="bibr">Pureswaran &#x00026; Borden, 2003</xref>; <xref rid="ref-22" ref-type="bibr">Keeling &#x00026; Bohlmann, 2006</xref>) and have been implicated in host selection (<xref rid="ref-32" ref-type="bibr">Moeck &#x00026; Simmons, 1991</xref>). They have been found to be toxic to bark beetles (<xref rid="ref-54" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 1961</xref>, <xref rid="ref-55" ref-type="bibr">1963</xref>, <xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">1965</xref>; <xref rid="ref-45" ref-type="bibr">Raffa <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1985</xref>), precursors to aggregation and anti-aggregation pheromones (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Conn <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1984</xref>), and synergists to pheromones (<xref rid="ref-30" ref-type="bibr">Miller &#x00026; Borden, 1990</xref>; <xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Borden <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Conn <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1983</xref>). Resins are maintained in most conifers as a primary constitutive defense and produced as an induced defense, triggered when a tree is under attack (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Raffa, 1991</xref>). For example, lodgepole pine has been found to respond to attack by the mountain pine beetle and its associated fungi with large increases of total terpenes in the tree (<xref rid="ref-53" ref-type="bibr">Shrimpton, 1973</xref>; <xref rid="ref-40" ref-type="bibr">Raffa &#x00026; Berryman, 1982</xref>, <xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">1983<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref rid="ref-31" ref-type="bibr">Miller, Berryman &#x00026; Ryan, 1986</xref>; <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Boone <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2011</xref>). Similarly, in jack pine, total monoterpene concentrations have been found to be elevated in induced tissue compared to levels in constitutive tissue after attack by jack pine budworm (<xref rid="ref-58" ref-type="bibr">Wallin &#x00026; Raffa, 1999</xref>).</p><p>We compared the constitutive resin chemistry and induced responses to simulated attack between lodgepole pine in southern BC (where outbreaks are common) and northern BC (mainly outside of the historical range of the beetle) with those of jack pine in northern and central Alberta. Our objective was to compare the terpene defenses of lodgepole and jack pine trees to gain insight into the beetles&#x02019; ability to locate suitable hosts, attract conspecifics, and use the resource to successfully reproduce in these new hosts.</p></sec><sec sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Methods and materials</title><sec><title>Constitutive Defenses</title><p>Uninfested jack and lodgepole pine trees, as determined by the absence of pitch tubes and frass, were sampled along a transect from the Alberta/Saskatchewan border to Prince George, BC (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). We attempted to sample trees at even intervals along the transect, but large gaps where suitable pine could not be found due to agricultural or oil extraction activities, or natural breaks in the forest, could not be avoided. In 2006, seven locations were sampled. In 2007, an additional five sites were sampled to increase the total number of samples. A maximum of ten trees, each with a minimum diameter at breast height (d.b.h.; 1.3 m above the ground) of 15 cm, were sampled per location. At some sites, ten trees meeting the minimum size requirements could not be found so fewer than ten trees were sampled (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-1">Fig.&#x000a0;1</xref>). A 10 mm diameter punch (No. 149 Arch Punch 10 mm; C.S. Osborne &#x00026; Co., Harrison, N.J.) was used to remove a disk of bark and phloem at breast height. Each disk was stored in individually labeled envelopes and immediately placed into dry ice where it remained until transferred to a &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C freezer. Samples were kept at &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C until they were shipped, buried in dry ice, to the British Columbia Ministry of Forests and Range Forest Research Laboratory, Victoria, BC, for processing and analysis.</p><fig id="fig-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/fig-1</object-id><label>Figure&#x000a0;1</label><caption><title>Map of sample locations in British Columbia and Alberta.</title></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g001"/></fig><p>Phloem samples were processed using gas chromatographic-flame ionization detection analyses (GC-FID) to identify compounds by matching their retention time with synthetic standards. Samples were processed as described in <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Clark, Carroll &#x00026; Huber (2010)</xref>.</p><p>Based upon the location of the trees sampled in comparison with the sampling locations by <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Pollack &#x00026; Dancik (1985)</xref>, trees at each location were classified either as lodgepole or jack pine. Terpene concentrations (ppm) and the percent resin content of each terpene were analyzed using a two-sample non-parametric Wilcoxon rank sum test to determine if there were differences between the two species (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05) as most of the terpene data could not be transformed to meet the assumption of homoscedasticity based upon a Levene&#x02019;s test. All data were analyzed using R v.2.6.2 (<xref rid="ref-38" ref-type="bibr">R Development Core Team, 2008</xref>). Values below 5 ppm were considered to be zero for analysis.</p></sec><sec><title>Enantiomeric composition</title><p>To assess the enantiomeric composition of three of the predominant monoterpenes (limonene, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene, and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene), samples from three populations &#x02013; two lodgepole pine (BC) and one jack pine (Alberta) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>) &#x02013; taken in the same manner as previously described were analyzed. A Cyclodex-B column (Agilent Technologies) was used with helium as the carrier gas. All data for enantiomeric composition were analyzed using ANOVA with a Tukey&#x02019;s HSD post-hoc test (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05). Data were transformed when necessary to meet assumptions of homoscedasticity based upon a visual examination of the residual plots.</p><table-wrap id="table-1" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/table-1</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;1</label><caption><title>Sampling locations (Kelowna and Chetwynd &#x02013; lodgepole pine, Fort McMurray &#x02013; jack pine), number of trees sampled at each location, and dates of sampling for work on induced defenses.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g004"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"># of trees</th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Coordinates</th><th colspan="3" align="center" rowspan="1">Dates Sampled</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 0</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 2</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Day 14</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Kelowna</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N 49&#x000b0;57.684<sup><italic>&#x02032;</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W 119&#x000b0;42.551<sup><italic>&#x02032;</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">01 Aug 07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">03 Aug 07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15 Aug 07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Chetwynd</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N 49&#x000b0;53.145<sup><italic>&#x02032;</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W 120&#x000b0;25.121<sup><italic>&#x02032;</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">05 Aug 07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">07 Aug 07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">19 Aug 07</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Fort McMurray</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">N 57&#x000b0;21.640<sup><italic>&#x02032;</italic></sup></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">W 111&#x000b0;32.281<sup><italic>&#x02032;</italic></sup>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">09 Aug 07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">11 Aug 07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23 Aug 07</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Induced Defenses</title><p>Uninfested lodgepole pine trees, as determined by an absence of frass and pitch tubes, were selected in a stand near Chetwynd, BC (LP-N), located further north and east than recorded mountain pine beetle infestations prior to 1970 and near the northern edge of the historical range of mountain pine beetle (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik &#x00026; Carroll, 2006</xref>), and near Kelowna, BC (LP-S). In addition, a stand of jack pine &#x02013; a population assumed to be unexposed to mountain pine beetle &#x02013; was selected near Fort McMurray, Alberta (JP) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>). Two initial samples were taken by bark punch (10 mm diameter) from both the east and west side of the trees at breast height. Silicone plugs (Mack&#x02019;s&#x000ae;&#x000a0;Pillow Soft&#x000ae;&#x000a0;silicone earplugs; McKeon Products, Inc., Warren, MI) were used to cover the wound.</p><p>Prior to sampling the tree, the area where the bark punch was to be made was scraped to remove loose debris and then sprayed with ethanol (95%). The tools used in the treatment and sampling process were also sprayed with ethanol before use on each tree to reduce potential contamination. The bark and phloem disks removed from each punch site were saved in individual, labeled envelopes and immediately buried in dry ice in a cooler, where it was kept until it could be transferred to a &#x02212;80&#x000b0;C freezer for longer-term storage prior to analysis.</p><p>Each pine was sampled in the same manner three times in August 2007: (1) the initial sample; (2) two days after initial sampling &#x02013; with the sampling side randomly selected by a coin flip &#x02013; approximately 10 mm above the initial punch wound; and (3) fourteen days after initial sampling on the side of the tree opposite from the two-day sample, again approximately 10 mm above the initial punch. The timing of the second sample at two days post-wounding was used because mass attack is normally completed in one or two days following contact of the first mountain pine beetle with the tree (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik &#x00026; Carroll, 2006</xref>). Therefore, it is the initial response by the tree to wounding during this time that is most likely to have an effect on successful colonization.</p><p>Samples were shipped to the British Columbia Ministry of Forests and Range Forest Research Laboratory, Victoria, BC for processing using gas chromatographic-flame ionization detection analysis exactly as described previously. One of the two initial phloem samples from each tree (from either east or west side of the tree) was selected by coin toss to be processed for comparison of induced levels of monoterpenes; the other sample was used for analysis of enantiomeric composition. Data on nine monoterpenes (3-carene, limonene, linalool, myrcene, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene, pulegone, terpinolene) and the total of all of the 26 terpenes measured were analyzed. Data were analyzed by analysis of variance (ANOVA) to compare monoterpene levels between locations at day 0, 2, and 14. If required, data were transformed [log<sub>10</sub>(<italic>x</italic> + 1)] to meet requirements of homoscedasticity based on a visual examination of the residual plots. If the ANOVA was significant (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05), means were separated by a <italic>post-hoc</italic> Tukey&#x02019;s HSD. Data were also analyzed to compare the rate of change in levels of each terpene between the sampling days using the Kruskal-Wallis non-parametric test followed by two sample non-parametric Wilcoxon rank sum test as data could not be transformed to meet requirements of homoscedasticity based on a visual examination of the residual plots.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>Constitutive Defenses</title><p>Based upon the location of collection, we sampled 50 lodgepole pine trees and 61 jack pine trees. There was no significant difference in tree diameter between the two species in the sample population (<italic>P</italic> &#x0003e; 0.05). <xref rid="ref-35" ref-type="bibr">Pollack &#x00026; Dancik (1985)</xref> found that <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene were the most important variables for differentiating between lodgepole pine and jack pine and the putative hybrid populations in Alberta. With only one exception (which was analyzed as a jack pine), all of the trees sampled at sites considered to be occupied by jack pine had a higher percentage of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene compared with <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene; and all of the trees from sampling locations occupied by lodgepole pine had a higher percentage of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene compared with <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene.</p><p>There were significant differences (Wilcoxon rank sum test, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05) between the constitutive concentrations (ppm) in lodgepole and jack pine for all but three of the 26 monoterpenes considered (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Of the monoterpenes that differed, lodgepole pine had higher levels of 20 of the 23 terpenes with the exceptions of: linalool, pulegone, and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene. Total terpenes were also higher in lodgepole pine than in jack pine. Lodgepole and jack pine also differed significantly in the percentage composition of all but five terpenes in the phloem resin (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-3">Table&#x000a0;3</xref>). In addition, lodgepole pine had a higher percent composition of all of the terpenes tested that differed between species, except for bornyl acetate (0.37% vs. 1.80%), <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-caryophyllene (0.11% vs. 0.29%), pulegone (0.24% vs. 4.16%), and <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene (7.09% vs. 58.42%).</p><table-wrap id="table-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/table-2</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;2</label><caption><title>Mean content of terpenes (PPM) (&#x000b1;1 SE) of lodgepole and jack pine trees.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g005"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-2fna">a</xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Mean content (ppm)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lodgepole pine</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jack pine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borneol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">14.67&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.64</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bornyl acetate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.004</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">45.95&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;12.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.52&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.41</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">88.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;4.51</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.041</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.69&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.85</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-Carene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1738.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;321.80</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">226.99&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;44.95</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Caryophyllene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;3.32</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.24</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Copaene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">13.70&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.68</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.78</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Cubebene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.273</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.46</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.79&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.63</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>p</italic>-Cymene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">32.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.11</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.90&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Humulene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">42.35&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;7.30</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.42</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">848.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;164.35</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">203.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;48.89</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.220</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">64.73&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;9.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">117.74&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;16.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myrcene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">435.45&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;45.48</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;15.71</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ocimene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">31.75&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.21</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Phellandrene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">175.77&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.93</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.62&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.38</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Phellandrene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">9096.72&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;960.59</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">157.21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;40.39</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Pinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">949.81&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;132.72</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2518.14&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;328.27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Pinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">921.46&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;127.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">283.98&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;43.68</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulegone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.039</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">30.21&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.81</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">107.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;22.81</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sabinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">141.94&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;17.74</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.12&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.17</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Terpinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15.39&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.95</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-Terpinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">23.81&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;5.42</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpineol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">53.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;8.55</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">16.50&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;6.59</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinolene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">352.79&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;48.44</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">47.07&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;13.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Thujone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.122</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.84</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.85&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.20</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Total</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">15144.92&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1463.47</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3881.44&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;395.26</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-2fna"><label>a</label><p>Differences between species as determined by a Wilcoxon rank sum test (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05, significant differences in bold).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="table-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/table-3</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;3</label><caption><title>Mean relative content of terpenes (%) (&#x000b1;1 SE) of lodgepole and jack pine.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g006"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic>-value<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-3fna">a</xref></th><th colspan="2" align="center" rowspan="1">Mean relative content (% of total monoterpenes)</th></tr><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Lodgepole pine</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Jack pine</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Borneol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.016</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Bornyl acetate</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.80&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.26</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.874</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.64&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.60&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.08</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Camphor</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.120</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.06&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3-Carene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">10.56&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.33</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">8.68&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.48</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Caryophyllene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.03</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.29&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Copaene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Cubebene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.307</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.01&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.04&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">p-Cymene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.07&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.04</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Humulene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Limonene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.004</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.26&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.85</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.77&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Linalool</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.090</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.87&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.38</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5.93&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.37</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Myrcene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold>&#x000a0;=&#x000a0;<bold>0.005</bold></td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.98&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">2.16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.28</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Ocimene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.18&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.05</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Phellandrene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.13&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.07</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Phellandrene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.25&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.92</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.99</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Pinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">7.09&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.91</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">58.42&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;2.32</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-Pinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.687</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.74&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.77</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">6.47&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.72</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Pulegone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.24&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">4.16&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.23</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Sabinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.91&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.09</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.19&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Terpinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.08&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b3;</italic>-Terpinene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.11&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.00&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.00</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpineol</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.37&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.06</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.30&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.12</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Terpinolene</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">
<bold><italic>P</italic>&#x000a0;&#x0003c;&#x000a0;0.001</bold>
</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">3.29&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;1.02</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">1.32&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.35</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Thujone</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>P</italic> = 0.128</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.02&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.01</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0.20&#x000a0;&#x000b1;&#x000a0;0.14</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-3fna"><label>a</label><p>Differences between species as determined by a two-sample Wilcoxon test (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05, significant differences in bold).</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Enantiomeric composition</title><p>There were significant differences between lodgepole and jack pine in the percent enantiomeric composition of limonene, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene, and <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>). Both populations of lodgepole pine had significantly (<italic>F</italic> = 20.75; <italic>df</italic> = 2,60; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) higher percentage of (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene than the population of jack pine [and corresponding lower percentage of (+)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene (<italic>F</italic> = 20.57; <italic>df</italic> = 2,60; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001)] (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>). Both populations of lodgepole pine and the jack pine population had higher percentages of the (&#x02013;)-enantiomer of limonene than the (+)-enantiomer. The southern BC population of lodgepole pine near Kelowna had a higher percentage of (+)-limonene than the jack pine population (<italic>F</italic> = 4.87; <italic>df</italic> = 2,50; <italic>P</italic> = 0.01), which conversely had higher percentage of (&#x02013;)-limonene (<italic>F</italic> = 4.23; <italic>df</italic> = 2,50; <italic>P</italic> = 0.02). All three populations of the two species contained exclusively (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>).</p><table-wrap id="table-4" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/table-4</object-id><label>Table&#x000a0;4</label><caption><title>Mean percentages of chiral monoterpenes (&#x000b1;1 SE) from lodgepole pine trees in northern and southern locations (LP-N and LP-S respectively) and jack pine trees (JP)<xref ref-type="table-fn" rid="table-4fna">a</xref>.</title></caption><alternatives><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g007"/><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><colgroup span="1"><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/><col span="1"/></colgroup><thead><tr><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">Location</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(&#x02212;)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(+)-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(&#x02212;)-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(R)-(+)-limonene</th><th rowspan="1" colspan="1">(S)-(&#x02212;)-limonene</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LP-S</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">37 (&#x000b1;4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">63 (&#x000b1;4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">29 (&#x000b1;5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">71 (&#x000b1;5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 28</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 27</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 27</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">LP-N</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (&#x000b1;6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">50 (&#x000b1;6)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">17 (&#x000b1;5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">83 (&#x000b1;5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 17</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 16</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 16</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">JP</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">78 (&#x000b1;4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">22 (&#x000b1;4)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">0</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">100</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">5 (&#x000b1;5)</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1">95 (&#x000b1;5)</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"/><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 18</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 14</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 10</td><td rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>n</italic> = 10</td></tr></tbody></table></alternatives><table-wrap-foot><fn id="table-4fna"><label>a</label><p>Number of samples for each compound and location varied due to sample failures.</p></fn></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></sec><sec><title>Induced Defenses</title><p>There were significant differences between the terpene levels sampled at day 0, 2, and 14, and between the locations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). There were also significant differences in the rate of change between locations for five of the terpenes: limonene, myrcene, <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene, <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene, pulegone (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>).</p><fig id="fig-2" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/fig-2</object-id><label>Figure&#x000a0;2</label><caption><title>Mean levels of terpenes at day 0 (initial sample), day 2, and day 14 in two populations of lodgepole pine (LP-S &#x02013; southern lodgepole pine, Kelowna; LP-N &#x02013; northern lodgepole pine, Chetwynd) and one population of jack pine (JP &#x02013; Fort McMurray) in response to wounding.</title><p>Different lower case letters within each terpene indicate significant differences (<italic>&#x003b1;</italic> = 0.05) between locations for that terpene.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g002"/></fig><fig id="fig-3" orientation="portrait" position="float"><object-id pub-id-type="doi">10.7717/peerj.240/fig-3</object-id><label>Figure&#x000a0;3</label><caption><title>Change in terpene levels at day 0, day 2, and day 14 in two populations of lodgepole pine (LP-S &#x02013; southern lodgepole pine, Kelowna; LP-N &#x02013; northern lodgepole pine, Chetwynd) and one population of jack pine (JP &#x02013; Fort McMurray) in response to wounding.</title><p>Asterisks indicate significant differences in the rate of change of the monoterpene levels.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="peerj-02-240-g003"/></fig><p>The southern BC lodgepole pine had a higher rate of increase in levels of limonene (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> = 14.99; <italic>df</italic> = 2; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) between day 0 and 2 compared to the rates of increase in northern BC lodgepole pine and jack pine. The only difference (<italic>F</italic> = 4.25; <italic>df</italic> = 2, 28; <italic>P</italic> = 0.02) in limonene levels between locations was in the initial sample between the northern BC lodgepole pine and the jack pine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>The northern BC lodgepole pine also had a lower rate of increase of myrcene levels (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> = 10.92; <italic>df</italic> = 2; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) compared to the southern BC lodgepole pine, but neither lodgepole pine population differed from the jack pine between day 0 and 2. Only the initial sample had myrcene levels that were higher (<italic>F</italic> = 4.16; <italic>df</italic> = 2, 28; <italic>P</italic> = 0.03) in the northern BC lodgepole pine trees compared to the jack pine trees (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>The rate of increase of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene levels in the southern BC lodgepole pine trees was higher (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> = 10.35; <italic>df</italic> = 2; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) than in the northern BC lodgepole pine trees, while the rate of increase of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene levels in jack pine trees was not different from either population of lodgepole pine between day 0 and 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>). However, the absolute levels of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene were higher (<italic>F</italic> = 20.8; <italic>df</italic> = 2, 28; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <italic>F</italic> = 13.68; <italic>df</italic> = 2, 28; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001; <italic>F</italic> = 45.46; <italic>df</italic> = 2, 28; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) in jack pine on all three sample dates compared to both lodgepole pine populations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The rates of increase in <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene levels were higher (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> = 12.90; <italic>df</italic> = 2; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.01) in jack pine and the southern BC lodgepole pine compared to the northern BC lodgepole pine from day 0 to 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>).</p><p>The rate of increase in pulegone levels was higher (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> = 16.93; <italic>df</italic> = 2; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) in the northern BC lodgepole pine compared to the jack pine and the level of pulegone was higher in the northern BC lodgepole pine compared with the other two sites (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). The level of pulegone in the southern BC lodgepole pine showed a significant rate of decrease compared with both other populations between day 0 and 2 (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) and the level was lower (<italic>F</italic> = 19.32; <italic>df</italic> = 2,2 8; <italic>P</italic> &#x0003c; 0.001) than in northern BC lodgepole pine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>). Between day 2 and 14, jack pine showed a higher (<italic>&#x003c7;</italic><sup>2</sup> = 6.37; <italic>df</italic> = 2; <italic>P</italic> = 0.04) rate of increase in pulegone compared to the southern BC lodgepole pine (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-3">Fig.&#x000a0;3</xref>) although the levels at day 14 were not different between any of the locations (<xref ref-type="fig" rid="fig-2">Fig.&#x000a0;2</xref>).</p><p>There was no difference between locations in rate of change in the total phloem terpene levels, although the initial sample did show higher (<italic>F</italic> = 3.75; <italic>df</italic> = 2, 28; <italic>P</italic> = 0.04) levels of total terpenes in northern BC lodgepole pine compared to the jack pine. However, the levels of total terpenes were not different at day 2 or 14.</p></sec></sec><sec sec-type="discussion"><title>Discussion</title><p>Comparison of bark resin terpene compositions of lodgepole and jack pine sampled in our study showed that lodgepole pine have higher constitutive levels of most terpenes than does jack pine, including 3-carene, myrcene, and terpinolene (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-2">Table&#x000a0;2</xref>). Many of these terpenes are important semiochemicals for the mountain pine beetle. For example, trap catches of mountain pine beetle in pheromone baited traps were enhanced by 3-carene released at a high rate (<xref rid="ref-29" ref-type="bibr">Miller &#x00026; Borden, 2000</xref>). Myrcene and terpinolene together were found to be an even more effective synergist than myrcene alone in pheromone baited traps (<xref rid="ref-3" ref-type="bibr">Borden, Pureswaran &#x00026; Lafontaine, 2008</xref>), while myrcene was the most effective synergist in a baited tree study (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Borden <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1983</xref>). This suggests that lodgepole pine may be more apparent than jack pine to foraging mountain pine beetles. On the other hand we found lower concentrations of the terpenes that are generally considered to be toxic &#x02013; e.g., the ovicidal limonene and 3-carene (<xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Raffa &#x00026; Berryman, 1983<italic>b</italic></xref>) &#x02013; in jack pine compared to lodgepole pine. As &#x0223c;47% of the jack pine in our study had undetectable levels of 3-carene, this host species is potentially more suitable than lodgepole pine for mountain pine beetle reproduction, although <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2013)</xref> found that jack pine released higher levels of 3-carene than lodgepole pine after beetle introduction. There is likely to be regional variation in the terpene composition of jack pine which could partially explain this difference between our observations and <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2013)</xref> just as has been observed in lodgepole pine (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Forrest, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Clark, Carroll &#x00026; Huber, 2010</xref>). <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2013)</xref> also used cut bolts rather than living trees which could further explain the discrepancies.</p><p>When considering our results it is important to remember that there is considerable regional variation in monoterpene composition among lodgepole pine populations (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Forrest, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="ref-57" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Clark, Carroll &#x00026; Huber, 2010</xref>), and given the extensive historic range of the mountain pine beetle, it appears to have evolved to deal with this variation. Our sampling method does not allow us to account for any intraspecific variation in terpene levels as we are only separating by tree species. There is variation in terpene composition within the same tree species (<xref rid="ref-15" ref-type="bibr">Forrest, 1980</xref>; <xref rid="ref-6" ref-type="bibr">Clark, Carroll &#x00026; Huber, 2010</xref>) but we focused on interspecific variation between the two pine species in this study.</p><p>The complex interactions between the insect and resin <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene levels are very important in light of the fact that levels of this monoterpene in jack pine are significantly higher than in lodgepole pine (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>), thereby potentially affecting the mountain pine beetle&#x02019;s behavior and success in colonization of jack pine. <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Pinene (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-1">Table&#x000a0;1</xref>) is metabolized by female mountain pine beetle to produce <italic>trans</italic>-verbenol, the primary component of the mountain pine beetle aggregation pheromone (<xref rid="ref-9" ref-type="bibr">Conn <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1984</xref>), which is essential to successful mass attack (<xref rid="ref-48" ref-type="bibr">Rudinsky, 1962</xref>). <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2013)</xref> showed that the higher emissions of <italic>trans</italic>-verbenol by female mountain pine beetle on jack pine are associated with higher <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene levels in that host. <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-Pinene is also auto-oxidized to verbenone, an anti-aggregation pheromone of the mountain pine beetle (<xref rid="ref-20" ref-type="bibr">Hunt <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1989</xref>), and <xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2013)</xref> found equal amounts of verbenone emitted from lodgepole and jack pine bolts. Incorporating the host defenses into the chemical signals that regulate aggregation helps optimize the beetles&#x02019; success (<xref rid="ref-41" ref-type="bibr">Raffa &#x00026; Berryman, 1983<italic>a</italic></xref>).</p><p>The enantiomeric composition of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene can be important to some bark beetles (<xref rid="ref-47" ref-type="bibr">Renwick, Hughes &#x00026; Krull, 1976</xref>). Even though the overall levels of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene were higher in the jack pine, there was a lower proportion of (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene compared with both populations of lodgepole pine (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>). Volatiles collected from bolts of lodgepole pine from southern BC showed 67.7% and 100% of (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>- and (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene respectively (<xref rid="ref-37" ref-type="bibr">Pureswaran, Gries &#x00026; Borden, 2004</xref>), which corresponds well with our findings for the southern BC lodgepole pine bark and phloem (62.6% and 100% respectively) (<xref ref-type="table" rid="table-4">Table&#x000a0;4</xref>). There is a correlation between the enantiomeric composition of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene the insects were exposed to and the ratio of pheromone enantiomers produced by several species of <italic>Ips</italic> (<xref rid="ref-52" ref-type="bibr">Seybold, 1993</xref>). For example, a higher percentage of (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene in the host spruce [<italic>Picea abies</italic> (L.) H. Karst.] was found to correlate with a higher percentage of <italic>cis</italic>-verbenol produced by <italic>Ips typographus</italic> (<xref rid="ref-25" ref-type="bibr">Lindstr&#x000f6;m <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1989</xref>). We found significantly higher ratios of (&#x02013;)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene in jack pine compared to lodgpole pine which corresponds to findings by (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2013</xref>). Electroantennogram studies have shown that the mountain pine beetle can differentiate between enantiomers of verbenol and verbenone (<xref rid="ref-59" ref-type="bibr">Whitehead <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1989</xref>), although electrophysiological responses do not necessarily translate into specific behaviors and <italic>cis</italic>-verbenol was not as attractive as <italic>trans</italic>-verbenol to mountain pine beetles when combined with myrcene and <italic>exo</italic>-brevicomin (<xref rid="ref-28" ref-type="bibr">Miller &#x00026; Lafontaine, 1991</xref>). However (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) did not find the production of (&#x02212;)-<italic>trans</italic>-verbenol to be limited by the enantiomeric composition of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene in the jack pine.</p><p>There were also differences in the rate of change in the levels of some terpenes after wounding, and if induced defensive responses are adequate and rapid beetles will sometimes abandon their colonization attempts (<xref rid="ref-39" ref-type="bibr">Raffa, 1991</xref>). Uninfested lodgepole pine trees near Kelowna, BC were hard to find due to the high level of beetle activity in that area. While the sampled trees were uninfested, likely due to chance or geographic distance from infested stands, it is also possible that they may have possessed some characteristic that made them relatively unsuitable for colonization. Furthermore, in an attempt to standardize the levels of observed induced defenses these trees were only mechanically wounded as there is large variability between the beetles and the microorganisms they carry (<xref rid="ref-24" ref-type="bibr">Lee, Kim &#x00026; Breuil, 2006</xref>). Our results could therefore be different than the induced response that would be caused by beetle attack.</p><p> Limonene, a terpene toxic to bark beetles (<xref rid="ref-56" ref-type="bibr">Smith, 1965</xref>; <xref rid="ref-42" ref-type="bibr">Raffa &#x00026; Berryman, 1983<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref rid="ref-7" ref-type="bibr">Cook &#x00026; Hain, 1988</xref>), was found to have a higher rate of increase between day 0 and day 2 in the southern population of lodgepole pine compared with the northern lodgepole pine population. This stronger response by the southern lodgepole pine after wounding compared with the northern pine trees supports the hypothesis that tree populations with more prior exposure to mountain pine beetle outbreaks maintain a more effective response to attack &#x02013; i.e., rapid increase in levels of a toxic terpene &#x02013; and hence are also less suitable for reproduction (<xref rid="ref-10" ref-type="bibr">Cudmore <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). The rate of increase of myrcene as well as the levels and rate of increase of <italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-pinene, did not differ between southern lodgepole pine and jack pine, which indicates that the beetle would experience a similar rate of response in this new host species for these terpenes.</p><p>The outcome of the interaction of the mountain pine beetle with phloem resin constituents in a novel host such as jack pine could also be dependent on beetle population levels. <xref rid="ref-2" ref-type="bibr">Boone <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2011)</xref> found that the resin defenses in lodgepole pine play an important role in protecting trees from mountain pine beetle attack at low population levels but not at high populations. Our results suggest that due to the generally lower levels of terpene-based defenses in jack pine relative to lodgepole pine, incipient-epidemic populations of mountain pine beetles may have a greater success in colonizing jack pine. Furthermore, beetles may be able to exploit the relatively higher levels of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene in jack pine to produce aggregation pheromones that further increase colonization success (<xref rid="ref-13" ref-type="bibr">Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2013</xref>) and allow populations to increase rapidly.<xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2012)</xref> predicted the distribution of lodgepole and jack pine using genetic information. Their work indicates that the range of pure jack pine begins further east than the historical range given by <xref rid="ref-26" ref-type="bibr">Little (1971)</xref>. Based on <xref rid="ref-11" ref-type="bibr">Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2012)</xref> we may have sampled trees that we have identified as jack pine in this study that are not necessarily considered pure. However, we have shown that the mountain pine beetle is moving into an area that has significant differences in the absolute and relative terpene levels regardless of the hybrid-genetic status of the hosts that they encounter. Most studies on the behavioral and toxic effects of terpenes on mountain pine beetle are conducted using lodgepole or ponderosa pine (<italic>Pinus ponderosa</italic> Dougl. ex Laws.) as model host species. The minimum levels of resin terpenes necessary to provide an adequate attractant plume from an attacked bole are not known. Therefore there could be an additive effect between a number of host kairomones (<xref rid="ref-4" ref-type="bibr">Borden <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1983</xref>; <xref rid="ref-8" ref-type="bibr">Conn <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 1983</xref>), which in combination with the higher levels of total terpenes present in lodgepole pine may suggest that lodgepole pine are easier for mountain pine beetle to locate than jack pine. The terpene composition may also make the lodgepole pine easier to identify as a suitable host. For example, despite what appears to be a preferable chemical environment in a novel host, whitebark pine (<italic>Pinus albicaulis</italic>), compared to lodgepole pine, <xref rid="ref-44" ref-type="bibr">Raffa, Powell &#x00026; Townsend (2013)</xref> found that mountain pine beetle did not show preference for whitebark pine in mixed stands, indicating that mountain pine beetle may be better at recognizing its traditional host in such situations. However, the combination of lower levels of some terpenes generally considered toxic to insects, and an increased concentration of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene, which is a precursor of both the primary aggregation and antiaggregation pheromones, may make jack pine easier to attack and colonize. This implies a substantial potential for ongoing and increased success for the mountain pine beetle in this new geographic range and host, particularly if climatic suitability increases as predicted (<xref rid="ref-49" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik &#x00026; Carroll, 2006</xref>; <xref rid="ref-51" ref-type="bibr">Safranyik <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic>, 2010</xref>). As the beetle spreads further into pure jack pine forests, it will be critical to conduct further research into the behavior and reproductive success of mountain pine beetle in this new host.</p></sec></body><back><ack><p>Analytical chemistry analyses on phloem samples were performed by Mr. Clive Dawson of the British Columbia Ministry of Forests, Lands and Natural Resources Operations.</p></ack><sec sec-type="additional-information"><title>Additional Information and Declarations</title><fn-group content-type="competing-interests"><title>Competing Interests</title><fn id="conflict-1" fn-type="conflict"><p>Dr. Huber is an Academic Editor for PeerJ.</p></fn></fn-group><fn-group content-type="author-contributions"><title>Author Contributions</title><fn id="contribution-1" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-1">Erin L. Clark</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, analyzed the data, wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-2" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-2">Caitlin Pitt</xref> performed the experiments.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-3" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-3">Allan L. Carroll</xref> and <xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-4">B. Staffan Lindgren</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, wrote the paper.</p></fn><fn id="contribution-4" fn-type="con"><p><xref ref-type="contrib" rid="author-5">Dezene Huber</xref> conceived and designed the experiments, wrote the manuscript, and contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools.</p></fn></fn-group></sec><ref-list content-type="authoryear"><title>References</title><ref id="ref-1"><label>Birgersson &#x00026; Leufv&#x000e9;n (1988)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Birgersson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Leufv&#x000e9;n</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The influence of host tree response to <italic>Ips typographus</italic> and fungal attack on production of semiochemicals</article-title><source>Insect Biochemistry</source><year>1988</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>761</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0020-1790(88)90098-4</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-2"><label>Boone <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Boone</surname><given-names>CK</given-names></name><name><surname>Aukema</surname><given-names>BH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Efficacy of tree defense physiology varies with bark beetle population density: a basis for positive feedback in eruptive species</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</source><year>2011</year><volume>41</volume><fpage>1174</fpage><lpage>1188</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/x11-041</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-3"><label>Borden, Pureswaran &#x00026; Lafontaine (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Pureswaran</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Synergistic blends of monoterpenes for aggregation pheromones of the mountain pine beetle (Coleoptera: Curculionidae)</article-title><source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source><year>2008</year><volume>101</volume><fpage>1266</fpage><lpage>1275</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0022-0493(2008)101[1266:SBOMFA]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18767736</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-4"><label>Borden <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Conn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Friskie</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Chong</surname><given-names>LJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>HDJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Oehlschlager</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Semiochemicals for the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae), in British Columbia: Baited-tree studies</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</source><year>1983</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>325</fpage><lpage>333</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/x83-046</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-5"><label>Cerezke (1995)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cerezke</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Egg gallery, brood production, and adult characteristics of mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> Hopkins (Coleoptera: Scolytidae), in three pine hosts</article-title><source>The Canadian Entomologist</source><year>1995</year><volume>127</volume><fpage>955</fpage><lpage>964</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/Ent127955-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-6"><label>Clark, Carroll &#x00026; Huber (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Clark</surname><given-names>EL</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Huber</surname><given-names>DPW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differences in the constitutive terpene profile of lodgepole pine across a geographical range in British Columbia, and correlation with historical attack by mountain pine beetle</article-title><source>The Canadian Entomologist</source><year>2010</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>17</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/n10-022</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-7"><label>Cook &#x00026; Hain (1988)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cook</surname><given-names>SP</given-names></name><name><surname>Hain</surname><given-names>FP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of host monoterpenes to Dendroctonus frontalis and <italic>Ips</italic> calligraphus (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Journal of Entomological Science</source><year>1988</year><volume>23</volume><fpage>287</fpage><lpage>292</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-8"><label>Conn <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>BE</given-names></name><name><surname>Friskie</surname><given-names>LM</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>HD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Oehlschlager</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Semiochemicals for the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae) in British Columbia: Field trapping studies</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</source><year>1983</year><volume>13</volume><fpage>320</fpage><lpage>324</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/x83-045</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-9"><label>Conn <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1984)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Conn</surname><given-names>JE</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DWA</given-names></name><name><surname>Holman</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitney</surname><given-names>HS</given-names></name><name><surname>Spanier</surname><given-names>OJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Pierce</surname><given-names>HD</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name><name><surname>Oehlschlager</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Pheromone production by axenically reared <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> and <italic>Ips paraconfusus</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>1984</year><volume>10</volume><fpage>281</fpage><lpage>290</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00987856</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24318497</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-10"><label>Cudmore <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cudmore</surname><given-names>TJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Bj&#x000f6;rklund</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Climate change and range expansion of an aggressive bark beetle: evidence of higher reproductive success in na&#x000ef;ve host tree populations</article-title><source>Journal of Applied Ecology</source><year>2010</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1036</fpage><lpage>1043</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2664.2010.01848.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-11"><label>Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2012)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cullingham</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>James</surname><given-names>PMA</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>JEK</given-names></name><name><surname>Coltman</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Characterizing the physical and genetic structure of the lodgepole pine &#x000d7; jack pine hybrid zone: mosaic structure and differential introgression</article-title><source>Evolutionary Applications</source><year>2012</year><volume>5</volume><fpage>879</fpage><lpage>891</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1752-4571.2012.00266.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">23346232</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-12"><label>Cullingham <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2011)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cullingham</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>JEK</given-names></name><name><surname>Dang</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Coltman</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mountain pine beetle host-range expansion threatens the boreal forest</article-title><source>Molecular Ecology</source><year>2011</year><volume>20</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>15</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-294X.2011.05086.x</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-13"><label>Erbilgin <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Erbilgin</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name><name><surname>Whitehouse</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Shan</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Najar</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Evenden</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Chemical similarity between historical and novel host plants promotes range and host expansion of the mountain pine beetle in a na&#x000ef;ve host ecosystem</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><issue>3</issue><year>2013</year><volume>201</volume><fpage>940</fpage><lpage>950</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/nph.12573</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24400902</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-14"><label>Eyles <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Eyles</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Riedle</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Cipollini</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Schwartz</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Chan</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Herms</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bonello</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Comparative phloem chemistry of Manchurian (<italic>Fraxinus mandshurica</italic>) and two North American ash species (<italic>Fraxinus americana</italic> and <italic>Fraxinus pennsylvanica</italic>)</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>2007</year><volume>33</volume><fpage>1430</fpage><lpage>1448</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-007-9312-3</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17522965</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-15"><label>Forrest (1980)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Forrest</surname><given-names>GI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Geographic variation in the monoterpenes of <italic>Pinus contorta</italic> oleoresin</article-title><source>Biochemical Systematics and Ecology</source><year>1980</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>343</fpage><lpage>359</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0305-1978(80)90037-X</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-16"><label>Furniss &#x00026; Schenk (1969)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Furniss</surname><given-names>MM</given-names></name><name><surname>Schenk</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Sustained natural infestation by the mountain pine beetle in seven new <italic>Pinus</italic> and <italic>Picea</italic> hosts</article-title><source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source><year>1969</year><volume>62</volume><fpage>518</fpage><lpage>519</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-17"><label>Gershenzon &#x00026; Croteau (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gershenzon</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Croteau</surname><given-names>RB</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>GA</given-names></name><name><surname>Berembaum</surname><given-names>MR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Terpenoids</article-title><source>Herbivores: Their interactions with secondary plant metabolites</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>CRC Press</publisher-name><fpage>165</fpage><lpage>219</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-18"><label>Ghandi &#x00026; Herms (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ghandi</surname><given-names>KJK</given-names></name><name><surname>Herms</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Direct and indirect effects of alien insect herbivores on ecological processes and interactions in forest of eastern North America</article-title><source>Biological Invasions</source><year>2010</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>389</fpage><lpage>405</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10530-009-9627-9</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-19"><label>Haack <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Haack</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name><name><surname>Jendek</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Liu</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Marchant</surname><given-names>KR</given-names></name><name><surname>Petrice</surname><given-names>TR</given-names></name><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>Ye</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The emerald ash borer: A new exotic pest in North America</article-title><source>Newsletter of the Michigan Entomological Society</source><year>2002</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>1</fpage><lpage>5</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-20"><label>Hunt <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1989)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Hunt</surname><given-names>DWA</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name><name><surname>Lindgren</surname><given-names>BS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gries</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of autoxidation of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene in the production of pheromones of <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Forest Research</source><year>1989</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1275</fpage><lpage>1282</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/x89-194</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-21"><label>Keane &#x00026; Crawley (2002)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keane</surname><given-names>RM</given-names></name><name><surname>Crawley</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Exotic plant invasions and the enemy release hypothesis</article-title><source>Trends in Ecology &#x00026; Evolution</source><year>2002</year><volume>117</volume><fpage>164</fpage><lpage>170</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(02)02499-0</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-22"><label>Keeling &#x00026; Bohlmann (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Keeling</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name><name><surname>Bohlmann</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Genes, enzymes and chemicals of terpenoid diversity in the constitutive and induced defense of conifers against insects and pathogens</article-title><source>New Phytologist</source><year>2006</year><volume>170</volume><fpage>657</fpage><lpage>675</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2006.01716.x</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16684230</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-23"><label>Langor, Rice &#x00026; Williams (2007)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Langor</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rice</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Williams</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Mountain pine beetle invasion of boreal forests</article-title><source>Canadian Silviculture.</source><issue>1</issue><year>2007</year><volume>2007</volume><fpage>5</fpage><lpage>7</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-24"><label>Lee, Kim &#x00026; Breuil (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lee</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Kim</surname><given-names>J-J</given-names></name><name><surname>Breuil</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Diversity of fungi associated with the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> and infested lodgepole pines in British Columbia</article-title><source>Fungal Diversity</source><year>2006</year><volume>22</volume><fpage>91</fpage><lpage>105</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-25"><label>Lindstr&#x000f6;m <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1989)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lindstr&#x000f6;m</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Norin</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Birgersson</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Schlyter</surname><given-names>F</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Variation of enantiomeric composition of <italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene in Norway spruce, <italic>Picea abies</italic>, and its influence on production of verbenol isomers by <italic>Ips typographus</italic> in the field</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>1989</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>541</fpage><lpage>548</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01014699</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24271797</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-26"><label>Little (1971)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Little</surname><given-names>EL</given-names><suffix>Jr</suffix></name></person-group><source>Atlas of United States trees. Volume 1: conifers and important hardwoods. 1146</source><year>1971</year><publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc><publisher-name>US Department of Agriculture Miscellaneous Publication</publisher-name></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-27"><label>Logan &#x00026; Powell (2001)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Logan</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ghost forests, global warming, and the mountain pine beetle (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>American Entomologist</source><year>2001</year><volume>47</volume><fpage>160</fpage><lpage>172</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-28"><label>Miller &#x00026; Lafontaine (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Lafontaine</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>cis</italic>-Verbenol: An aggregation pheromone for the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> Hopkins (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Journal of the Entomological Society of British Columbia</source><year>1991</year><volume>88</volume><fpage>34</fpage><lpage>38</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-29"><label>Miller &#x00026; Borden (2000)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Dose-dependent and species-specific response of pine bark beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytidae) to monoterpenes in association with pheromones</article-title><source>The Canadian Entomologist</source><year>2000</year><volume>132</volume><fpage>183</fpage><lpage>195</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/Ent132183-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-30"><label>Miller &#x00026; Borden (1990)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title><italic>&#x003b2;</italic>-phellandrene: Kairomone for pine engraver, <italic>Ips pini</italic> (Say) (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>1990</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>2519</fpage><lpage>2531</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01017475</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24264217</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-31"><label>Miller, Berryman &#x00026; Ryan (1986)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name><name><surname>Berryman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Ryan</surname><given-names>CA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biotic elicitors of defense reactions in lodgepole pine</article-title><source>Phytochemistry</source><year>1986</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>611</fpage><lpage>612</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0031-9422(86)88008-6</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-32"><label>Moeck &#x00026; Simmons (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moeck</surname><given-names>HA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simmons</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Primary attraction of mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> Hopk. (Coleoptera: Scolytidae), to bolts of lodgepole pine</article-title><source>The Canadian Entomologist</source><year>1991</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>299</fpage><lpage>304</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/Ent123299-2</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-33"><label>Moss (1949)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Moss</surname><given-names>EH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Natural pine hybrids in Alberta</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Research</source><issue>5</issue><year>1949</year><volume>27c</volume><fpage>218</fpage><lpage>229</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/cjr49c-018</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-34"><label>Poland &#x00026; McCullough (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Poland</surname><given-names>TM</given-names></name><name><surname>McCullough</surname><given-names>DG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Emerald ash borer: Invasion of the urban forest and the treat to North America&#x02019;s ash resource</article-title><source>Journal of Forestry</source><year>2006</year><volume>104</volume><fpage>118</fpage><lpage>124</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-35"><label>Pollack &#x00026; Dancik (1985)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pollack</surname><given-names>JC</given-names></name><name><surname>Dancik</surname><given-names>BP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoterpene and morphological variation and hybridization of <italic>Pinus contorta</italic> and <italic>P. banksiana</italic> in Alberta</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source><year>1985</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>201</fpage><lpage>210</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b85-023</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-36"><label>Pureswaran &#x00026; Borden (2003)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pureswaran</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Test of semiochemical mediated host specificity in four species of tree killing bark beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Environmental Entomology</source><year>2003</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>969</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0046-225X-32.5.963</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-37"><label>Pureswaran, Gries &#x00026; Borden (2004)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Pureswaran</surname><given-names>DS</given-names></name><name><surname>Gries</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Borden</surname><given-names>JH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Quantitative variation in monoterpenes in four species of conifers</article-title><source>Biochemical Systematics and Ecology</source><year>2004</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1109</fpage><lpage>1136</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bse.2004.04.006</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-38"><label>R Development Core Team (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="other"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>R Development Core Team</surname><given-names/></name></person-group><year>2008</year><comment>R: A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria. <italic>Available at:</italic>&#x000a0;<uri xlink:href="http://www.R-project.org">http://www.R-project.org</uri></comment></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-39"><label>Raffa (1991)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Tallamy</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Raupp</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Induced defensive reactions in conifer-bark beetle systems</article-title><source>Phytochemical induction by herbivores</source><year>1991</year><publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc><publisher-name>John Wiley and Sons, Inc</publisher-name><fpage>245</fpage><lpage>276</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-40"><label>Raffa &#x00026; Berryman (1982)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berryman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological differences between lodgepole pines resistant and susceptible to the mountain pine beetle and associated microorganisms</article-title><source>Environmental Entomology</source><year>1982</year><volume>11</volume><fpage>486</fpage><lpage>492</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-41"><label>Raffa &#x00026; Berryman (1983a)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berryman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of host plant resistance in the colonization behavior and ecology of bark beetles (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Ecological Monographs</source><year>1983a</year><volume>53</volume><fpage>27</fpage><lpage>49</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1942586</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-42"><label>Raffa &#x00026; Berryman (1983b)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berryman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Physiological aspects of lodgepole pine wound responses to a fungal symbiont of the mountain pine beetle, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>The Canadian Entomologist</source><year>1983b</year><volume>115</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>734</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/Ent115723-7</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-43"><label>Raffa &#x00026; Berryman (1987)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berryman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interacting selective pressures in conifer-bark beetle systems: A basis for reciprocal adaptations?</article-title><source>American Naturalist of the United States of America</source><year>1987</year><volume>129</volume><fpage>234</fpage><lpage>262</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-44"><label>Raffa, Powell &#x00026; Townsend (2013)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Powell</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Townsend</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Temperature-driven range expansion of an irruptive insect heightened by weakly coevolved plant defenses</article-title><source>Proceedings of National Academy of Sciences USA</source><year>2013</year><volume>110</volume><fpage>2193</fpage><lpage>2198</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.1216666110</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-45"><label>Raffa <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1985)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Berryman</surname><given-names>AA</given-names></name><name><surname>Simasko</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Teal</surname><given-names>W</given-names></name><name><surname>Wong</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effects of grand fir monoterpenes on the fir engraver <italic>Scolytus ventralis</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae) and its symbiotic fungus</article-title><source>Environmental Entomology</source><year>1985</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>552</fpage><lpage>556</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-46"><label>Rebek, Herms &#x00026; Smitley (2008)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rebek</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Herms</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Smitley</surname><given-names>DR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interspecific variation in resistance to emerald ash borer (Coleoptera: Buprestidae) among North American and Asian ash (<italic>Fraxinus</italic> spp.)</article-title><source>Environmental Entomology</source><year>2008</year><volume>37</volume><fpage>242</fpage><lpage>246</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1603/0046-225X(2008)37[242:IVIRTE]2.0.CO;2</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18348816</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-47"><label>Renwick, Hughes &#x00026; Krull (1976)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Renwick</surname><given-names>JAA</given-names></name><name><surname>Hughes</surname><given-names>PR</given-names></name><name><surname>Krull</surname><given-names>IS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Selective production of <italic>cis</italic>- and <italic>trans</italic>-verbenol from (&#x02212;)- and (+)-<italic>&#x003b1;</italic>-pinene by a bark beetle</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1976</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>199</fpage><lpage>201</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1246609</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1246609</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-48"><label>Rudinsky (1962)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Rudinsky</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ecology of scolytidae</article-title><source>Annual Review of Entomology</source><year>1962</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>327</fpage><lpage>348</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.en.07.010162.001551</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-49"><label>Safranyik &#x00026; Carroll (2006)</label><element-citation publication-type="book"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safranyik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name></person-group><person-group person-group-type="editor"><name><surname>Safranyik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Wilson</surname><given-names>WR</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The biology and epidemiology of the mountain pine beetle in lodgepole pine forests</article-title><source>The mountain pine beetle: A synthesis of biology, management, and impacts on lodgepole pine</source><year>2006</year><publisher-loc>Victoria, British Columbia</publisher-loc><publisher-name>Natural Resources Canada, Canadian Forest Service, Pacific Forestry Centre</publisher-name><fpage>3</fpage><lpage>66</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-50"><label>Safranyik &#x00026; Linton (1982)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safranyik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Linton</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Survival and development of mountain pine beetle broods in jack pine bolts from Ontario</article-title><source>Canadian Forestry Service Research Notes</source><year>1982</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>17</fpage><lpage>18</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-51"><label>Safranyik <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (2010)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Safranyik</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Carroll</surname><given-names>AL</given-names></name><name><surname>R&#x000e9;gni&#x000e8;re</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Langor</surname><given-names>DW</given-names></name><name><surname>Riel</surname><given-names>WG</given-names></name><name><surname>Shorem</surname><given-names>TL</given-names></name><name><surname>Peter</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Cooke</surname><given-names>BJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Nealis</surname><given-names>VG</given-names></name><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SW</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Potential for range expansion of mountain pine beetle into the boreal forest of North America</article-title><source>The Canadian Entomologist</source><year>2010</year><volume>142</volume><fpage>415</fpage><lpage>442</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.4039/n08-CPA01</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-52"><label>Seybold (1993)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Seybold</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Role of chirality in olfactory-directed behavior: Aggregation of pine engraver beetles in the genus <italic>Ips</italic> (Coleoptera: Scolytidae)</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>1993</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>1809</fpage><lpage>1831</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00982310</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24249243</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-53"><label>Shrimpton (1973)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Shrimpton</surname><given-names>DM</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Extractives associated with wound response of lodgepole pine attacked by the mountain pine beetle and associated microorganisms</article-title><source>Canadian Journal of Botany</source><year>1973</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>527</fpage><lpage>534</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/b73-064</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-54"><label>Smith (1961)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The fumigant toxicity of three pine resins to Dendroctonus brevicomis and <italic>D. Jeffreyi</italic></article-title><source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source><year>1961</year><volume>54</volume><fpage>365</fpage><lpage>369</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-55"><label>Smith (1963)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Toxicity of pine resin vapors to three species of Dendroctonus bark beetles</article-title><source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source><year>1963</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>827</fpage><lpage>831</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-56"><label>Smith (1965)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Effect of monoterpene vapors on the western pine beetle</article-title><source>Journal of Economic Entomology</source><year>1965</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>509</fpage><lpage>510</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-57"><label>Smith (1983)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Smith</surname><given-names>RH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoterpenes of lodgepole pine xylem resin: a regional study in Western United States</article-title><source>Forest Science</source><year>1983</year><volume>29</volume><fpage>333</fpage><lpage>340</lpage></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-58"><label>Wallin &#x00026; Raffa (1999)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wallin</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name><name><surname>Raffa</surname><given-names>KF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Altered constitutive and inducible phloem monoterpenes following natural defoliation of jack pine: Implications to host mediated interguild interactions and plant defense theories</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>1999</year><volume>25</volume><fpage>861</fpage><lpage>880</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1020853019309</pub-id></element-citation></ref><ref id="ref-59"><label>Whitehead <italic>et&#x000a0;al.</italic> (1989)</label><element-citation publication-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Whitehead</surname><given-names>AT</given-names></name><name><surname>Scott</surname><given-names>DT</given-names></name><name><surname>Schmitz</surname><given-names>RF</given-names></name><name><surname>Mori</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Electroantennograms by mountain pine beetles, <italic>Dendroctonus ponderosae</italic> Hopkins, exposed to selected chiral semiochemicals</article-title><source>Journal of Chemical Ecology</source><year>1989</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>2089</fpage><lpage>209</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01207440</pub-id><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">24272298</pub-id></element-citation></ref></ref-list></back></article>